<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><OAI-PMH
	xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd"><responseDate>2018-08-02T07:42:59Z</responseDate><request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:4547424" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request><GetRecord><record><header><identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:4547424</identifier><datestamp>2015-08-25</datestamp><setSpec>chiadpsymeh</setSpec><setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec></header><metadata><article xmlns="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.0/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.0/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1.xsd" article-type="research-article">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Child Adolesc Psychiatry Ment Health</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Child Adolesc Psychiatry Ment Health</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Child and Adolescent Psychiatry and Mental Health</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1753-2000</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC4547424</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4547424</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">4547424</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26306098</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">77</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13034-015-0077-0</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Research Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Positive parenting: a randomised controlled trial evaluation of the Parents Plus Adolescent Programme in schools</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Nitsch</surname>
            <given-names>Eileen</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <email>nitsch@eircom.net</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Hannon</surname>
            <given-names>Geraldine</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <email>geraldine.hannon@ucdconnect.ie</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Rickard</surname>
            <given-names>Eóin</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <email>rickarde@tcd.ie</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Houghton</surname>
            <given-names>Sharon</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <email>sharon.houghton@ul.ie</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Sharry</surname>
            <given-names>John</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <email>john.sharry@gmail.com</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2"/>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="Aff1"><label/>University of Limerick, Limerick, Ireland </aff>
        <aff id="Aff2"><label/>Parents Plus Charity, ℅ Mater Hospital, 15 St Vincent Street North, Dublin 7, Ireland </aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>25</day>
        <month>8</month>
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
        <day>25</day>
        <month>8</month>
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>9</volume>
      <elocation-id>43</elocation-id>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>18</day>
          <month>8</month>
          <year>2014</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>13</day>
          <month>8</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>© Nitsch et al. 2015</copyright-statement>
        <license license-type="OpenAccess">
          <license-p>
<bold>Open Access</bold>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract id="Abs1">
        <sec>
          <title>Background</title>
          <p>The aim of this study was to evaluate the Parents Plus Adolescents Programme (PPAP)—a parent training course specifically targeting parents of young adolescents (aged 11–16 years)—when delivered as a preventative programme in community school settings.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Methods</title>
          <p>A sample of 126 parents (mean age of children = 12.34 years; range = 10–16 years) were randomly assigned to either a treatment (PPAP; <italic>n</italic> = 82) or a waiting-list control condition (WC; <italic>n</italic> = 44). Analyses are based on a study-completer sample post-treatment (n = 109 parents: PPAP n = 70; WC n = 39) and sample at 6 month follow up (n = 42 parents).</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Results</title>
          <p>Both post-treatment (between groups) and 6-month follow-up comparisons of study completers (within PPAP group) revealed significant positive effects of the parenting intervention with respect to adolescent behaviour problems and parenting stress. The post treatment comparisons demonstrated large effect sizes on global measures of child difficulties (partial eta squared = 0.15) and self-reported parent stress (partial eta squared = 0.22); there was a moderate effect size on the self-reported parent satisfaction (partial eta squared = 0.13).</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Conclusions</title>
          <p>This study provides preliminary evidence that PPAP may be an effective model of parent-training implemented in a community-based setting. The strengths and limitations of the study are discussed.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <custom-meta-group>
        <custom-meta>
          <meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name>
          <meta-value>© The Author(s) 2015</meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="Sec1">
      <title>Background</title>
      <p>Antisocial behaviour in young people is a growing problem. In the US and UK, 5–10 % of children aged 5–15 years present with clinically significant conduct disorders [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>], while adolescent risk 
behaviour is deemed a persistent problem and a significant cause of youth morbidity and mortality [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. Behaviour problems in adolescence are costly, due to the trauma and psychological problems caused to others who are victims of crime, aggression, or bullying, together with the financial costs to services for treatment of both the condition and its long-term sequelae. Use of health, social, education, and legal services is ten times higher for this population, and this usage is mostly borne by publicly funded services, especially in areas of social exclusion [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. A UK study conducted by Scott, Knapp, Henderson, and Maughan [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>] suggested that, by age 28 years, the costs of individuals with a clinical diagnosis of conduct disorder were ten times higher than for those with no problems, and costs for those with conduct problems not meeting the diagnostic criteria were 3½ times higher.</p>
      <p>Overwhelmingly, the research literature confirms the strong and enduring influence of parenting practices on adolescents [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. Research has shown that poor parenting skills (e.g., harsh, authoritarian, disproportionately punitive, laissez-faire; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>] and inconsistent parenting strategies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>] can lead to undesirable outcomes in children and adolescents. These outcomes include behavioural and emotional problems [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>], externalising and internalising behaviours [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>], and decreased cognitive and academic development [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. Additionally, poor parenting skills have been linked with poorer self-regulation in children and adolescents [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>], use of aggression [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>], and severe behavioural problems that persist over time [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>].</p>
      <sec id="Sec2">
        <title>Parent training and adolescence</title>
        <p>Internationally, the majority of parenting interventions target pre-adolescent children [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>] with a smaller number targeting the needs of adolescents (e.g., the Triple P Teen programme [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>] and the Strengthening Families Programme [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]). Generally, parenting education is viewed as a valuable way of avoiding adolescent anti-social behaviour and, therefore, more costly interventions in the future [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. Indeed, there is a body of research suggesting that early intervention with parents (e.g., starting in infancy or early childhood) can be effective in reducing adolescent behaviour problems [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>].</p>
        <p>There are, however, several reasons for developing and utilising adolescent-specific parenting programmes. Not all families successfully engage in parenting programmes when children are younger, and only seek help during their adolescence. Even parents who have attended previous courses may need to re-attend during adolescence to tackle the emergence of new problems. Moreover, adolescence brings with it a range of new developmental and social challenges that are not present or relevant when children are young (e.g., alcohol use). Discipline strategies will also necessarily change during the adolescent period, with strategies that were effective with younger children no longer effective or developmentally desirable. Certainly, research has shown that for parenting programmes to be effective they must be developmentally timed to be relevant to the parent’s needs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>].</p>
        <p>Given the evidence confirming the strong and enduring influences of parenting practices on adolescents, there is a great need for increased accessibility to community-based parent-training programmes targeted at the needs of adolescents. In addition, corresponding evaluations of these programmes need to be conducted to determine their effectiveness, given the potential challenges of this age group and the possibility that problems may be more fixed and less amenable to change.</p>
        <p>In relation to the delivery of such a programme, schools have been identified as a natural, suitable, and, in some cases, preferred location for the provision of mental health services [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>], with the benefits of basing preventative and intervention programmes in the school setting being well-established (e.g., Lean and Corlucci [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>], Van Acker and Mayer [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]). In the US, for example, it has been reported that 75 % of children and adolescents who receive mental health services do so through their schools [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>].</p>
        <p>Furthermore, it has frequently been reported that the period during and after the transition from primary to post-primary school can be extremely challenging for young people [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>], with a reported increase in behavioural [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>], academic [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>], and discipline problems [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>] accompanying the change. Factors such as the onset of puberty [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>], concern about knowing the new rules/procedures of the school [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>], and secondary school being a more intimidating environment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>] have all being identified as stressors during this period. Given the apparent increased likelihood of difficulties occurring in the transition to secondary school, it was decided to specifically target this time period in the current research, with schools being chosen as the location for the roll-out of the Parents Plus Adolescents Programme (PPAP), as an extension of previous research evaluations of the PPAP.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec3">
        <title>Parents Plus Adolescents Programme</title>
        <p>The PPAP [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>] is a group-based training intervention for parents of young adolescents aged 11–16 years. It is one of three Parents Plus Programmes targeting different age groups, with corresponding programmes for primary school [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>] and preschool children [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>].</p>
        <p>Like international programmes such as Triple P Teen [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>] and Strengthening Families [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>], the PPAP draws largely from a social learning theoretical background, but also incorporates ideas from conflict management and negotiation models [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>] and discipline strategies from Parent Effectiveness Training [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. The PPAP differs from the international programmes in that the programme materials and DVD footage was developed with Irish parents and teenagers and the delivery of the programme draws from a solution-focused and strengths-based collaborative approach to working with families [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]. In addition the PPAP facilitators use parent evaluations of sessions, which are not anonymised, to tailor the delivery of the programme to the specific group of parents attending and to be proactive in guarding against attrition by speaking with parents who are not satisfied with the programme.</p>
        <p>The PPAP includes two DVDs, a facilitator’s manual, and an accompanying parent handbook. The manual contains extensive background information, a guide on how to prepare and run each session, and hand-outs and home-work assignments for participants. The DVDs contain 2 h footage of both acted and real scenes of parenting situations.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec4">
        <title>Programme content</title>
        <p>The central philosophy in each group session is balance. The aim each week is to introduce one positive parenting idea (e.g., listening) and one discipline/behaviour management idea (e.g., using consequences), giving parents two new ideas to reflect on and practice. This makes the course positive and preventative, while also tackling the behaviour problems that parents are concerned about. An outline of the topics covered over the 8 weeks is seen in Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>. While some of the topics covered in PPAP are similar to the original programme aimed at parents of younger children (e.g., social learning principles), there are also a number of differences. For example, in the PPAP the skills of connecting, relationship building and problem solving covered in Sessions 1–7 are specific to an adolescent’s stage of development who is in the process of becoming independent from the family.<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Overview of PPAP course content</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Session</th><th align="left">Content</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Session 1</td><td align="left">Introduction to course</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Positive communication</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Session 2</td><td align="left">Getting to know your teenager</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Communicating rules positively</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Session 3</td><td align="left">Connecting with your teenager</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Communicating rules positively</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Session 4</td><td align="left">Encouraging your teenager</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Using consequences</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Session 5</td><td align="left">Listening to your teenager</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Having a discipline plan</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Session 6</td><td align="left">Empowering teenagers</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Dealing with conflict and aggression</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Session 7</td><td align="left">Problem solving with young people</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Dealing with specific issues</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3">Session 8</td><td align="left">Dealing with specific issues</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Parental self-care</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Closing and course evaluation</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec5">
        <title>Parents Plus research basis and the evidence-base for parent management training in adolescence</title>
        <p>There are currently 12 published studies providing evidence for the effectiveness of the Parents Plus Programmes in reducing behavioural problems and parental stress in a variety of contexts and with a variety of age groups (e.g., [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]).</p>
        <p>For example, in a large-scale, multisite controlled study of children aged 1–6 years (<italic>N</italic> = 97), findings indicated that parents completing the Parents Plus programme reported significant decreases in child problem behaviour and parental stress, a reduction in commands, and an increase in positive attends in the parent–child interaction post-intervention [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]. Additionally, no significant difference in benefit was identified between children with developmental delays and children with primarily behaviour problems, suggesting that the PPEY may be equally beneficial to both groups and could be used as broad-based intervention in child mental health services [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>].</p>
        <p>Though there are less studies, research evidence supports the efficacy of parent management training in adolescence. In particular, there is a growing body of evidence for the effectiveness of international Parenting Programmes targeting teens such as Teen Triple P [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>] and the Strengthening Families Programme [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>].</p>
        <p>There has been one previous small controlled evaluation of the PPAP in an adolescent mental health setting with 55 families indicated that, compared to wait-list controls, parents completing the PPAP reported higher goal attainment, greater improvements in their relationship with their child, and a reduction in behavioural difficulties (i.e., improvements on the SDQ Total Difficulties scale, and Peer and Conduct subscales) when compared to waiting-list control group [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>].</p>
        <p>The overall aim of the current study is to expand upon this research by examining the effectiveness of the Parents Plus Adolescents Programme as a preventive programme for parents of children in the process of transition to second level schooling. The primary outcome expected was that there would be a reduction in any child emotional and behaviour problems, which would be both statistically and clinically significant. Positive outcomes for parents in terms of increased parents satisfaction and reduced parental stress are also expected after attendance at the eight-week programme and subsequent improvements are expected to be maintained at six-month follow-up. We also included a parent-report measure to evaluate parent’s attainment of personal goals and parent-defined goals for their child identified prior to starting the programme.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec6" sec-type="methods">
      <title>Methods</title>
      <sec id="Sec7">
        <title>Study design</title>
        <p>This study utilised a Randomised Controlled Trial (RCT) design, in which 126 parents were randomly assigned to one of two conditions: PPAP or a waiting-list control group. The waiting-list control group did not receive any intervention during the wait period and were enrolled in the subsequent PPAP programme. Assessments were conducted prior to programme delivery (Time 1), immediately after programme delivery (Time 2), and at six-month follow-up (Time 3). The waiting-list control group completed assessments at the pre- and post-assessment stages only (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>).<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>PPAP RCT participant flow</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13034_2015_77_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec8">
        <title>Procedure</title>
        <p>The study received ethical approval from the Research Ethics Committee of the University of Limerick, Ireland. The study was undertaken from September 2009 to September 2010. The PPAP was delivered in primary and post-primary schools throughout counties Cork and Kerry in the Republic of Ireland. As part of a county-wide initiative to support adolescents transitioning from primary to post-primary schools, families with children in the last year of primary school and the first year of secondary school were particularly targeted. Schools whose principals expressed an interest were selected for participation, dependent on the availability of locally trained community facilitators. Participant enrolment was conducted by the staff at each school.</p>
        <p>In order to recruit parents, promotional materials were provided to participating schools and information letters sent to all parents. The PPAP information evenings were also advertised in local communities via notices in local newspapers and newsletters. As the programme was implemented as a preventative group, an open recruitment strategy was used, and the only mandatory inclusion criterion was that the child of concern to the parent was between 10 and 16 years. Sample size was thus determined by the number of parents who were willing and able to take part.</p>
        <p>An information evening was held at participating schools where the PPAP was introduced and explained. Parents who expressed an interest in attending the parenting programme were also invited to take part in the study and those who agreed completed a consent form and the set of standardised assessment measures. The inclusion criterion for was that children were aged 10–16 years; there were no specific exclusion criteria. At the end of the information session the primary researcher then randomly allocated participating parents to either the PPAP group or WC group by assigning sequentially numbered envelopes, with those allocated to the WC condition made aware that they would be participating in the subsequent PPAP group. Randomisation was done on a 2:1 basis. The rationale for choosing a 2:1 ratio was to increase the number of treatment groups and thus increase the study’s power for a fixed total sample size. In addition, a high drop-out rate was anticipated. As this study was a waiting-list controlled RCT, participants, care providers, and those assessing outcomes were aware of which experimental group they had been assigned to after random allocation.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec9">
        <title>PPAP and programme facilitators</title>
        <p>All participants in the treatment group attended one of ten Parents Plus Adolescent Programmes (PPAP) thus receiving the same 8 week video-modelling parenting intervention. Each group was delivered by two facilitators. The main facilitator for each group was experienced in delivering the PPAP, and co-facilitators for each group underwent an intensive 2-day facilitators training course, delivered by the programme authors, prior to programme implementation. All facilitators had a professional background in health or education. Treatment fidelity and integrity was adhered to via the use of a manualised programme. Facilitators completed adherence checklists at the end of each group session, and also attended a small group supervision sessions with other facilitators during the group delivery.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec10">
        <title>Participants and attrition</title>
        <p>Participants recruited at baseline were 126 parents who were randomly assigned to either the PPAP group (<italic>n</italic> = 82) or the Waiting-list Control (WC) group (<italic>n</italic> = 44). Only one parent per family participated in the study. Parents who attended five or more of the eight parenting sessions were included in the final analyses. Of the 126 parents, a total of n = 109 (86.5 %) completed Time 2 measurements. This figure included 85.4 % (n = 70) of the PPAP Group and 88.6 % (n = 39) of the WC group. The remaining 13.5 % (n = 12) of participants in the PPAP Group did not complete Time 2 measurements because they dropped out of the PPAP. The remaining 13.6 % (n = 5) of the WC group also dropped out of the study. Data from dropouts were excluded from the final analysis.</p>
        <p>The young people of concern to the parents who completed the PPAP had a mean age of 12.34 years (SD = 1.36; range 10–16 years) and the majority were female (61 %, n = 66 vs. Male: 39 %, n = 43). In the PPAP Group, 10 % of the children were receiving a clinical service compared with 8 % in the WC group. These clinical services included Occupational Therapy, Speech and Language Therapy, Psychology and Cardiology. Statistical analysis demonstrated no significant difference between the groups based on this variable. The demographic characteristics of the parents and their children in the PPAP group and the WC groups are presented in Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>.<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Demographic information</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2">Variable</th><th align="left" colspan="2">PPAP group (<italic>n</italic> = 70)</th><th align="left" colspan="2">WC group (<italic>n</italic> = 39)</th></tr><tr><th align="left">
<italic>N</italic>
</th><th align="left">%</th><th align="left">
<italic>N</italic>
</th><th align="left">%</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="5">Parents</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5"> Parent type<sup>a</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">  Mother</td><td char="." align="char">61</td><td char="." align="char">87</td><td char="." align="char">32</td><td char="." align="char">82</td></tr><tr><td align="left">  Father</td><td char="." align="char">9</td><td char="." align="char">13</td><td char="." align="char">6</td><td char="." align="char">15</td></tr><tr><td align="left">  Foster Mother</td><td align="left">–</td><td align="left">–</td><td char="." align="char">1</td><td char="." align="char">3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5"> Mothers’ employment status</td></tr><tr><td align="left">  Public sector</td><td char="." align="char">22</td><td char="." align="char">36</td><td char="." align="char">16</td><td char="." align="char">50</td></tr><tr><td align="left">  Private sector</td><td char="." align="char">6</td><td char="." align="char">10</td><td align="left">–</td><td align="left">–</td></tr><tr><td align="left">  Health service</td><td char="." align="char">3</td><td char="." align="char">5</td><td char="." align="char">6</td><td char="." align="char">19</td></tr><tr><td align="left">  Full-time homemaker</td><td char="." align="char">28</td><td char="." align="char">46</td><td char="." align="char">11</td><td char="." align="char">31</td></tr><tr><td align="left">  Student</td><td char="." align="char">2</td><td char="." align="char">3</td><td align="left">–</td><td align="left">–</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5"> Fathers’ employment status</td></tr><tr><td align="left">  Public sector</td><td char="." align="char">7</td><td char="." align="char">78</td><td char="." align="char">2</td><td char="." align="char">34</td></tr><tr><td align="left">  Full-time homemaker</td><td char="." align="char">2</td><td char="." align="char">22</td><td char="." align="char">2</td><td char="." align="char">33</td></tr><tr><td align="left">  Health service</td><td align="left">–</td><td align="left">–</td><td char="." align="char">2</td><td char="." align="char">33</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5">Children</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5"> Gender</td></tr><tr><td align="left">  Male</td><td char="." align="char">27</td><td char="." align="char">39</td><td char="." align="char">16</td><td char="." align="char">41</td></tr><tr><td align="left">  Female</td><td char="." align="char">43</td><td char="." align="char">61</td><td char="." align="char">23</td><td char="." align="char">59</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5"> Receiving a Clinical Service (educational, speech and language, psychological, etc.)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">  Yes</td><td char="." align="char">7</td><td char="." align="char">7</td><td char="." align="char">3</td><td char="." align="char">8</td></tr><tr><td align="left">  No</td><td char="." align="char">63</td><td char="." align="char">63</td><td char="." align="char">36</td><td char="." align="char">92</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>
<sup>a</sup>Only one parent per family participated in the study</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
        <p>The intervention group was followed up after 6 months. The attrition rate from the PPAP Group at 6 month follow up was 49 % (n = 40 parents), with n = 42 parents providing follow up data. Descriptive data indicate that the parents (n = 28) who dropped out between Time 2 and Time 3 (6-month follow up) obtained higher mean Total Difficulties Score on the SDQ at Time 2 compared with parents (n = 42) who completed outcome measures at Time 3. These parents (n = 28), who were lost to follow up at Time 3, also reported lower levels of satisfaction with the parenting role at Time 2, although there was only a one point difference between the groups on the self-report satisfaction measure; they also reported lower levels of parenting stress compared with study completers. Of note is that these differences reported on post intervention measures were not statistically significant.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec11">
        <title>Instruments</title>
        <sec id="Sec112">
          <title>Demographic Questionnaire</title>
          <p>The Demographic Questionnaire was developed specifically for the current evaluation study. This instrument was designed to gather family demographic information including contact details, marital and employment status.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="Sec113">
          <title>Strengths and Difficulties Questionnaire</title>
          <p><italic>(SDQ)</italic> The SDQ [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>] is a 25-item behavioural screening inventory, which asks parents about pro-social and difficult behaviour in children aged 4–16 years. It consists of five subscales (Emotional Problems; Conduct Problems; Hyperactivity; Peer Problems; and Prosocial behaviour), each with five items. A Total Difficulties Score is derived from the combined scores of the first four scales, and a score of 17 or above is in the ‘abnormal’ range. The subscales have a mean internal consistency reliability coefficient of 0.71, mean test–retest reliability co-efficient over 6 months of 0.62, and strong criterion validity for predicting psychological disorders [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>]. The Cronbach’s alpha coefficient in the current study was 0.81 for the Total Difficulties scale, and &gt;0.7 for the Hyperactivity, Emotional Problems, and Prosocial subscales. The reliability coefficient for the Conduct Problems subscale was 0.51, while Peer Problems yielded an alpha of 0.69.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="Sec114">
          <title>Parenting Stress Index–Short Form (PSI/SF)</title>
          <p>This measure is a direct derivative of the full-length (120 item) test and consists of a 36-item parent report scale, with a 5-point Likert response format [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>]. The scale yields a total parenting stress score on three 12-item subscales: Parental Distress; Difficult Child; and Parent–Child Dysfunctional Interaction. As the majority of children of participants (74 %) in the current study were aged 12 years or under, the 0–12 years version of the PSI/SF was used. The total scale and subscales of the PSI/SF have been found to have internal consistency reliability coefficients above 0.9 and test–retest reliability coefficients of between 0.65 and 0.96 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>]. The alpha coefficient in the current study was 0.88 for the Total Parenting Stress subscale and 0.81 for the Parental Distress and Difficult Child subscales, while the Parent–Child Dysfunctional Interaction subscale yielded an alpha value of 0.77.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="Sec115">
          <title>Kansas Parenting Satisfaction Scale (KPSS)</title>
          <p>This is a 3-item instrument designed to measure an individual’s satisfaction with themselves as a parent, the behaviour of their children, and their relationship with their children [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>]. A 7-point Likert response scale is used, and the scores for all three items are summed to yield a total parenting satisfaction score. The KPSS has been found to have internal consistency reliability coefficients ranging from 0.78 to 0.95 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>]. The alpha coefficient for the KPSS in the current study was 0.82.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="Sec116">
          <title>Parents Plus Goal Form</title>
          <p>The Parents Plus Goal Form was designed by the authors of the Parents Plus Programmes in order to (1) evaluate attainment of target goals that parents identify in relation to their child; and (2) evaluate parent’s attainment of personal goals identified prior to starting the programme. A visual analogue scale was used to measure parents’ rating of goal attainment, and they listed two goals for themselves and two for their child. Parents indicated how far they and their child were, at the time of completion, from achieving each goal by rating it from 0 to 10 on the analogue scale, where 0 is ‘very far away from goal’ and 10 is ‘have reached this goal’. A mean goal score is calculated, again ranging from 0 to 10. At subsequent data collection times (each week and at Time 2 and Time 3 data collection) parents reviewed their initial goals and indicated how close they and their child now were to achieving their goals. Examples of common goals reported by parents on the PPGF can be seen in Table <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>.<table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Examples of goals stated by parents on the PPGF at pre-intervention</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Goals for their child</th><th align="left">Goals for themselves</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">To confide more in their parents</td><td align="left">To have better awareness of possible conflict</td></tr><tr><td align="left">To be more independent</td><td align="left">To stop losing my temper so quickly</td></tr><tr><td align="left">To understand and accept boundaries</td><td align="left">To be able to listen more</td></tr><tr><td align="left">To have a more positive relationship with us</td><td align="left">To be less critical and more accepting of my child</td></tr><tr><td align="left">To communicate problems better</td><td align="left">To better deal with conflict</td></tr><tr><td align="left">To have more confidence in themselves</td><td align="left">To be more patient</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec12">
        <title>Analyses</title>
        <p>Data were analysed using the PASW Statistics 18 package for Windows. Prior to analyses all variables were examined for accuracy of data entry, missing values, presence of outliers, and normality of distribution. Inspection of the distribution of scores on the continuous dependent variables showed that the scores were reasonably normally distributed.</p>
        <p>Descriptive statistics: namely; percentages, means, frequencies and standard deviations were computed for demographic variables. We also tested for differences between the PPAP and WC groups on parent and child demographic characteristics and Time 1 scores on the standardised outcome measures using independent samples t tests and Chi square tests. In order to reduce the risk of obtaining a Type 1 error, a more stringent alpha value was set at 0.003 (Bonferroni adjustment).</p>
        <p>One-way repeated measures analysis of variance (ANOVA) was used to examine change over time (Time 1–3) for the intervention group on standardized measures. Where significant differences were found in the one-way ANOVAs across the three time stages, paired-samples t-tests were employed in order to illuminate the nature of observed differences in mean scores.</p>
        <p>A series of mixed ANOVAs were used to test for interactions between time (Time 1 and Time 2) and group (PPAP and WC) on the same standardized measures. Where significant interactions were observed tests of simple effects were carried out to further examine the nature of the interactions. Effect sizes were evaluated in accordance with Cohen’s (1998) guidelines: 0.01 = Small effect, 0.06 = Moderate effect, 0.14 = Large effect.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec13" sec-type="results">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="Sec14">
        <title>Preliminary analyses</title>
        <p>Results of independent samples t tests and Chi squared analyses on parent and child demographic characteristics at study entry showed no significant differences between the PPAP and WC groups at study entry for any variable.</p>
        <p>Independent-samples t tests also revealed no significant difference in scores between the two groups for any of the measures administered to participants at Time 1 (see Table <xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>), with the exception of the Emotional Symptoms subscale of the SDQ, where the mean score for the PPAP group (<italic>M</italic> = 3.93, SD = 2.41) was found to be significantly higher than the WC group (<italic>M</italic> = 2.56, SD = 2.10). As the overall Total Difficulties score for the SDQ did not significantly differ between the groups, this aspect is not critical, but findings for this individual subscale should be interpreted with caution.<table-wrap id="Tab4"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Independent t test results for all assessments administered at Time 1 (<italic>N</italic> = 109)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Scale</th><th align="left">
<italic>t</italic>
</th><th align="left">
<italic>p</italic>
</th><th align="left">
<italic>η</italic>
<sup>2</sup>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="4">SDQ</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> TD</td><td align="left">
<italic>t</italic> (107) = 0.92</td><td char="." align="char">0.360</td><td char="." align="char">0.008</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> HYP</td><td align="left">_<sup>a</sup>
</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left"> CON</td><td align="left">
<italic>t</italic> (107) = -0.53</td><td char="." align="char">0.596</td><td char="." align="char">0.003</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> EMOT</td><td align="left">
<italic>t</italic> (107) = 2.96</td><td char="." align="char">0.004*</td><td char="." align="char">0.075</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> PEER</td><td align="left">
<italic>t</italic> (107) = 1.01</td><td char="." align="char">0.317</td><td char="." align="char">0.009</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> PRO</td><td align="left">
<italic>t</italic> (107) = 0.65</td><td char="." align="char">0.515</td><td char="." align="char">0.004</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4">PSI</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> PSI total</td><td align="left">
<italic>t</italic> (107) = 1.99</td><td char="." align="char">0.054</td><td char="." align="char">0.036</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> PD</td><td align="left">
<italic>t</italic> (107) = −0.85</td><td char="." align="char">0.399</td><td char="." align="char">0.007</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> DC</td><td align="left">
<italic>t</italic> (107) = 1.15</td><td char="." align="char">0.253</td><td char="." align="char">0.012</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> CDI</td><td align="left">
<italic>t</italic> (107) = 0.71</td><td char="." align="char">0.479</td><td char="." align="char">0.005</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4">Parent-Defined Goals</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> PDPG</td><td align="left">
<italic>t</italic> (107) = −0.88</td><td char="." align="char">0.379</td><td char="." align="char">0.007</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> PDCG</td><td align="left">
<italic>t</italic> (107) = 1.07</td><td char="." align="char">0.287</td><td char="." align="char">0.010</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4">KPSS</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> KPSS total</td><td align="left">t (107) = 0.798</td><td char="." align="char">0.427</td><td char="." align="char">0.006</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>
<italic>SDQ</italic> Strengths and Difficulties Questionnaire, <italic>TD</italic> Total Difficulties, <italic>EMOT</italic> Emotional Symptoms, <italic>HYPER</italic> Hyperactivity, <italic>CON</italic> Conduct Problems, <italic>PEER</italic> Peer Problems, <italic>PRO</italic> prosocial behavior, <italic>PSI</italic> Parenting Stress Index, <italic>PSI total</italic> total stress, <italic>PD</italic> parental distress, <italic>DC</italic> Difficult Child, <italic>P-CDI</italic> Parent–Child dysfunctional interaction, <italic>KPSS</italic> Kansas Parenting Satisfaction Scale, <italic>KPSS total</italic> KPSS total parenting satisfaction, <italic>PDCG</italic> Parent-Defined Child Goals, <italic>PDPG</italic> Parent-Defined Personal Goals</p><p>* <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05</p><p>
<sup>a</sup>Given that no higher order effects were observed for the SDQ-Hyperactivity subscale the main effects detected for them can be reported. No main effect for group was observed for this subscale</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec15">
        <title>Comparison of means of assessment measures for the PPAP and WC groups</title>
        <p>Treatment effects observed for the PPAP group were compared with the WC group. Because there was no data collected for the WC group at Time 3, only Time 1 and Time 2 data were considered. In order to explore for Group × Time interactions, Time effects, and Group effects, each dependent variable was analysed using a two-way ANOVA.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec16">
        <title>ANOVA results for SDQ, PSI/SF, KPSS, and PDGF</title>
        <p>Change over time for the PPAP and WC groups was examined across the dependent measures, SDQ, PSI/SF, KPSS, and PDGF. The means and standard deviations for the PPAP and WC groups at Time 1 and Time 2 for each of the standardised scales are presented in Table <xref rid="Tab5" ref-type="table">5</xref>.<table-wrap id="Tab5"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Mean scores for PPAP and WC groups on SDQ, PSI, and KPSS scales across Time 1 and Time 2 (standard deviations in parentheses)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2">Scale</th><th align="left" colspan="2">PPAP group (n = 70)</th><th align="left" colspan="2">WC group (n = 39)</th></tr><tr><th align="left">Time 1</th><th align="left">Time 2</th><th align="left">Time 1</th><th align="left">Time 2</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="5">SDQ</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> TD</td><td char="(" align="char">11.97 (5.96)</td><td char="(" align="char">5.70 (4.13)</td><td char="(" align="char">10.82 (6.78)</td><td char="(" align="char">10.92 (6.80)</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> HYP</td><td char="(" align="char">3.33 (2.28)</td><td char="(" align="char">2.86 (1.84)</td><td char="(" align="char">3.79 (2.76)</td><td char="(" align="char">3.90 (2.69)</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> CON</td><td char="(" align="char">2.30 (1.61)</td><td char="(" align="char">0.886 (1.09)</td><td char="(" align="char">2.49 (2.01)</td><td char="(" align="char">2.38 (2.16)</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> EMO</td><td char="(" align="char">3.93 (2.41)</td><td char="(" align="char">0.986 (1.62)</td><td char="(" align="char">2.5 (2.10)</td><td char="(" align="char">2.56 (1.94)</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> PEER</td><td char="(" align="char">2.41 (2.26)</td><td char="(" align="char">0.971 (1.44)</td><td char="(" align="char">1.97 (2.07)</td><td char="(" align="char">2.08 (1.91)</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> PRO</td><td char="(" align="char">6.90 (2.53)</td><td char="(" align="char">8.33 (1.63)</td><td char="(" align="char">7.21 (1.94)</td><td char="(" align="char">7.38 (1.94)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5">PSI</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> PSI total</td><td char="(" align="char">77.97 (14.69)</td><td char="(" align="char">65.87 (14.39)</td><td char="(" align="char">84.10 (18.13)</td><td char="(" align="char">83.95 (19.44)</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> PD</td><td char="(" align="char">28.17 (7.65)</td><td char="(" align="char">21.59 (6.36)</td><td char="(" align="char">29.46 (7.57)</td><td char="(" align="char">28.97 (8.45)</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> DC</td><td char="(" align="char">30.71 (7.66)</td><td char="(" align="char">23.21 (6.25)</td><td char="(" align="char">28.95 (7.71)</td><td char="(" align="char">29.41 (7.96)</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> PSI-P-CDI</td><td char="(" align="char">26.16 (6.34)</td><td char="(" align="char">21.07 (5.01)</td><td char="(" align="char">25.23 (6.85)</td><td char="(" align="char">25.56 (6.84)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5">KPSS</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> KPSS total</td><td char="(" align="char">14.23 (16.89)</td><td char="(" align="char">16.89 (2.36)</td><td char="(" align="char">13.72 (2.88)</td><td char="(" align="char">13.62 (3.08)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5">Parent-Defined Goals</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> PDCG</td><td char="(" align="char">3.97 (1.54)</td><td char="(" align="char">6.53 (1.42)</td><td char="(" align="char">4.31 (1.62)</td><td char="(" align="char">4.15 (1.66)</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> PDPG</td><td char="(" align="char">3.63 (1.48)</td><td char="(" align="char">6.93 (1.38)</td><td char="(" align="char">3.90 (1.60)</td><td char="(" align="char">3.87 (1.66)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>
<italic>SDQ</italic> Strengths and Difficulties Questionnaire, <italic>TD</italic> Total Difficulties, <italic>EMOT</italic> Emotional Symptoms, <italic>HYPER</italic> Hyperactivity, <italic>CON</italic> Conduct Problems, <italic>PEER</italic> Peer Problems, <italic>PRO</italic> prosocial behavior, <italic>PSI</italic> Parenting Stress Index, <italic>PSI total</italic> total stress, <italic>PD</italic> parental distress, <italic>DC</italic> Difficult Child, <italic>P-CDI</italic> Parent–Child dysfunctional interaction, <italic>KPSS</italic> Kansas Parenting Satisfaction Scale, <italic>KPSS total</italic> KPSS total parenting satisfaction, <italic>PDCG</italic> Parent-Defined Child Goals, <italic>PDPG</italic> Parent-Defined Personal Goals</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
        <p>Significant interaction effects were observed across parents’ mean scores for the Total Difficulties score and all subscales, with the exception of SDQ-Hyperactivity, and for parent-defined goals (see Table <xref rid="Tab6" ref-type="table">6</xref>).<table-wrap id="Tab6"><label>Table 6</label><caption><p>Mixed between-within ANOVA group, time, and interaction main effects for SDQ, PSI, and KPSS scales across the PPAP and WC groups</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2">Scale</th><th align="left" colspan="2">Group</th><th align="left" colspan="2">Time</th><th align="left" colspan="2">Interaction</th></tr><tr><th align="left">
<italic>F</italic>
</th><th align="left">
<italic>p</italic>
</th><th align="left">
<italic>F</italic>
</th><th align="left">
<italic>p</italic>
</th><th align="left">
<italic>F</italic>
</th><th align="left">
<italic>p</italic>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="7">SDQ</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> TD</td><td align="left">
<italic>F</italic> (1, 107) = 3.53</td><td char="." align="char">0.063</td><td align="left">
<italic>F</italic> (1, 107) = 60.01</td><td char="." align="char">&lt;0.001***</td><td align="left">
<italic>F</italic> (1, 107) = 64.07</td><td char="." align="char">&lt;0.001***</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> HYP</td><td align="left">
<italic>F</italic> (1, 107) = 3.28</td><td char="." align="char">0.073</td><td align="left">
<italic>F</italic> (1, 107) = 0.787</td><td char="." align="char">0.377</td><td align="left">
<italic>F</italic> (1, 107) = 1.91</td><td char="." align="char">0.170</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> CON</td><td align="left">
<italic>F</italic> (1, 107) = 7.98</td><td char="." align="char">0.006*</td><td align="left">
<italic>F</italic> (1, 107) = 26.74</td><td char="." align="char">&lt;0.001***</td><td align="left">
<italic>F</italic> (1, 107) = 19.98</td><td char="." align="char">&lt;0.001***</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> EMOT</td><td align="left">
<italic>F</italic> (1, 107) = 190.8</td><td char="." align="char">0.769</td><td align="left">
<italic>F</italic> (1, 107) = 62.76</td><td char="." align="char">&lt;0.001***</td><td align="left">
<italic>F</italic> (1, 107) = 62.76</td><td char="." align="char">&lt;0.001***</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> PEER</td><td align="left">
<italic>F</italic> (1, 107) = 0.895</td><td char="." align="char">0.346</td><td align="left">
<italic>F</italic> (1, 107) = 18.04</td><td char="." align="char">&lt;0.001***</td><td align="left">
<italic>F</italic> (1, 107) = 23.98</td><td char="." align="char">&lt;0.001***</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> PRO</td><td align="left">
<italic>F</italic> (1, 107) = 0.80</td><td char="." align="char">0.373</td><td align="left">
<italic>F</italic> (1, 107) = 15.23</td><td char="." align="char">&lt; 0.001***</td><td align="left">
<italic>F</italic> (1, 107) = 9.19</td><td char="." align="char">&lt;0.001***</td></tr><tr><td align="left">PSI</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left"> PSI total</td><td align="left">
<italic>F</italic> (1, 107) = 15.29</td><td char="." align="char">&lt;0.001***</td><td align="left">
<italic>F</italic> (1, 107) = 46.40</td><td char="." align="char">&lt;0.001***</td><td align="left">
<italic>F</italic> (1, 107) = 44.08</td><td char="." align="char">&lt;0.001***</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> PD</td><td align="left">
<italic>F</italic> (1, 107) = 9.87</td><td char="." align="char">&lt;0.001***</td><td align="left">
<italic>F</italic> (1, 107) = 45.04</td><td char="." align="char">&lt;0.001***</td><td align="left">
<italic>F</italic> (1, 107) = 33.48</td><td char="." align="char">&lt;0.001***</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> DC</td><td align="left">
<italic>F</italic> (1, 107) = 2.78</td><td char="." align="char">0.098</td><td align="left">
<italic>F</italic> (1, 107) = 33.55</td><td char="." align="char">&lt;0.001***</td><td align="left">
<italic>F</italic> (1, 107) = 42.93</td><td char="." align="char">&lt;0.001***</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> CDI</td><td align="left">
<italic>F</italic> (1, 107) = 2.59</td><td char="." align="char">0.111</td><td align="left">
<italic>F</italic> (1, 107) = 20.53</td><td char="." align="char">&lt;0.001***</td><td align="left">
<italic>F</italic> (1, 107) = 26.69</td><td char="." align="char">&lt;0.001***</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="7">KPSS</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> KPSS total</td><td align="left">
<italic>F</italic> (1, 107) = 11.96</td><td char="." align="char">&lt;0.001***</td><td align="left">
<italic>F</italic> (1, 107) = 36.03</td><td char="." align="char">&lt;0.001***</td><td align="left">
<italic>F</italic> (1, 107) = 42.05</td><td char="." align="char">&lt;0.001***</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>
<italic>SDQ</italic> Strengths and Difficulties Questionnaire, <italic>TD</italic> Total Difficulties, <italic>EMOT</italic> Emotional Symptoms, <italic>HYPER</italic> Hyperactivity, <italic>CON</italic> Conduct Problems, <italic>PEER</italic> Peer Problems, <italic>PRO</italic> prosocial behavior, <italic>PSI</italic> Parenting Stress Index, <italic>PSI total</italic> total stress, <italic>PD</italic> parental distress, <italic>DC</italic> Difficult Child, <italic>P-CDI</italic> Parent–Child dysfunctional interaction, <italic>KPSS</italic> Kansas Parenting Satisfaction Scale, <italic>KPSS total</italic> KPSS total parenting satisfaction</p><p>* Significant at <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05, *** significant at p &lt; 0.001</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec17">
        <title>Within-group outcomes for the PPAP Group</title>
        <p>A series of one-way repeated measures ANOVAs were used to evaluate changes in scores on parent measures from Time 1 (pre-intervention) to Time 2 (post-intervention) and Time 3 (at 6-month follow-up) within the PPAP group. The means, standard deviations, and main effects for time are displayed in Table <xref rid="Tab7" ref-type="table">7</xref>.<table-wrap id="Tab7"><label>Table 7</label><caption><p>Means, standard deviations (in parentheses), and repeated measures ANOVA time effects for PPAP Group</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Scale</th><th align="left">Time 1 (<italic>n</italic> = 70)</th><th align="left">Time 2 (<italic>n</italic> = 70)</th><th align="left">Time 3 (<italic>n</italic> = 42)</th><th align="left">ANOVA</th><th align="left">Partial <italic>η</italic>
<sup>2</sup>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="6">SDQ</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> TD</td><td char="(" align="char">11.97 (5.96)</td><td char="(" align="char">5.70 (4.13)</td><td char="(" align="char">4.90 (3.28)</td><td align="left">
<italic>F</italic> (2, 41) = 35.57, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001***</td><td char="." align="char">0.63</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> EMOT</td><td char="(" align="char">3.93 (2.41)</td><td char="(" align="char">0.986 (1.62)</td><td char="(" align="char">0.837 (1.09)</td><td align="left">
<italic>F</italic> (2, 41) = 31.47, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001***</td><td char="." align="char">0.61</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> HYPER</td><td char="(" align="char">3.33 (2.28)</td><td char="(" align="char">2.86 (1.84)</td><td char="(" align="char">1.86 (1.61)</td><td align="left">
<italic>F</italic> (2, 41) = 5.64, <italic>p</italic> = 0.007*</td><td char="." align="char">0.22</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> CON</td><td char="(" align="char">2.30 (1.61)</td><td char="(" align="char">0.886 (1.09)</td><td char="(" align="char">1.28 (1.22)</td><td align="left">
<italic>F</italic> (2, 41) = 17.53, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001***</td><td char="." align="char">0.46</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> PEER</td><td char="(" align="char">2.41 (2.26)</td><td char="(" align="char">0.971 (1.44)</td><td char="(" align="char">0.930 (1.24)</td><td align="left">
<italic>F</italic> (2, 41) = 11.51, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001***</td><td char="." align="char">0.36</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> PRO</td><td char="(" align="char">6.90 (2.53)</td><td char="(" align="char">8.33 (1.63)</td><td char="(" align="char">8.23 (1.70)</td><td align="left">
<italic>F</italic> (2, 41) = 2.88, <italic>p</italic> = 0.068</td><td char="." align="char">0.12</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="6">PSI</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> PSI total</td><td char="(" align="char">77.97 (14.69)</td><td char="(" align="char">65.87 (14.39)</td><td char="(" align="char">65.86 (16.92)</td><td align="left">
<italic>F</italic> (2, 41) = 34.44, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001***</td><td char="." align="char">0.62</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> PD</td><td char="(" align="char">28.17 (7.65)</td><td char="(" align="char">21.59 (6.36)</td><td char="(" align="char">21.60 (6.68)</td><td align="left">
<italic>F</italic> (2, 41) = 27.48, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001***</td><td char="." align="char">0.58</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> DC</td><td char="(" align="char">30.71 (7.66)</td><td char="(" align="char">23.21 (6.25)</td><td char="(" align="char">23.22 (7.24)</td><td align="left">
<italic>F</italic> (2, 41) = 18.86, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001***</td><td char="." align="char">0.55</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> P-CDI</td><td char="(" align="char">26.26 (6.34)</td><td char="(" align="char">21.07 (5.01)</td><td char="(" align="char">21.02 (4.94)</td><td align="left">
<italic>F</italic> (2, 41) = 17.16, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001***</td><td char="." align="char">0.46</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="6">KPSS</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> KPSS total</td><td char="(" align="char">14.23 (3.37)</td><td char="(" align="char">16.89 (2.36)</td><td char="(" align="char">16.58 (2.74)</td><td align="left">
<italic>F</italic> (2, 41) = 20.09, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001***</td><td char="." align="char">0.50</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>
<italic>SDQ</italic> Strengths and Difficulties Questionnaire, <italic>TD</italic> Total Difficulties, <italic>EMOT</italic> Emotional Symptoms, <italic>HYPER</italic> Hyperactivity, <italic>CON</italic> Conduct Problems, <italic>PEER</italic> Peer Problems, <italic>PRO</italic> prosocial behavior, <italic>PSI</italic> Parenting Stress Index, <italic>PSI total</italic> total stress, <italic>PD</italic> parental distress, <italic>DC</italic> Difficult Child, <italic>P-CDI</italic> Parent–Child dysfunctional interaction, <italic>KPSS</italic> Kansas Parenting Satisfaction Scale, <italic>KPSS total</italic> KPSS total parenting satisfaction</p><p>* Significant at <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05, *** significant at p &lt; 0.001</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
        <sec id="Sec122">
          <title>Strength and Difficulties Questionnaire (SDQ)</title>
          <p>There were significant differences between the mean scores of the two groups at Time 2, <italic>t</italic> (107) = 4.37, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05, <italic>η</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.15, with the mean scores of the PPAP significantly lower than those of the WC group (large effect size). There were similar findings for the Conduct Problems, <italic>t</italic> (107) = −4.05, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05, <italic>η</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.13, and Emotional Symptoms subscales, <italic>t</italic> (107) = −4.54, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05, <italic>η</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.16, with large effect sizes for both, and parents in the PPAP group also reported significantly lower rates of problem behaviour on these variables at Time 2 compared to Time 1. There was no significant change over time reported by parents in the control group on any of these subscales of the SDQ. Parents in both the PPAP and WC groups reported only minor changes in SDQ Hyperactivity scores from Time 1 to Time 2.</p>
          <p>Furthermore, a significant difference with a moderate effect size was revealed between groups on the SDQ Prosocial subscale at Time 2, <italic>t</italic> (107) = 2.70, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05, <italic>η</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.064, with parents in the PPAP group reporting a significant increase in prosocial behaviour on completion of the parenting programme.</p>
          <p>There were significant time effects for SDQ Total Difficulties and the Emotional Symptoms, Hyperactivity, Conduct Problems, and Peer Problems subscales, with large effect sizes for these changes. Paired-samples t tests among Time 1, 2, and 3 scores, identified significant differences in the mean scores for Total Difficulties, Conduct problems, Hyperactivity, and Emotional Symptoms between Time 1 and Time 2, and these changes were maintained at Time 3.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec18">
        <title>Clinical improvement</title>
        <p>Cases were classified as clinically improved if they moved from the clinical and borderline ranges to the non-clinical range on the SDQ Total Difficulties scale. Of the 24 (34.3 %) children in the PPAP group who scored in the clinical/borderline range at Time 1, 21 (30 %) of these moved into the non-clinical range at Time 2. This number further decreased to just 1 (2.3 %) child remaining in the clinical range at Time 3. This positive trend in terms of clinical improvement from Time 1 to Time 2 was not observed for the control group.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec19">
        <title>Parent satisfaction, parental stress and child problems</title>
        <sec id="Sec118">
          <title>Parenting Stress Index (PSI/SF)</title>
          <p>A significant difference was revealed between the mean scores of the two groups at Time 2 for Total Parenting Stress, <italic>t</italic> (107) = −5.51, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05, <italic>η</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.22; Parental Distress, <italic>t</italic> (107) = 5.16, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05, <italic>η</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.199; Difficult Child, <italic>t</italic> (107) = −4.49, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05, <italic>η</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.16; and Parent–Child Dysfunctional Interaction, <italic>t</italic> (107) = −3.93, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05, <italic>η</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.13. The effect size for the difference between groups was large for the former three variables, and moderate to large for Parent–Child Dysfunctional Interaction. In essence, parents in the PPAP group reported a significant decrease in parenting stress following attendance at the parenting programme compared to the control group.</p>
          <p>There were significant time effects for Total Parenting Stress and Parental Distress, Difficult Child, and Parent–Child Dysfunctional Interaction subscales for the PPAP group, with large effects sizes for these changes. Paired-samples <italic>t</italic> test analyses indicated a significant improvement in scores for each variable from Time 1 to Time 2, which was maintained at six-month follow-up.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="Sec120">
          <title>Kansas Parenting Satisfaction Scale</title>
          <p>A significant difference in KPSS scores between the two groups was identified at Time 2, <italic>t</italic> (107) = −3.93, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05, <italic>η</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.13, with a moderate to large effect size for this difference. A significant effect for time was observed for the PPAP group, with a large effect size, <italic>t</italic> (69) = −8.97, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05, <italic>η</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.53, but not for the WC group, <italic>t</italic> (38) = 0.503, <italic>p</italic> &gt; 0.05, <italic>η</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.001, The PPAP group reported a significant increase in overall parenting satisfaction from Time 1 to Time 2.</p>
          <p>The mean score of the PPAP group increased significantly from Time 1 to Time 2, and Time 1 to Time 3, with a small, non-significant decrease from Time 2 to Time 3. There was a large effect size for the change from Time 1 to Time 3. Additionally, the mean scores at post-intervention and follow-up were in the non-clinical range, above the clinical cut-off score of 15 for the KPSS.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec20">
        <title>Changes in parent defined goals</title>
        <sec id="Sec121">
          <title>Parent-defined goals</title>
          <p>For Parent-Defined Child Goals (PDCG), a significant difference with a large effect size was found between the PPAP and WC groups at Time 2, <italic>t</italic> (107) = 7.86, <italic>p</italic> &gt; 0.05, <italic>η</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.37. Similarly, for Parent-Defined Personal Goals (PDPG), a significant difference with a large effect size was found at Time 2, <italic>t</italic> (107) = 10.32, p &gt; 0.05, <italic>η</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.49, between the PPAP and WC groups. There was an interaction effect for parents’ mean scores on the Parent Defined Parent Goals (<italic>F</italic> (1, 107) = 131.3, p &lt; 0.05) and Parent Defined Child Goals (<italic>F</italic> (1, 107) = 81.95, p &lt; 0.05). However the p-value was lower than the Bonferroni adjusted level of p &gt; 0.003.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec21" sec-type="discussion">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>The findings of the evaluation study provide encouraging results for the parents who attended the PPAP and for their children (mean age 12.34 years) who were transitioning to secondary school, suggesting that the programme is effective in reducing behaviour problems. It is encouraging to find that the reported improvements were maintained at the six-month follow-up stage, as this suggests that the treatment effects observed are sustainable over time. Despite the high rate of dropout to Time 3 (49 %), analyses did not demonstrate a statistically significant difference between PPAP completers at Time 2 and those who participated in the follow up at Time 3. The implication of this finding is that all completers benefited from completing the PPAP.</p>
      <p>The results are broadly consistent with comparable studies on international programmes such as Teen Triple P [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>] as well as studies on the other Parents Plus Programmes (e.g., [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]), which have shown the positive impact of the parenting programmes on a range of parent and child outcomes, including improved child emotional and behaviour problems. One caution with regards to these findings is that the PPAP reported a significantly higher score on the SDQ Emotional Subscale at Time 1. Therefore, we cannot make a conclusive comment on effect of the PPAP on internalising problems in this sample.</p>
      <p>Another important finding is the beneficial outcome in terms of parents’ well-being and parental competencies following programme attendance. Parents reported a significant decrease in levels of parenting stress and a significant increase in levels of parenting satisfaction following course attendance. We can hypothesise about possible mechanism of change, e.g., by attending a group-based intervention and sharing their experiences may have led to reduced parent stress, increased satisfaction and improved child outcomes. Another hypothesis is that parents learned and implemented new parenting skills, which led to the positive study outcomes. As we did not measure changes in parenting practices, the latter is a tentative hypothesis, which could be address in future research.</p>
      <p>In terms of goal attainment, parents in the PPAP group reported significant advancement towards attainment of parent-defined child and personal goals compared to the WC group. The most common child and personal goals, as defined by parents at baseline were in relation to adolescent behaviour (e.g., compliance and cooperation) and positive parenting strategies (e.g., to stay calm). Making a direct comparison between treatment gains for the PPAP group against a randomised control group provides evidence that strongly suggests that these positive outcome gains resulted from parents’ attendance at the parenting programme.</p>
      <sec id="Sec22">
        <title>Methodological strengths and limitations</title>
        <sec id="Sec23">
          <title>Strengths</title>
          <p>The current study meets the criteria for a rigorous design (i.e., adequate sample size, randomised control). Another positive aspect of the study is that it was conducted in a ‘real world’ setting.</p>
          <p>The inclusion of a 6-month follow-up attests to the sustainability of the treatment effects and rules out change due to short-term fluctuations. Conducting a follow-up is important for establishing the social validity of an intervention [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>]. Keeping with this issue of follow-up assessment, prolonging the period before the follow-up assessment to 1 year or conducting a second stage of follow-up would be necessary steps to further test the sustainability of treatment effects observed following the PPAP.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec24">
        <title>Limitations</title>
        <p>However, there are methodological limitations to be noted. A major limitation of this study is that it relied on data from a single informant, the majority of whom were mothers. Parents were a community sample who self-selected into the study, which may have resulted in those with lower levels of behavioural and emotional problems than a clinical population. We are also unable to assess overall participation rates as all participants self-selected into the study.</p>
        <p>Parents were randomly assigned to a waitlist or treatment condition. In the absence of a comparison with another type of intervention or placebo condition it is difficult to distinguish genuine treatment effects. There was a high attrition rate at Time 3 (49 %). This rate may inflated the results of data analysis of treatment effects, however there were no significant differences between completers and dropouts on the outcome measures. As a result, we do not know whether all PPAP completers maintained their gains. A further point on distinguishing genuine treatment effects is that we were unable to conduct further analyses, e.g., Intention to Treat or Dropout analyses, as we do not have access to the original data set used in the study.</p>
        <p>Overall the reliability coefficients for the outcome measures were satisfactory. However, the reliability coefficient for the SDQ Conduct Problems subscale was 0.51, which could be described as poor. As the study comprised a community based sample with relatively low rates of emotional and behaviour difficulties, it may be that the narrow range of scores reduced the reliability of this subscale.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec25">
        <title>Implications for practice and policy</title>
        <p>The present findings indicate that the PPAP programme is effective when delivered in community-based settings. Cunningham, Bremner, and Boyle [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>] highlighted the benefits of delivering group parent-training in a community setting over a clinical setting, reporting that, in addition to offering a more cost-effective alternative to administering parent-training in a clinic setting, it also provides a service to families that is non-stigmatising, and thus more appealing, with the potential for reaching greater numbers of parents.</p>
        <p>While parent training programmes have been shown to have a positive impact on a range of outcomes the availability of these educational programmes is limited and many parents do not receive the support they need [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. With current media attention focusing on adolescent anti-social behaviour and taking into account the protective role of parents in preventing negative outcomes for their children, the availability and accessibility of parenting programmes at a community level needs to be addressed. Furthermore, given the high social and economic costs associated with ineffective parenting, the implementation of policies supporting education programmes, aimed at the development of positive parenting skills, should be prioritised.</p>
        <p>Of note, is that the majority were parents of children aged 12 years. That these parents benefited from a programme aimed at adolescents may be explained by the fact that all were parents of children transitioning to secondary school, where the same demands would be placed on a cohort of students in their first year of secondary education irrespective of age. The implication for practice is that programmes need to be offered to parents on the basis of the developmental stage of their children.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec26">
        <title>Implications for future research</title>
        <p>As this study targeted adolescents transitioning from primary to post-primary school, the mean age of the adolescents was in the younger age-group, notably 12.34 years. In addition, the majority of the young people were girls (61 %). In future studies it would be useful to explore the effectiveness of the PPAP with older adolescents, who may have more significant behavioural problems, and with a more balanced gender group. In addition, future research could aim to explore the factors that affect parenting programme attendance, as well as responsiveness to the intervention and maintenance of treatment gains. Furthermore, it would also be important to consider the role of adolescents in parenting programmes, i.e., what role do adolescents have to play in being involved in the interventions aimed at them, which involve their parents attending parent training. It would also be valuable to consider gathering data from adolescents whose parents have attended parent training in evaluating such programmes. Of note, is that the PPAP does provide scope for facilitators to implement individual family sessions, which involve adolescents and parents. It would be useful to include data gathered at these meetings in future research on PPAP. Fathers of adolescents are also important players who need to be considered in future research. Particular thought needs to be given to engaging fathers in parenting programmes and in programme evaluation.</p>
        <p>It would be important for researchers carrying out research in a community based sample to consider the resource implications of trying to gather follow-up from a sample of participants who may be ‘harder to reach’ by not being linked with a particular service. One suggestion from the researchers involved in the current study is to reengage participants by inviting them to follow-up programme or information sessions.</p>
        <p>Future research would be strengthened through the inclusion of qualitative data. Qualitative research is increasingly seen as having implications for practice and its inclusion in methodology has been both called for and supported in the research literature (e.g., [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>]).</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec27" sec-type="conclusions">
      <title>Conclusions</title>
      <p>This study provides preliminary evidence that PPAP may be an effective model of parent-training implemented in a community-based setting. The results are timely, given that the education, health, and social services, both within Ireland and globally, are experiencing dramatic cuts in funding and resources and cost-effective interventions are now needed. Parenting adolescents is a complex, challenging and significant life task and the PPAP may be seen as an important resource for supporting parents in their vital parental role.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Authors’ contributions</title>
      <p>EN was involved in the design of the study, data collection, statistical analysis, and drafting of the manuscript. SH participated in the design of the study, co-ordination of the research, and the drafting of the manuscript. ER was involved in statistical analysis and drafting of the manuscript. GH was involved in revising the manuscript. JS co-developed the Parents Plus Adolescents Programme, and was involved in the design of the study, co-ordination of the research, data collection, and in the drafting of the manuscript. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p>
      <sec id="d30e2883">
        <title>Compliance with ethical guidelines</title>
        <p><bold>Competing interests</bold> Dr. John Sharry is one of the co-developers of the Parents Plus Adolescents Programme.</p>
      </sec>
    </ack>
    <ref-list id="Bib1">
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="CR1">
        <label>1.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Belsky</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Melhuish</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Barnes</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Leyland</surname>
              <given-names>AH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Romaniuk</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>National evaluation of Sure Start research team. Effects of sure start local programmes on children and families: early findings from a quasi-experimental, cross-sectional study</article-title>
          <source>Br Med J</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>332</volume>
          <fpage>1476</fpage>
          <lpage>1478</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.38853.451748.2F</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16782721</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR2">
        <label>2.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Anderson</surname>
              <given-names>RN</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Smith</surname>
              <given-names>BL</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Deaths: leading causes for 2002</article-title>
          <source>Nat Vital Stat Rep</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>53</volume>
          <issue>17</issue>
          <fpage>1</fpage>
          <lpage>90</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR3">
        <label>3.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Fergusson</surname>
              <given-names>DM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Horwood</surname>
              <given-names>LJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ridder</surname>
              <given-names>EM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Tests of causal linkages between cannabis use and psychotic symptoms</article-title>
          <source>Addiction</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>100</volume>
          <fpage>354</fpage>
          <lpage>366</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1360-0443.2005.01001.x</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 15733249?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15733249</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR4">
        <label>4.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Scott</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Knapp</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Henderson</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Maughan</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Financial cost of social exclusion: follow up study of antisocial children into adulthood</article-title>
          <source>Br Med J</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>323</volume>
          <fpage>191</fpage>
          <lpage>194</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.323.7306.191</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11473907</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR5">
        <label>5.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>DeVore</surname>
              <given-names>ER</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ginsburg</surname>
              <given-names>KR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The protective effects of good parenting on adolescents</article-title>
          <source>Postgrad Obstet Gynecol</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>25</volume>
          <issue>25</issue>
          <fpage>1</fpage>
          <lpage>6</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00256406-200512150-00001</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR6">
        <label>6.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bradley</surname>
              <given-names>RH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Corwyn</surname>
              <given-names>RF</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Externalizing problems in fifth grade: relations with productive activity, maternal sensitivity, and harsh parenting from infancy through middle childhood</article-title>
          <source>Dev Psychol</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>43</volume>
          <issue>6</issue>
          <fpage>1390</fpage>
          <lpage>1401</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/0012-1649.43.6.1390</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 18020819?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18020819</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR7">
        <label>7.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hurth-Bocks</surname>
              <given-names>AC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hughes</surname>
              <given-names>HM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Parenting stress, parenting behaviour, and children’s adjustment in families experiencing intimate partner violence</article-title>
          <source>J Fam Violence</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>23</volume>
          <fpage>243</fpage>
          <lpage>251</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10896-007-9148-1</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR8">
        <label>8.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ary</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Duncan</surname>
              <given-names>TE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Duncan</surname>
              <given-names>SC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hops</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Adolescent problem behaviour: the influence of parents and peers</article-title>
          <source>Behav Res Ther</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <volume>37</volume>
          <fpage>217</fpage>
          <lpage>230</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0005-7967(98)00133-8</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 10087640?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10087640</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR9">
        <label>9.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Foster</surname>
              <given-names>EM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Prinz</surname>
              <given-names>RJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sanders</surname>
              <given-names>MR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shapiro</surname>
              <given-names>CJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The costs of a public health infrastructure for delivering parenting and family support</article-title>
          <source>Child Youth Serv Rev</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>30</volume>
          <fpage>493</fpage>
          <lpage>501</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.childyouth.2007.11.002</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR10">
        <label>10.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Spoth</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Randall</surname>
              <given-names>GK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shin</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Increasing school success through partnership-based family competency training: experimental study of long-term outcomes</article-title>
          <source>Sch Psychol Q</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>23</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>70</fpage>
          <lpage>89</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/1045-3830.23.1.70</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 20376279?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20376279</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR11">
        <label>11.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Coley</surname>
              <given-names>RL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vortuba-Drzal</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schindler</surname>
              <given-names>HS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Trajectories of parenting processes and adolescent substance use: reciprocal effects</article-title>
          <source>J Abnorm Child Psychol</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>36</volume>
          <fpage>613</fpage>
          <lpage>625</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10802-007-9205-5</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 18288605?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18288605</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR12">
        <label>12.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hughes</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ensor</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Positive and protective: effects of early theory of mind on problem behaviours in at-risk preschoolers</article-title>
          <source>J Child Psychol Psychiatry</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>48</volume>
          <issue>10</issue>
          <fpage>1025</fpage>
          <lpage>1032</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-7610.2007.01806.x</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 17915003?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17915003</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR13">
        <label>13.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Dretzke</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Davenport</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Frew</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Barlow</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Stewart-Brown</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bayliss</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Taylor</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sandercock</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hyde</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The clinical effectiveness of different parenting programmes for children with conduct problems: a systematic review of randomised controlled trials</article-title>
          <source>Child Adolesc Psychiatry Mental Health</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>3</volume>
          <issue>7</issue>
          <fpage>1</fpage>
          <lpage>10</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR14">
        <label>14.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Zubrick</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ward</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Silburn</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lawrence</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Williams</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Blair</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Robertson</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sanders</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Prevention of child behaviour problems through universal implementation of a group behavioural family intervention</article-title>
          <source>Prev Sci</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>6</volume>
          <fpage>287</fpage>
          <lpage>304</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11121-005-0013-2</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 16160760?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16160760</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR15">
        <label>15.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ralph</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sanders</surname>
              <given-names>MR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>The ‘teen triple P’ positive parenting program: a preliminary evaluation</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <publisher-loc>Canberra</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Australian Institute of Criminology</publisher-name>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR16">
        <label>16.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kumpfer</surname>
              <given-names>KL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Xie</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>O’Driscoll</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Effectiveness of a culturally adapted strengthening families program 12–16 years for high-risk Irish families</article-title>
          <source>Child Youth Care Forum</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>41</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <fpage>173</fpage>
          <lpage>195</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10566-011-9168-0</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR17">
        <label>17.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Day</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Davis</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Community child mental health services: a framework of the development of parenting initiatives</article-title>
          <source>Clin Child Psychol Psychiatry</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <volume>4</volume>
          <fpage>475</fpage>
          <lpage>482</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1359104599004004004</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR18">
        <label>18.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Webster-Stratton</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Taylor</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Nipping early risk factors in the bud: preventing substance abuse, delinquency, and violence in adolescence through interventions targeted at young children (0–8 years)</article-title>
          <source>Prev Sci</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>2</volume>
          <fpage>165</fpage>
          <lpage>192</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/A:1011510923900</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11678292</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR19">
        <label>19.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Webster-Stratton</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hammond</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Predictors of treatment outcome in parent training for families with conduct problem children</article-title>
          <source>Behav Ther</source>
          <year>1990</year>
          <volume>21</volume>
          <fpage>319</fpage>
          <lpage>337</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0005-7894(05)80334-X</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR20">
        <label>20.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>McLennan</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Reckord</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Clarke</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A mental health outreach program for elementary schools</article-title>
          <source>J Can Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>17</volume>
          <fpage>122</fpage>
          <lpage>130</lpage>
          <?supplied-pmid 18769642?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18769642</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR21">
        <label>21.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lean</surname>
              <given-names>DS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Colucci</surname>
              <given-names>VA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Barriers to learning: The case for integrated mental health services in schools</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <publisher-loc>Lanham</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Rowman and Littlefield</publisher-name>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR22">
        <label>22.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Van Acker</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mayer</surname>
              <given-names>MJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor">
            <name>
              <surname>Mayer</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Van Acker</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lochman</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gresham</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Cognitive-behavioural interventions and the social context of the school: a stranger in a strange land</article-title>
          <source>Cognitive-behavioural interventions for emotional and behavioural disorders: school-based practice</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Guilford Press</publisher-name>
          <fpage>82</fpage>
          <lpage>108</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR23">
        <label>23.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Farmer</surname>
              <given-names>EM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Burns</surname>
              <given-names>BJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Phillips</surname>
              <given-names>SD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Angold</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Costello</surname>
              <given-names>EJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Pathways into and through mental health services for children and adolescents</article-title>
          <source>Psychiatr Ser</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>54</volume>
          <fpage>60</fpage>
          <lpage>66</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1176/appi.ps.54.1.60</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR24">
        <label>24.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Chung</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Elias</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schneider</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Patterns of individual adjustment changes during the middle school transition</article-title>
          <source>J Sch Psychol</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <volume>36</volume>
          <fpage>83</fpage>
          <lpage>101</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0022-4405(97)00051-4</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR25">
        <label>25.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Dryfoos</surname>
              <given-names>JG</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Adolescents at risk: prevalence and prevention</source>
          <year>1990</year>
          <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR26">
        <label>26.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Alspaugh</surname>
              <given-names>JW</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Achievement loss associated with the transition to middle school and high school</article-title>
          <source>J Educ Res</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <volume>92</volume>
          <fpage>20</fpage>
          <lpage>25</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/00220679809597572</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR27">
        <label>27.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Theriot</surname>
              <given-names>MT</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dupper</surname>
              <given-names>DR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Student discipline problems and the transition from elementary to middle school</article-title>
          <source>Educ Urban Soc</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>42</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <fpage>205</fpage>
          <lpage>222</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0013124509349583</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR28">
        <label>28.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Cauley</surname>
              <given-names>KM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jovanovich</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Developing an effective transition program for students entering middle school or high school</article-title>
          <source>Clear House</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>80</volume>
          <fpage>15</fpage>
          <lpage>25</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3200/TCHS.80.1.15-25</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR29">
        <label>29.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Elias MJ (2011) Middle school transition: it’s harder than you think. Making the transition to middle school successful. Middle Matters 1–2</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR30">
        <label>30.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sharry</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fitzpatrick</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Parents Plus Adolescents Programme: a DVD based parenting course on managing conflict and getting on better with older children and teenagers aged 11–16 years</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <publisher-loc>Dublin</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Parents Plus</publisher-name>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR31">
        <label>31.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sharry</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fitzpatrick</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Parents Plus Children’s’ Programme: a video-based parenting guide to managing behaviour problems and promoting learning and confidence in children aged 6–11</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <publisher-loc>Dublin</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Parents Plus</publisher-name>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR32">
        <label>32.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sharry</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hampson</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fanning</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Parents Plus Early Years Programme: a DVD-based parenting course on promoting development and managing behaviour problems in young children aged 1–6</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <publisher-loc>Dublin</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Parents Plus</publisher-name>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR33">
        <label>33.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Fisher</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ury</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Patton</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Getting to yes: negotiating agreement without giving in</source>
          <year>1991</year>
          <edition>2</edition>
          <publisher-loc>Dublin</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Penguin</publisher-name>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR34">
        <label>34.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Gordon</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source><italic>P. E. T.:</italic> parent effectiveness training</source>
          <year>1975</year>
          <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Penguin</publisher-name>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR35">
        <label>35.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sharry</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Solution focused groupwork</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <edition>2</edition>
          <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Sage</publisher-name>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR36">
        <label>36.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sharry</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Madden</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Darmody</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Becoming a solution-focused detective: identifying your client strengths in brief therapy</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Haworth</publisher-name>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR37">
        <label>37.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Behan</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fitzpatrick</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sharry</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Carr</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Waldron</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Evaluation of the Parenting Plus Programme</article-title>
          <source>Ir J Psychol</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>22</volume>
          <fpage>238</fpage>
          <lpage>256</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR38">
        <label>38.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Coughlin</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sharry</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fitzpatrick</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Guerin</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Drumm</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A controlled clinical evaluation of the Parents Plus Children’s Programme: a video-based programme for parents of children aged 6–11 with behavioural and developmental problems</article-title>
          <source>Clin Child Psychol Psychiatry</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>14</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <fpage>541</fpage>
          <lpage>558</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1359104509339081</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 19759073?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19759073</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR39">
        <label>39.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Griffin</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Guerin</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sharry</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Drumm</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A multi-centre controlled study of an early intervention parenting programme for young children with behavioural and developmental difficulties</article-title>
          <source>Int J Clin Health Psychol</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>10</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <fpage>279</fpage>
          <lpage>294</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR40">
        <label>40.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hand</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>McDonnell</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Honari</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sharry</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A community led approach to delivery of the parents plus children’s programme for the parents of children aged 6–11</article-title>
          <source>Int J Clin Health Psychol</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>13</volume>
          <fpage>81</fpage>
          <lpage>90</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1697-2600(13)70011-5</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR41">
        <label>41.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hand</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Raghallaigh</surname>
              <given-names>CN</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cuppage</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Coyle</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sharry</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A controlled clinical evaluation of the parents plus children’s programme for parents of children aged 6–12 with mild intellectual disability in a school setting</article-title>
          <source>Clin Child Psychol Psychiatry</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>18</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <fpage>536</fpage>
          <lpage>555</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1359104512460861</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 23104965?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23104965</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR42">
        <label>42.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Quinn</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Carr</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Carroll</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>O’Sullivan</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>An evaluation of the Parents Plus Programme for pre-school children with conduct problems: a comparison of those with and without developmental difficulties</article-title>
          <source>Ir J Psychol</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>27</volume>
          <fpage>168</fpage>
          <lpage>191</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/03033910.2006.10446239</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR43">
        <label>43.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Quinn</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Carr</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Carroll</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>O’Sullivan</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Parents Plus Programme 1: evaluation of its effectiveness for pre-school children with developmental disabilities and behavioural problems</article-title>
          <source>J Appl Res Intellect Disabil</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>20</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <fpage>345</fpage>
          <lpage>359</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1468-3148.2006.00352.x</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR44">
        <label>44.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Chu</surname>
              <given-names>JTW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bullen</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Farruggia</surname>
              <given-names>SP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dittman</surname>
              <given-names>CK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sanders</surname>
              <given-names>MR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Parent and adolescent effects of a universal group program for the parenting of adolescents</article-title>
          <source>Prev Sci</source>
          <year>2014</year>
          <volume>16</volume>
          <fpage>609</fpage>
          <lpage>620</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11121-014-0516-9</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25373684</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR45">
        <label>45.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ralph</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sanders</surname>
              <given-names>MR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Preliminary evaluation of the Group Teen Triple P program for parents of teenagers making the transition to high school</article-title>
          <source>Aust e-J Adv Mental Health</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>2</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <fpage>169</fpage>
          <lpage>178</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5172/jamh.2.3.169</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR46">
        <label>46.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kumpfer</surname>
              <given-names>KL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Whiteside</surname>
              <given-names>HO</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Greene</surname>
              <given-names>JA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Allen</surname>
              <given-names>KC</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Effectiveness outcomes of four age versions of the strengthening families program in statewide field sites</article-title>
          <source>Group Dyn Theor Res Prac</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>14</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <fpage>211</fpage>
          <lpage>229</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/a0020602</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR47">
        <label>47.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Fitzpatrick C, Beattie D, O’Donohoe P, Guerin S (2007) Parent management training for adolescent mental health disorders – A controlled trial. Paper presented at the 54th Annual Meeting of the American Academy of Child and Adolescent Psychiatry, October, Boston, MA, USA</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR48">
        <label>48.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Goodman</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The Strengths and Difficulties Questionnaire: a research note</article-title>
          <source>J Child Psychol Psychiatry</source>
          <year>1997</year>
          <volume>38</volume>
          <fpage>581</fpage>
          <lpage>586</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-7610.1997.tb01545.x</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 9255702?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9255702</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR49">
        <label>49.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Goodman</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Psychometric properties of the Strengths and Difficulties Questionnaire</article-title>
          <source>J Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>40</volume>
          <fpage>1337</fpage>
          <lpage>1347</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00004583-200111000-00015</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 11699809?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11699809</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR50">
        <label>50.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Abidin</surname>
              <given-names>RR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>The parenting stress index professional manual</source>
          <year>1995</year>
          <publisher-loc>Odessa</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Psychol Assess Res</publisher-name>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR51">
        <label>51.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lessenberry</surname>
              <given-names>BM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rehfeldt</surname>
              <given-names>RA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Evaluating stress levels of parents of children with disabilities</article-title>
          <source>Except Child</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>70</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <fpage>231</fpage>
          <lpage>244</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/001440290407000207</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR52">
        <label>52.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>James</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schumm</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kennedy</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Grigsby</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shectman</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nichols</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Characteristics of the Kansas Parental Satisfaction Scale among two samples of married parents</article-title>
          <source>Psychol Rep</source>
          <year>1985</year>
          <volume>57</volume>
          <fpage>163</fpage>
          <lpage>169</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2466/pr0.1985.57.1.163</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR53">
        <label>53.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>DeCato Murphy</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Donohue</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Azrin</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Teichner</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Crum</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Adolescents and their parents: a critical review of measures to assess their satisfaction with one another</article-title>
          <source>Clin Psychol Rev</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>23</volume>
          <fpage>129</fpage>
          <lpage>170</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0272-7358(03)00016-3</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 12560002?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12560002</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR54">
        <label>54.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Serketich</surname>
              <given-names>WJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dumas</surname>
              <given-names>JE</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The effectiveness of behavioural parent training to modify antisocial behaviour in children: a meta-analysis</article-title>
          <source>Behav Ther</source>
          <year>1996</year>
          <volume>27</volume>
          <fpage>171</fpage>
          <lpage>186</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0005-7894(96)80013-X</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR55">
        <label>55.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Cunningham</surname>
              <given-names>CE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bremner</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Boyle</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Large group community based parenting programs for families of preschoolers at risk for disruptive behaviour disorders: utilisation, cost effectiveness, and outcome</article-title>
          <source>J Child Psychol Psychiatry</source>
          <year>1995</year>
          <volume>36</volume>
          <fpage>1141</fpage>
          <lpage>1160</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-7610.1995.tb01362.x</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 8847377?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8847377</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR56">
        <label>56.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Morse</surname>
              <given-names>JM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Swanson</surname>
              <given-names>JM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kuzel</surname>
              <given-names>AJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>The nature of qualitative evidence</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <publisher-loc>California</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Sage</publisher-name>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>

</metadata></record></GetRecord></OAI-PMH>