<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Psychol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Psychol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Psychology</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Psychology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1664-1078</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Research Foundation</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">22973249</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3434872</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpsyg.2012.00318</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Psychology</subject><subj-group><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Individual Variation in the Late Positive Complex to Semantic Anomalies</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kos</surname><given-names>Miriam</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn001">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>van den Brink</surname><given-names>Danielle</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hagoort</surname><given-names>Peter</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>Radboud University Nijmegen, Donders Institute for Brain, Cognition and Behaviour</institution><country>Nijmegen, The Netherlands</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>Radboud University Nijmegen, Behavioural Science Institute</institution><country>Nijmegen, The Netherlands</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><sup>3</sup><institution>Max Planck Institute for Psycholinguistics</institution><country>Nijmegen, Netherlands</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited by: Guillaume Thierry, Bangor University, UK</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Reviewed by: Mireille Besson, Institut de Neurosciences Cognitives de la Meditarran&#x000e9;e, France; Itziar Laka, University of the Basque Country UPV/EHU, Spain</p></fn><corresp id="fn001">*Correspondence: Miriam Kos, Donders Institute for Brain, Cognition and Behaviour, Centre for Cognitive Neuroimaging, Radboud University Nijmegen, P.O. Box 9101, NL-6500 HB Nijmegen, Netherlands. e-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">m.kos@donders.ru.nl</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other" id="fn002"><p>This article was submitted to Frontiers in Language Sciences, a specialty of Frontiers in Psychology.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epreprint"><day>05</day><month>6</month><year>2012</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>06</day><month>9</month><year>2012</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2012</year></pub-date><volume>3</volume><elocation-id>318</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>16</day><month>5</month><year>2012</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>11</day><month>8</month><year>2012</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2012 Kos, van den Brink and Hagoort.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2012</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://www.frontiersin.org/licenseagreement"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the <uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</uri>, which permits use, distribution and reproduction in other forums, provided the original authors and source are credited and subject to any copyright notices concerning any third-party graphics etc.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>It is well-known that, within ERP paradigms of sentence processing, semantically anomalous words elicit N400 effects. Less clear, however, is what happens after the N400. In some cases N400 effects are followed by Late Positive Complexes (LPC), whereas in other cases such effects are lacking. We investigated several factors which could affect the LPC, such as contextual constraint, inter-individual variation, and working memory. Seventy-two participants read sentences containing a semantic manipulation (Whipped cream tastes <italic>sweet/anxious</italic> and creamy). Neither contextual constraint nor working memory correlated with the LPC. Inter-individual variation played a substantial role in the elicitation of the LPC with about half of the participants showing a negative response and the other half showing an LPC. This individual variation correlated with a syntactic ERP as well as an alternative semantic manipulation. In conclusion, our results show that inter-individual variation plays a large role in the elicitation of the LPC and this may account for the diversity in LPC findings in language research.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>late positive complex</kwd><kwd>inter-individual variation</kwd><kwd>event-related potentials</kwd><kwd>semantics</kwd><kwd>sentence processing</kwd><kwd>N400</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="5"/><table-count count="0"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="45"/><page-count count="10"/><word-count count="7226"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>Since its discovery (Kutas and Hillyard, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">1980</xref>), the N400 has proven to be a reliable and consistent measure in the processing of meaning. Words that are semantically incongruent or have a poor semantic fit given the preceding context elicit a larger negative effect around 400&#x02009;ms compared to words that fit well within the context (Kutas and Federmeier, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">2011</xref>). There is, however, less consistency with respect to the Event-Related brain Potentials (ERPs) following the N400 time window. Some studies report that the N400 is followed by a late positivity or Late Positive Complex (LPC) with a broad, posterior (M&#x000fc;nte et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">1998</xref>; Severens and Hartsuiker, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">2009</xref>; Van de Meerendonk et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">2010</xref>; Sanford et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">2011</xref>; Szewczyk and Schriefers, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">2011</xref>) or, sometimes, frontal distribution (Federmeier et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">2007</xref>; DeLong et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">2011</xref>; Thornhill and Van Petten, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">2012</xref>), whereas in other studies such an LPC is lacking (Osterhout and Mobley, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">1995</xref>; Van den Brink et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">2006</xref>; Van Berkum et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">2008</xref>; Baggio et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2010</xref>; Stroud and Phillips, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">2012</xref>; for a review see Van Petten and Luka, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">2012</xref>).</p><p>Currently, it is not clear what causes this inconsistency in findings. In this study we address this issue by investigating potential triggers of the LPC. It is known that the performance of a plausibility judgment task can trigger late positivities (Kolk et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">2003</xref>; Geyer et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">2006</xref>; Kuperberg, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">2007</xref>). However, this factor does not account for all findings, as in some experiments without an online rating task the N400 was followed by an LPC (e.g., M&#x000fc;nte et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">1998</xref>; Szewczyk and Schriefers, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">2011</xref>), and in other ERP studies, containing an online judgment task, the LPC was lacking (e.g., Stroud and Phillips, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">2012</xref>). We investigated a number of possible triggers of LPCs in two studies that did not require a response from the participant.</p><p>One potential factor that could play a role in the elicitation of the LPC is sentential constraint. Unexpected continuations in high- but not low-constraining contexts, quantified by means of cloze probability of the highest probability continuation, have been found to elicit a, predominantly frontally distributed, LPC (Federmeier et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">2007</xref>; DeLong et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">2011</xref>; Thornhill and Van Petten, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">2012</xref>; Van Petten and Luka, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">2012</xref>). A second potential trigger of the LPC is inter-individual variation, as has previously been found by Nieuwland and Van Berkum (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">2008</xref>). In their ERP study one group of participants showed the standard negative shift (NRef effect) to referentially ambiguous nouns (e.g., &#x0201c;She admired the <italic>necklace</italic>&#x02026;&#x0201d; in a context with two necklaces), whereas for the other half of participants an LPC was found. Importantly, this pattern of results was related to the LPC elicited by semantically anomalous words (e.g., &#x0201c;She stepped into the <italic>necklace</italic>&#x02026;&#x0201d;). Participants who elicited an LPC to the referentially ambiguous nouns, also showed a larger LPC to the semantically anomalous nouns as compared to the &#x0201c;NRef-group&#x0201d; (Nieuwland and Van Berkum, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">2008</xref>). In addition, other experiments investigating sentence processing revealed large individual differences in late positivities as well, indicating that there are qualitative differences in the way in which subjects process sentences (Osterhout et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">1997</xref>). Therefore, inter-individual differences in language processing could partly account for the variability of findings with respect to the LPC to semantic anomalies. Inter-individual differences in sentence processing have often been linked to differences in working memory (St George et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">1997</xref>; Friederici et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">1998</xref>; Gunter et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">2003</xref>; Otten and Van Berkum, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">2009</xref>; Nakano et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">2010</xref>). Moreover, amplitude differences in the N400 effect and the LPC have also been linked to working memory variation (Van Petten et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">1997</xref>). Therefore, inter-individual variation in the LPC may be related to working memory differences between individuals.</p><p>In the current study we investigated a number of possible underlying causes of the LPC. We did this on the basis of a substantial dataset, collected across two ERP experiments. Seventy-two participants were visually presented, amongst others, with a semantic manipulation [semantically coherent (SC): Whipped cream tastes <italic>sweet</italic> and creamy; semantically anomalous (SA): Whipped cream tastes <italic>anxious</italic> and creamy]. In addition, this dataset contained a subject-verb agreement manipulation (The spoiled child <italic>throws/throw</italic> the toy on the floor.), known to elicit a P600 effect (Hagoort et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">1993</xref>). One half of the subjects was also presented with a semantic-thematic manipulation (congruent: Father eats a <italic>sandwich/</italic>Father eats in a <italic>restaurant</italic>, semantic-thematic violation: Father eats a <italic>restaurant</italic>/Father eats in a <italic>sandwich</italic>), known to elicit an N400 effect (Kos et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">2010</xref>). This dataset gave us the opportunity to explore post hoc several factors known or hypothesized to affect the LPC. As it has been shown that contextual constraint affects the LPC (Federmeier et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">2007</xref>; DeLong et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">2011</xref>; Thornhill and Van Petten, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">2012</xref>), we compared high versus low constraint items of the semantic manipulation. In addition, given the findings of individual differences in late positive effects in sentence processing (Osterhout et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">1997</xref>; Nieuwland and Van Berkum, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">2008</xref>), we inspected inter-individual variation within the LPC time window. Finally, we tested whether individual differences within the LPC time window were related to working memory performance (cf. Van Petten et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">1997</xref>). Identification of factors involved in the elicitation of the LPC will contribute to a better understanding of human language processing.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec><title>Participants</title><p>Ninety-four highly educated native speakers of Dutch of the Donders Institute participant pool participated in one of two ERP experiments. The data of 20 of the participants were excluded from final analysis due to an excessive number of artifacts in the EEG signal, two participants were not included because of technical problems during the measurement. As a consequence, the data of 72 of the participants were included in the final analysis (36 males, mean age 21.5&#x02009;years, range 18&#x02013;31). All had normal or corrected-to-normal vision and were right-handed. None of the participants had any neurological or language impairment. All participants signed informed consent and received reimbursement or course credits for participation. The study was approved by the local ethics committee.</p></sec><sec><title>Materials</title><p>The manipulation of interest concerned a semantic manipulation consisting of 80 Dutch sentence pairs containing a semantic violation and a correct control (Whipped cream tastes <italic>sweet/anxious</italic> and creamy). These sentence pairs had already been used in other experiments and are known to elicit an N400 effect (Swaab et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">1997</xref>; Van den Brink et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">2001</xref>; Hagoort et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">2004</xref>). The experimental sentence pairs were identical with the exception of one word, which was the critical word for our analyses (printed in bold). Each pair consisted of a sentence that was completely semantically coherent (SC: Whipped cream tastes <italic>sweet</italic> and creamy) and a sentence that contained a semantic anomaly (SA: Whipped cream tastes <italic>anxious</italic> and creamy). The critical words were never in sentence-final position and were matched across conditions for word frequency (SC&#x02009;=&#x02009;2.964, SA&#x02009;=&#x02009;2.862), based on log lemma frequencies of the Dutch database CELEX (Baaijen et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1993</xref>), and length (SC&#x02009;=&#x02009;5.69, SA&#x02009;=&#x02009;5.73). The length of the sentences ranged from 5 to 19 words. The average length was 12.7 words (SD&#x02009;=&#x02009;3.0).</p><p>Sentential constraint, i.e., the cloze probability of the highest probability continuation, was assessed by means of a behavioral experiment. Thirty-six participants, who had not participated in the EEG experiment, completed 40 sentences of these materials. Sentences were presented on a computer screen up to the critical word. Participants were asked to give one completion per item resulting in a well-formed sentence, while it was emphasized to type the first completion that came to mind. The average sentential constraint was 0.70, SD&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.22.</p><p>In addition, both ERP experiments contained a syntactic manipulation consisting of a subject-verb agreement manipulation (The spoiled child <italic>throws/throw</italic> the toy on the floor), known to elicit a P600 effect (Hagoort et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">1993</xref>). The semantic and syntactic manipulations were part of two separate ERP experiments. The two experiments had a comparable setup, which enabled us to pool the data of the semantic and syntactic manipulations, resulting in a large dataset of 72 subjects. Both experiments also contained 50 coherent items, which served as filler sentences. These coherent sentences were selected from the Dutch CLEF corpus (Van der Beek et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">2001</xref>). In addition, we included 20 practice-items, which were similar in nature to the experimental items. For purposes which fall beyond the scope of this paper, the experiments differed with respect to the rest of the materials. One of the experiments (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;36) additionally contained a set of ambiguous relative clauses and, importantly, a semantic-thematic manipulation (Father eats a <italic>sandwich/restaurant</italic>&#x02026;/Father eats in a <italic>restaurant/sandwich</italic>&#x02026;), known to elicit an N400 effect (Kos et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">2010</xref>). In contrast to the semantic anomalies described above, in which the incongruent words are semantically anomalous irrespective of thematic role, the content words of the sentences of the semantic-thematic manipulation form a plausible script (e.g., father-eat-restaurant). In the thematic role violations (e.g., Father eats a <italic>restaurant</italic>), where in principle a syntactic alternative could be easily constructed in line with the thematic bias [<italic>EAT</italic> (AGENT, THEME, LOC) in which restaurant perfectly fits the LOC slot but not the THEME slot], the syntactic constraints impose a certain thematic role onto the critical word, which conflicts with its semantic-thematic role in the plausible script, resulting in an implausible scenario. Within the other experiment a set of complement clauses and a set of relative clauses (Kolk et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">2003</xref>) were included.</p><p>Per experiment, materials were divided across lists, which were mixed pseudo randomly, with each version of each item distributed equally across the two lists, all containing an equal number of items per condition. No participant read the same sentence in more than one variant, and each variant was presented to an equal number of participants. The length of the sentences ranged from 5 to 19 words. The average length was 10.8 words (SD&#x02009;=&#x02009;2.10; experiment1: mean&#x02009;=&#x02009;10.3, SD&#x02009;=&#x02009;2.26, experiment2: mean&#x02009;=&#x02009;11.6, SD&#x02009;=&#x02009;1.89).</p></sec><sec><title>Procedure</title><p>Each participant took part in one of the two ERP experiments, consisting of one experimental session. Sentences were presented centrally using rapid visual serial presentation (both word-duration and ISI 300&#x02009;ms). Participants read for comprehension in a dimly lit (Fiber optic lights DMX 512 at 60%), sound-attenuating booth. No other task demands were imposed.</p><p>After a short practice session, trials were presented in five blocks of 15&#x02009;min each, separated by rest periods of approximately 5&#x02009;min each. Halfway through every block there was an additional 30&#x02009;s break. Viewing distance was approximately 110&#x02009;cm. The first word of the sentence started with a capital letter, the rest of the words were presented in white lowercase ARIAL (23-point font size) against a dark background in the center of a CFT 60&#x02009;Hz computer screen. Each word was presented for 300&#x02009;ms followed by a blank screen for 300&#x02009;ms. The final word of the sentence ended with a period. After the final word an asterisk appeared for 2&#x02009;s, indicating to the participants that they could blink and move their eyes. There was a 1.2-s blank interval between the asterisk and the start of the next trial. Sentences were presented using Presentation software (Neurobehavioral systems, <uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.neuro-bs.com">www.neuro-bs.com</uri>).</p><p>For a subset of 52 participants we assessed verbal working memory post hoc by means of a standard computerized version of the Reading Span task (mean 74.2, SD 9.8; Van den Noort et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">2008</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>EEG recording and analysis</title><p>The EEG was recorded from 28 cap-mounted Ag/AgCl electrodes (Easycap and Acticap). Four electrodes were placed over the standard 10% system midline sites Fz, FCz, Cz, and Pz. Eleven pairs were located over the standard lateral sites FP1/FP2, F7/F8, F3/F4, FC5/FC6, FC1/FC2, T7/T8, C3/C4, CP5/CP6, CP1/CP2, P7/P8, and O1/O2. Two electrodes were placed at the outer left and right canthi to monitor horizontal eye movements. Vertical eye movements were monitored using FP1 and an electrode placed below the left eye. An additional electrode was placed on the right mastoid bone. During measurement, all electrodes were referenced to the left mastoid. For the Easycap electrode impedances of the EEG- and EOG-electrodes were kept below 5 and 10&#x02009;k&#x003a9; respectively, for the Acticap electrode impedances kept below 20&#x02009;k&#x003a9;. Signals were recorded with a BrainAmp DC amplifier (Brain Products, Germany), using a 125&#x02009;Hz low-pass filter, a time constant of 10&#x02009;s, and a 500&#x02009;Hz sampling frequency. The software package Brain Vision Analyzer (Brain Products, Germany) was used to analyze the waveforms.</p><p>Offline, the EEG electrodes were re-referenced to the mean of the right and left mastoid and the EOG-electrodes were converted into bipolar horizontal and vertical EOG signals. A 30&#x02009;Hz, 12&#x02009;dB low-pass, Hanning filter was applied. Subsequently, the critical words were segmented using a window which started 200&#x02009;ms before and ended 1500&#x02009;ms after the critical word. These segments were baseline corrected to the 200&#x02009;ms pre-critical-word interval. Subsequently, artifact-contaminated target trials were rejected (average 12.1%) and the remaining EEG segments were averaged per participant and per condition. Twenty participants were excluded from the analysis because more than 20% of the trials were rejected, leaving 72 participants for subsequent analysis.</p><p>Mean amplitudes of the N400 (300&#x02013;600&#x02009;ms) and LPC (600&#x02013;1000&#x02009;ms) latency windows were evaluated in repeated measures analyses of variance (ANOVA), using four quadrants (left anterior: F3, F7, FC1, FC5, C3; right anterior: F4, F8, FC2, FC6, C4, left posterior: CP1, CP5, P3, P7, O1; right posterior: CP2, CP6, P4, P8, O2), and midline sites (Fz, FCz, Cz, Pz). Whenever appropriate, Greenhouse&#x02013;Geisser correction was applied. In these cases the corrected <italic>p</italic>-values with the original degrees of freedom will be reported.</p><p>In order to verify whether individual variation was systematic or not, we computed correlations of semantic ERP effect sizes with the subject-verb agreement manipulation (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;72), known to elicit a P600 effect (Hagoort et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">1993</xref>) and with the semantic-thematic manipulation (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;36), known to elicit an N400 effect (Kos et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">2010</xref>). These tests were conducted using Bonferroni adjusted alpha levels.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>A shows the grand-average waveforms of the semantic anomalies and the correct controls (in the absence of significant interactions between experiment and Semantic Fit, we collapsed the data over two experiments). The topographical distributions of the effects between 300 and 600, 600 and 1000, and 1000 and 1350&#x02009;ms are depicted in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>B. The semantic anomalies elicited a clear N400 effect. Instead of an LPC, the negativity of the N400 seems to extend into the LPC time window; only after around 1000&#x02009;ms a positivity is emerging.</p><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><bold>(A)</bold> Grand-average waveforms of the ERPs elicited by the semantic anomalies (dashed, blue line) and their correct controls (solid, black line) for electrodes CP1, CP2, P3, Pz, and P4. In this and all following figures the waveforms are time-locked to the onset of the critical word (0&#x02009;ms) and negative voltage is plotted upward. Furthermore, an 8&#x02009;Hz low-pass filter has been applied for illustrative purposes. The left, gray block and right, green block indicate the latency windows used for analysis for the N400 and LPC respectively. <bold>(B)</bold> Scalp distribution of the N400 effect elicited by the semantic manipulation between 300 and 600&#x02009;ms, and of the effect between 600 and 1000&#x02009;ms, and 1000 and 1350&#x02009;ms after critical word onset. (In this and following figures the electrodes for which the waveforms are displayed are highlighted).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpsyg-03-00318-g001"/></fig><p>The repeated measures ANOVA in the 300&#x02013;600&#x02009;ms time window revealed a main effect of Semantic Fit [<italic>F</italic>(1, 71)&#x02009;=&#x02009;137.94, MSE&#x02009;=&#x02009;32.21, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001] and an interaction between Semantic Fit and Quadrant [<italic>F</italic>(3, 213)&#x02009;=&#x02009;10.80, MSE&#x02009;=&#x02009;5.12, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001]. Subsequent analyses show a main effect of Semantic Fit for all four quadrants [Left Anterior: <italic>F</italic>(1, 71)&#x02009;=&#x02009;59.91, MSE&#x02009;=&#x02009;12.23, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001; Right Anterior: <italic>F</italic>(1, 71)&#x02009;=&#x02009;75.76, MSE&#x02009;=&#x02009;10.96, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001; Left Posterior: <italic>F</italic>(1, 71)&#x02009;=&#x02009;134.47, MSE&#x02009;=&#x02009;11.22, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001; Right Posterior: <italic>F</italic>(1, 71)&#x02009;=&#x02009;171.64, MSE&#x02009;=&#x02009;8.68, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001]. The midline analysis revealed an effect of Semantic fit as well [<italic>F</italic>(1, 71)&#x02009;=&#x02009;117.54, MSE&#x02009;=&#x02009;10.81, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001]. Even though the N400 effect is widespread, the topographical distribution shows that the effect was strongest over the posterior electrodes, which is common for N400 effects (Kutas and Van Petten, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">1994</xref>).</p><p>Within the LPC time window (600&#x02013;1000&#x02009;ms) we observed a significant negative effect of Semantic Fit across all quadrants [<italic>F</italic>(1, 71)&#x02009;=&#x02009;4.96, MSE&#x02009;=&#x02009;34.56, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05] and a significant interaction between Semantic Fit and Quadrant [<italic>F</italic>(3, 213)&#x02009;=&#x02009;13.41, MSE&#x02009;=&#x02009;7.59, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001]. Separate analyses for Semantic Fit per quadrant revealed significant negative effects for the two anterior quadrants [left anterior: <italic>F</italic>(1, 71)&#x02009;=&#x02009;14.88, MSE&#x02009;=&#x02009;11.35, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001; right anterior: <italic>F</italic>(1, 71)&#x02009;=&#x02009;18.13, MSE&#x02009;=&#x02009;10.10, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001], but no significant effects for the two posterior quadrants [left posterior: <italic>F</italic>(1, 71)&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;1; right posterior: <italic>F</italic>(1, 71)&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;1]. The midline analyses revealed a significant effect of Semantic Fit [<italic>F</italic>(1, 71)&#x02009;=&#x02009;9.03, MSE&#x02009;=&#x02009;13.12, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01].</p><p>On the basis of visual inspection we performed additional analyses between 1000 and 1350&#x02009;ms after word onset to explore the late positive effect. Across all quadrants there was no effect of Semantic Fit [<italic>F</italic>(1, 71)&#x02009;=&#x02009;1.33, MSE&#x02009;=&#x02009;40.89, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.253], but an interaction between Semantic Fit and Quadrant was found [<italic>F</italic>(3, 213)&#x02009;=&#x02009;16.93, MSE&#x02009;=&#x02009;7.60, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001]. Further analyses for the separate quadrants revealed a significant right posterior effect of Semantic Fit [left anterior: <italic>F</italic>(1, 71)&#x02009;=&#x02009;3.33, MSE&#x02009;=&#x02009;14.32, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.072; right anterior: <italic>F</italic>(1, 71)&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;1; left posterior: <italic>F</italic>(1, 71)&#x02009;=&#x02009;3.16, MSE&#x02009;=&#x02009;11.38, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.080; right posterior: <italic>F</italic>(1, 71)&#x02009;=&#x02009;13.06, MSE&#x02009;=&#x02009;15.87, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01]. Semantic Fit did not reach significance at the midline electrodes [<italic>F</italic>(1, 71)&#x02009;=&#x02009;2.97, MSE&#x02009;=&#x02009;14.96, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.089].</p><sec><title>Contextual constraint</title><p>We assessed effects of contextual constraint (cloze probability of the highest probability continuation) by grouping the items based on a median split (low constraint: mean&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.50, SD&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.11; high constraint: mean&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.90, SD&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.10; incongruent critical words matched across constraint conditions for frequency [<italic>t</italic>(158)&#x02009;=&#x02009;1.375, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.17]. Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>A shows the difference waveforms (incongruent minus congruent) for the high and low contextual constraint items. The N400 effect (300&#x02013;600&#x02009;ms) of the high contextual constraint sentences is larger compared to the low contextual constraint sentences across all four quadrants (Constraint&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;Semantic Fit <italic>F</italic>(1, 71)&#x02009;=&#x02009;9.82, MSE&#x02009;=&#x02009;48.73, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01). The interaction between Constraint&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;Semantic Fit&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;Quadrant was not significant [<italic>F</italic>(3, 213)&#x02009;=&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;1]. Midline analyses revealed a significant interaction between Constraint and Semantic Fit [<italic>F</italic>(1, 71)&#x02009;=&#x02009;6.34, MSE&#x02009;=&#x02009;21.81, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05]. Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>B shows the topographical distributions of the N400 effect elicited by the high constraint and low constraint items.</p><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><bold>(A)</bold> Difference waveforms elicited by the high contextual constraint (solid, black line) and low contextual constraint (dashed, blue line) items for electrodes FCz, Cz, and Pz. <bold>(B)</bold> Scalp distributions of the N400 effect of the high and low constraint items. The high constraint items elicit a larger N400 effect compared to the low constraint items. <bold>(C)</bold> Grand-average waveforms of the congruent high (solid, black line) and low constraint (dashed, blue line) items for electrodes FCz, Cz, and Pz.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpsyg-03-00318-g002"/></fig><p>Within the LPC time window (600&#x02013;1000) significant interactions between Contextual constraint and Semantic Fit are absent [across four quadrants: <italic>F</italic>(1, 71)&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;1; Constraint&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;Semantic Fit&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;Quadrant <italic>F</italic>(3, 213)&#x02009;=&#x02009;1.93, MSE&#x02009;=&#x02009;6.20, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.14; Midline: Constraint&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;Semantic Fit <italic>F</italic>(1, 71)&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;1].</p><p>As previous experiments revealed differences between high and low-constraining contexts of congruent semantic words (Federmeier et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">2007</xref>; DeLong et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">2011</xref>; Thornhill and Van Petten, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">2012</xref>), we also analyzed the ERPs of the congruent words within the high and low contextual constraint conditions (congruent critical words matched across constraint conditions for frequency [<italic>t</italic>(78)&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.17, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.86]). Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>C shows the waveforms to the congruent conditions for the high and low contextual constraint items. The low constraint words elicit a larger N400 component compared to the high constraint words over four quadrants and over the midline sites [four quadrants: <italic>F</italic>(1, 71)&#x02009;=&#x02009;14.30, MSE&#x02009;=&#x02009;57.25, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001; midline: <italic>F</italic>(1, 71)&#x02009;=&#x02009;6.81, MSE&#x02009;=&#x02009;24.22, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05]. The interaction between Constraint and Quadrant was also significant between 300 and 600&#x02009;ms [<italic>F</italic>(3, 213)&#x02009;=&#x02009;3.70, MSE&#x02009;=&#x02009;6.88, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05]. Separate analyses per quadrant revealed that the differences between high and low constraint were present for all four quadrants [left anterior: <italic>F</italic>(1, 71)&#x02009;=&#x02009;6.32, MSE&#x02009;=&#x02009;19.46, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05; right anterior: <italic>F</italic>(1, 71)&#x02009;=&#x02009;4.97, MSE&#x02009;=&#x02009;21.20, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05; left posterior: <italic>F</italic>(1, 71)&#x02009;=&#x02009;18.90, MSE&#x02009;=&#x02009;15.04, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001; right posterior <italic>F</italic>(1, 71)&#x02009;=&#x02009;21.63, MSE&#x02009;=&#x02009;17.07, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001].</p><p>Analyses between 600 and 1000&#x02009;ms showed no significant effects for Contextual constraint [all four quadrants: <italic>F</italic>(1, 71)&#x02009;=&#x02009;2.10, MSE&#x02009;=&#x02009;50.44, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.151; Midline: <italic>F</italic>(1, 71)&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;1], nor an interaction between Constraint and Quadrant [<italic>F</italic>(3, 213)&#x02009;=&#x02009;1.88, MSE&#x02009;=&#x02009;7.72, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.150].</p></sec><sec><title>Inter-individual variability LPC</title><p>Given the posterior distribution of the positivity observed across all participants between 1000 and 1350&#x02009;ms, we explored the individual effects within the standard LPC time window (600&#x02013;1000&#x02009;ms) across the 11 posterior electrodes (mean&#x02009;=&#x02009;&#x02212;0.06, SD&#x02009;=&#x02009;2.28). This analysis reveals the amount of individual variation within this time window with approximately half of the participants showing a negative and half a positive effect (see Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>A), resulting in an absence of a significant overall main effect. Inspection of the N400 time window shows that almost all participants elicit a negative effect with less overall variation (mean&#x02009;=&#x02009;&#x02212;2.98, SD&#x02009;=&#x02009;1.98; Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>B). To investigate whether the variation within the LPC time window could be attributed to noise, we inspected ERP effects elicited by other words within the sentence. To avoid temporal overlap or cross-over effects of semantically anomalous words, we analyzed the words that were positioned two words before the critical words used in the analyses above. Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>C depicts the individual ERP effects between 600 and 1000&#x02009;ms after onset of the word. Also here, the effects vary across individuals (mean&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.17, SD&#x02009;=&#x02009;1.51), but the variation to the random words is lower compared to the variation observed for the LPC [<italic>F</italic>(1, 142)&#x02009;=&#x02009;6.934, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01].</p><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Effect sizes per participant for the semantic manipulation within <bold>(A)</bold> the LPC time window (600&#x02013;1000&#x02009;ms) and <bold>(B)</bold> the N400 time window (300&#x02013;600&#x02009;ms). <bold>(C)</bold> Effects per participant on the word two positions before the critical word of the semantic manipulation between 600 and 1000&#x02009;ms. Participants are sorted on LPC effect size for easier comparison between the figures.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpsyg-03-00318-g003"/></fig><p>In order to further explore the consistency of the inter-individual variation, we performed correlation analyses with the subject-verb agreement and semantic-thematic manipulation using the individual effects between 600 and 1000&#x02009;ms of the critical words and the words positioned two words before these critical words. This resulted in four tests for which Bonferroni adjusted alpha levels of 0.0125 were used.</p><p>Individual ERP effects elicited by the syntactic and semantic manipulation between 600 and 1000&#x02009;ms were significantly correlated [<italic>r</italic>(70)&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.37, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01; see Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>A]. Furthermore, individual effects within the LPC time window of the two semantic manipulations were highly correlated [<italic>r</italic>(34)&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.65, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001; see Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>B]. In contrast, individual variation to the word positioned two words before the critical word did not correlate with the variation observed for the P600 [<italic>r</italic>(70)&#x02009;=&#x02009;&#x02212;0.20, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.10] nor with variation seen in the LPC time window of the semantic-thematic manipulation [<italic>r</italic>(34)&#x02009;=&#x02009;&#x02212;0.10, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.58].</p><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><bold>(A)</bold> Scatter plot of the effect of the semantic manipulation within the LPC time window (600&#x02013;1000&#x02009;ms) and the P600 effect elicited by subject-verb agreement violations within the same latency window, which are correlated. <bold>(B)</bold> Scatter plot for half of the participants who were offered two semantic manipulations. The plot shows the effects within the LPC time window. These effects are highly correlated.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpsyg-03-00318-g004"/></fig><p>In order to visualize the individual variation within the LPC time window, we divided the participants based on a median split (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>). One half of the participants showed an extended negativity after the N400, whereas the other half exhibited an LPC. On the right panel of Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref> the effects of the two groups are directly compared.</p><fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Two groups were created by means of a median split of the posterior effect between 600 and 1000&#x02009;ms. The left panel of this figure shows their grand-average waveforms of the ERPs elicited by the semantic anomalies (dashed, colored line) and the correct controls (solid, black line) for electrodes CP1, CP2, and Pz. Additionally, the scalp distribution of the effect elicited by the semantic manipulation between 600 and 1000&#x02009;ms is depicted. The right side displays the effect or difference waveforms of group 1 (blue, solid line) and group 2 (red, dashed line) at electrode Pz.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpsyg-03-00318-g005"/></fig><p>There were no relations between semantic ERP effects and reading span scores, as assessed by computing the correlation between the individual effects over posterior electrodes between 300 and 600 and 600 and 1000&#x02009;ms and their reading span scores [<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;52; 300&#x02013;600&#x02009;ms: <italic>r</italic>(50)&#x02009;=&#x02009;&#x02212;0.08, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.56; 600&#x02013;1000&#x02009;ms: <italic>r</italic>(50)&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.12, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.39; <italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;28 for the negative responders, <italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;24 for the positive responders]. Nor can these individual differences be explained by gender [<italic>t</italic>(70)&#x02009;=&#x02009;&#x02212;0.40, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.69] or experimental version [<italic>t</italic>(70)&#x02009;=&#x02009;&#x02212;0.16, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.99]. It has been suggested that familial left-handedness is related to individual differences in language processing (Townsend et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">2001</xref>). We retrieved information about the handedness of the parents of 70 of our participants. Fourteen out of 70 reported having at least one left-handed parent. Eleven of these 14 belong to the negative, no LPC group.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>A substantial dataset, consisting of the ERP responses of 72 participants to a semantic manipulation (Whipped cream tastes <italic>sweet/anxious</italic> and creamy.), enabled us to examine potential factors involved in the elicitation of the LPC, such as contextual constraint (Federmeier et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">2007</xref>; DeLong et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">2011</xref>), individual variation (Osterhout et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">1997</xref>; Nieuwland and Van Berkum, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">2008</xref>), and working memory (Van Petten et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">1997</xref>; Friederici et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">1998</xref>). The aim of this study was to identify possible underlying causes of the LPC and to reach to a better understanding of this ERP effect. We found that, across all 72 participants, the semantic manipulation elicited a robust N400 effect. The negativity of this N400 effect extended into the LPC time window over the frontal electrodes. There was no positivity within the standard LPC time window (600&#x02013;1000&#x02009;ms). Instead, a posterior positivity emerges only after around 1000&#x02009;ms (see Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>).</p><p>First, we investigated whether contextual constraint modulates ERP waveforms in the LPC time window, as previous research suggests that the LPC is related to the possible cost of processing unexpected words in strongly constraining contexts (Federmeier et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">2007</xref>; DeLong et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">2011</xref>; Thornhill and Van Petten, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">2012</xref>; Van Petten and Luka, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">2012</xref>). We found a larger N400 effect in the high constraint compared to the low constraint condition, and this is in line with previous research (Federmeier et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">2007</xref>; Kutas and Federmeier, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">2011</xref>). In contrast to earlier findings (Federmeier et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">2007</xref>), the effects within the LPC time window did not differ between the high and low-constraining conditions. Previous experiments revealed differences between high and low-constraining contexts of congruent semantic words leading to larger N400 components and larger frontally distributed LPCs (Federmeier et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">2007</xref>; DeLong et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">2011</xref>; Thornhill and Van Petten, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">2012</xref>; Van Petten and Luka, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">2012</xref>). Therefore, we also analyzed the effect of contextual constraint in the congruent condition. Again, the findings within the N400 time window mimic previous results with the N400 component of high cloze words being smaller compared to that of the low cloze words (DeLong et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">2011</xref>; Kutas and Federmeier, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">2011</xref>). We did, however, not find any differences with respect to contextual constraint within the LPC time window. The fact that the N400-results were compatible with previous findings does suggest that our experimental procedure was successful in achieving the desired contrast between high and low contextual constraint. Therefore, the findings within the LPC time window challenge theories presupposing that the LPC is mainly associated with processes driven by semantic expectancies (Federmeier et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">2007</xref>; DeLong et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">2011</xref>), as they would predict a modulation of the LPC based on the strength of contextual constraint.</p><p>Another potential factor which may play a role in the elicitation of the LPC are individual characteristics of the participants, as previous research revealed individual variation in ERP effects (Osterhout et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">1997</xref>) and even more specifically in the LPC (Nieuwland and Van Berkum, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">2008</xref>). Our relatively large dataset gave us the opportunity to explore individual variation within the LPC latency range. For our 72 participants we observed substantial inter-individual variation in the LPC latency window, with about one half of the participants showing an extended negative effect and the other half exhibiting an LPC (see Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>A). This was in contrast to the N400 latency window in which the individual effects showed hardly any variation with respect to polarity (see Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>B). To get an estimate about the standard amount of noise generated by the processing of an incoming word within our paradigm, we analyzed the variation of the ERP effects of another word within the same sentence (e.g., the word two positions before the critical word). Even though we observe some variation for these words, this variation is smaller compared to the variation observed for the LPC of the critical words, indicating that the variation found for the LPC not merely reflects noise (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>C). To gain further insight in whether the inter-individual variation observed for the effects within the LPC latency window was systematic, we looked at correlations with other manipulations at the individual level. We reasoned that if the variation was systematic, it should be associated with other manipulations affecting related ERP effects. Therefore, we analyzed whether the LPC and the P600 effect, elicited by a subject-verb agreement manipulation, were correlated. We found that the sizes of the individual ERP effects within the LPC time window of the semantic manipulation were indeed correlated with the sizes of the individual P600 effects. Moreover, the variation observed for the word positioned two words before the critical word of the semantic manipulation did not correlate with the syntactic manipulation.</p><p>Our dataset also contained a semantic-thematic manipulation for which an N400 effect was found (Kos et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">2010</xref>). It is to be expected that similar processes underlie the two semantic manipulations and that the individual variation within the LPC latency window of these two manipulations is closely correlated. Statistical analyses indeed revealed that the individual ERP responses within the LPC time window of the semantic manipulation were strongly correlated with the responses elicited by the semantic-thematic manipulation. Again, the variation found for the word positioned two words before the critical word was unrelated to this semantic-thematic manipulation. These findings confirmed that the individual variation observed for the LPC is systematic and is therefore indicative of an underlying cognitive process, which differs between participants.</p><p>Previous research points to differences in working memory playing a role in the elicitation of the LPC (Van Petten et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">1997</xref>). We did, however, not replicate the correlation between inter-individual variation within the LPC time window and working memory performance. Earlier research suggests that gender differences play a role in differences in semantic processing and the elicitation of the LPC (Daltrozzo et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">2007</xref>), but also this factor could not account for the individual variation in the LPC. It has been suggested that familial left-handedness is related to individual differences in language processing (Townsend et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">2001</xref>). We observed that a substantial part of our participants with one or two left-handed parents (i.e., 11 out of 14) are in the negative responders group. Handedness of family members and concomitant processing strategies may be related to the elicitation of the LPC. However, future research testing more balanced samples of right-handed participants with and without left-handed family members is necessary to draw more firm conclusions concerning this potential factor in elicitation of the LPC.</p><p>Individual variation in patterns of language-related ERPs has been reported before. Nieuwland and Van Berkum (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">2008</xref>) showed that some individuals elicited an LPC to referentially ambiguous nouns, whereas others did not. However, individual variation has not only been found with respect to the LPC. Also for other language-related tasks inter-individual variation has been observed, and this variation has been explained by a variety of factors. It has, for instance, been found that variation in syntactic processing is related to one&#x02019;s proficiency in grammar and vocabulary (Pakulak and Neville, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">2010</xref>). Ye and Zhou (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">2008</xref>) showed that differences in the processing of conflicting sentence representations were related to individual differences in cognitive control (quantified by performance on a Stroop task). Another sentence processing study using ERPs revealed that individual differences in verbal social information processing could be explained by individuals&#x02019; cognitive styles, related to one&#x02019;s ability to empathize (Van den Brink et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">2012</xref>). Additionally, studies investigating heritability or genetic effects reveal heritable variation in language processing across healthy individuals (Ramus and Fisher, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">2009</xref>; Snijders, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">2010</xref>). In sum, various individual factors may account for the inter-individual variation found for the LPC. Future ERP studies investigating semantic processing could take this variation into account when attempting to elucidate the nature of the individual differences by balancing the number of right-handed participants with and without left-handed family members, as well as obtaining additional individual behavioral measures such as measures of cognitive style or vocabulary.</p><p>With the lack of identification of an individual factor responsible for the elicitation of the LPC, we can only give tentative suggestions with respect to the functional process underlying the LPC. Partly based on findings in a recent fMRI study (Burholt Kristensen et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">2012</xref>), we have come to realize that across a sentence depth of processing may vary. This is related to what has been referred to as &#x0201c;good-enough&#x0201d; processing (Ferreira, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">2003</xref>). Violations of either type (semantic, grammatical) next to their language-related signatures (e.g., N400, P600) may also be triggers that recruit general attentional resources for more in-depth processing. Analogous to markers of Information Structure, violations could serve as triggering signals for deeper processing. The LPC is in this case a marker of (recruiting attentional resources for) deeper or extended processing, which should be distinguished from the P600. Here one can easily expect individual differences in the degree to which the violations trigger additional processing.</p><p>In conclusion, our results revealed substantial and systematic inter-individual variation within the LPC time window across a relatively large sample of subjects. In ERP studies it is common practice to average over participants and to assume that the averaged ERP waveform is indicative of similar neuronal processes in all participants. However, some ERP effects seem to be subject to inter-individual variability and in these cases the grand-average can obscure the differential underlying processes of participants. Importantly, variation between individuals may partly explain the inconsistency in results with respect to the LPC across experiments. Therefore, inter-individual variation is a factor to take into account in studies investigating language processing.</p></sec><sec><title>Conflict of Interest Statement</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec></body><back><ack><p>This research was supported by a SPINOZA prize from the Netherlands Organization for Scientific Research (NWO) to Peter Hagoort. We thank Robert Oostenveld for his advice on the analyses.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baaijen</surname><given-names>R. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Piepenbrock</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Rijn</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>). <source>The CELEX Lexical Database (CD-ROM)</source>. <publisher-loc>Philadelphia</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Linguistic Data Consortium, University of Pennsylvania</publisher-name></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baggio</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Choma</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>van Lambalgen</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hagoort</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Coercion and compositionality</article-title>. <source>J. Cogn. Neurosci.</source>
<volume>22</volume>, <fpage>2131</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2140</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1162/jocn.2009.21303</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19583469</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Burholt Kristensen</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Petersson</surname><given-names>K. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hagoort</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>The interface between language and attention: prosodic focus marking recruits a general attention network in spoken language comprehension</article-title>. <source>Cereb. Cortex</source><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/cercor/bhs164</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Daltrozzo</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wioland</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kotchoubey</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Sex differences in two event-related potentials components related to semantic priming</article-title>. <source>Arch. Sex. Behav.</source>
<volume>36</volume>, <fpage>555</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>568</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10508-006-9161-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17334908</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>DeLong</surname><given-names>K. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Urbach</surname><given-names>T. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Groppe</surname><given-names>D. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kutas</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Overlapping dual ERP responses to low cloze probability sentence continuations</article-title>. <source>Psychophysiology</source>
<volume>48</volume>, <fpage>1203</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1207</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-8986.2011.01199.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21457275</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Federmeier</surname><given-names>K. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wlotko</surname><given-names>E. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>De Ochoa-Dewald</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kutas</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Multiple effects of sentential constraint on word processing</article-title>. <source>Brain Res.</source>
<volume>1146</volume>, <fpage>75</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>84</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.brainres.2006.06.101</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16901469</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ferreira</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>The misinterpretation of noncanonical sentences</article-title>. <source>Cogn. Psychol.</source>
<volume>47</volume>, <fpage>164</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>203</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0010-0285(03)00005-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12948517</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Friederici</surname><given-names>A. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Steinhauer</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mecklinger</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>Working memory constraints on syntactic ambiguity resolution as revealed by electrical brain responses</article-title>. <source>Biol. Psychol.</source>
<volume>47</volume>, <fpage>193</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>221</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0301-0511(97)00033-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9564450</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Geyer</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Holcomb</surname><given-names>P. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuperberg</surname><given-names>G. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pearlmutter</surname><given-names>N. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Plausibility and sentence comprehension. An ERP study</article-title>. <source>J. Cogn. Neurosci. Suppl.</source> [abstract].</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gunter</surname><given-names>T. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Friederici</surname><given-names>A. D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Working memory and lexical ambiguity resolution as revealed by ERPs: a difficult case for activation theories</article-title>. <source>J. Cogn. Neurosci.</source>
<volume>15</volume>, <fpage>643</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>657</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1162/jocn.2003.15.5.643</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12965038</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hagoort</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Groothusen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>). <article-title>The syntactic positive shift (Sps) as an ERP measure of syntactic processing</article-title>. <source>Lang. Cogn. Process.</source>
<volume>8</volume>, <fpage>439</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>483</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/01690969308407585</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hagoort</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hald</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bastiaansen</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Petersson</surname><given-names>K. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Integration of word meaning and world knowledge in language comprehension</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>304</volume>, <fpage>438</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>441</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1095455</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15031438</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kolk</surname><given-names>H. H. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chwilla</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Herten</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Oor</surname><given-names>P. J. W.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Structure and limited capacity in verbal working memory: a study with event-related potentials</article-title>. <source>Brain Lang.</source>
<volume>85</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>36</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0093-934X(02)00548-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12681346</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kos</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vosse</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Van den Brink</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hagoort</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>About edible restaurants: conflicts between syntax and semantics as revealed by ERPs</article-title>. <source>Front. Psychol.</source>
<volume>1</volume>:<fpage>222</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpsyg.2010.00222</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21833277</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kuperberg</surname><given-names>G. R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Neural mechanisms of language comprehension: challenges to syntax</article-title>. <source>Brain Res.</source>
<volume>1146</volume>, <fpage>23</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>49</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.brainres.2006.12.063</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17400197</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kutas</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Federmeier</surname><given-names>K. D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Thirty years and counting: finding meaning in the N400 component of the event-related brain potential (ERP)</article-title>. <source>Annu. Rev. Psychol.</source>
<volume>62</volume>, <fpage>621</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>647</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.psych.093008.131123</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20809790</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kutas</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hillyard</surname><given-names>S. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1980</year>). <article-title>Reading senseless sentences &#x02013; brain potentials reflect semantic incongruity</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>207</volume>, <fpage>203</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>205</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.7350657</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7350657</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kutas</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Petten</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <article-title>&#x0201c;Psycholinguistics electrified: event-related potential investigations,&#x0201d;</article-title> in <source>Handbook of Psycholinguistics</source>, ed. <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Gernsbacher</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Academic Press</publisher-name>), <fpage>83</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>143</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>M&#x000fc;nte</surname><given-names>T. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Heinze</surname><given-names>H. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Matzke</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wieringa</surname><given-names>B. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Johannes</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>Brain potentials and syntactic violations revisited: no evidence for specificity of the syntactic positive shift</article-title>. <source>Neuropsychologia</source>
<volume>36</volume>, <fpage>217</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>226</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0028-3932(97)00119-X</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9622187</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nakano</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Saron</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Swaab</surname><given-names>T. Y.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Speech and span: working memory capacity impacts the use of animacy but not of world knowledge during spoken sentence comprehension</article-title>. <source>J. Cogn. Neurosci.</source>
<volume>22</volume>, <fpage>2886</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2898</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1162/jocn.2009.21400</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19929760</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nieuwland</surname><given-names>M. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Berkum</surname><given-names>J. J. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>The interplay between semantic and referential aspects of anaphoric noun phrase resolution: evidence from ERPs</article-title>. <source>Brain Lang.</source>
<volume>106</volume>, <fpage>119</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>131</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bandl.2008.05.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18556057</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Osterhout</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>McLaughlin</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bersick</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>Event-related brain potentials and human language</article-title>. <source>Trends Cogn. Sci.</source>
<volume>1</volume>, <fpage>203</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>209</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1364-6613(97)01073-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21223908</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Osterhout</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mobley</surname><given-names>L. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>Event-related brain potentials elicited by failure to agree</article-title>. <source>J. Mem. Lang.</source>
<volume>34</volume>, <fpage>739</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>773</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/jmla.1995.1033</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Otten</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Berkum</surname><given-names>J. J. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Does working memory capacity affect the ability to predict upcoming words in de the discourse?</article-title>
<source>Brain Res.</source>
<volume>1291</volume>, <fpage>92</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>101</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.brainres.2009.07.042</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19631622</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pakulak</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Neville</surname><given-names>H. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Proficiency differences in syntactic processing of monolingual native speakers indexed by event-related potentials</article-title>. <source>J. Cogn. Neurosci.</source>
<volume>22</volume>, <fpage>2728</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2744</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1162/jocn.2009.21393</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19925188</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ramus</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>S. E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>&#x0201c;Genetics of Language,&#x0201d;</article-title> in <source>The New Cognitive Neuroscience</source>, <edition>4th Edn</edition>, ed. <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Gazzaniga</surname><given-names>M. S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<publisher-loc>Cambridge, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>MIT Press</publisher-name>), <fpage>855</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>871</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sanford</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Leuthold</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bohan</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanford</surname><given-names>A. J. S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Anomalies at the borderline of awareness: an ERP study</article-title>. <source>J. Cogn. Neurosci.</source>
<volume>23</volume>, <fpage>514</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>523</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1162/jocn.2009.21370</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19925201</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Severens</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hartsuiker</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Is there a lexical bias effect in comprehension monitoring?</article-title>
<source>Lang. Cogn. Process.</source>
<volume>24</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>18</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/01690960902775517</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Snijders</surname><given-names>T. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <source>More than Words. Neural and Genetic Dynamics of Syntactic Unification</source>. <publisher-loc>Nijmegen</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Radboud University Nijmegen</publisher-name></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>St George</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mannes</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoffman</surname><given-names>J. E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>Individual differences in inference generation: an ERP analysis</article-title>. <source>J. Cogn. Neurosci.</source>
<volume>9</volume>, <fpage>776</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>787</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1162/jocn.1997.9.6.776</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stroud</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Examining the evidence for an independent semantic analyzer: an ERP study in Spanish</article-title>. <source>Brain Lang.</source>
<volume>120</volume>, <fpage>108</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>126</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bandl.2011.02.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21377198</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Swaab</surname><given-names>T. Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hagoort</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>Spoken sentence comprehension in aphasia: event-related potential evidence for a lexical integration deficit</article-title>. <source>J. Cogn. Neurosci.</source>
<volume>9</volume>, <fpage>39</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>66</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1162/jocn.1997.9.1.39</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Szewczyk</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schriefers</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Is animacy special? ERP correlates of semantic violations and animacy violations in sentence processing</article-title>. <source>Brain Res.</source>
<volume>1368</volume>, <fpage>208</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>221</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.brainres.2010.10.070</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21029726</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thornhill</surname><given-names>D. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Petten</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Lexical versus conceptual anticipation during sentence processing: frontal positivity and N400 ERP components</article-title>. <source>Int. J. Psychophysiol.</source>
<volume>83</volume>, <fpage>382</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>392</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijpsycho.2011.12.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22226800</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Townsend</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carrithers</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bever</surname><given-names>T. G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Familial handedness and access to words, meaning, and syntax during sentence comprehension</article-title>. <source>Brain Lang.</source>
<volume>78</volume>, <fpage>308</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>331</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/brln.2001.2469</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11703060</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van Berkum</surname><given-names>J. J. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Van den Brink</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tesink</surname><given-names>C. M. J. Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kos</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hagoort</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>The neural integration of speaker and message</article-title>. <source>J. Cogn. Neurosci.</source>
<volume>20</volume>, <fpage>580</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>591</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1162/jocn.2008.20054</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18052777</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van de Meerendonk</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kolk</surname><given-names>H. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vissers</surname><given-names>C. T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chwilla</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Monitoring in language perception: mild and strong conflicts elicit different ERP patterns</article-title>. <source>J. Cogn. Neurosci.</source>
<volume>22</volume>, <fpage>67</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>82</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1162/jocn.2008.21170</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19199401</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van den Brink</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>C. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hagoort</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Electrophysiological evidence for early contextual influences during spoken-word recognition: N200 versus N400 effects</article-title>. <source>J. Cogn. Neurosci.</source>
<volume>13</volume>, <fpage>967</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>985</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1162/089892901753165872</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11595099</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van den Brink</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>C. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hagoort</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>The cascaded nature of lexical selection and integration in auditory sentence processing</article-title>. <source>J. Exp. Psychol. Learn. Mem. Cogn.</source>
<volume>32</volume>, <fpage>364</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>372</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/0278-7393.32.3.364</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16569152</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van den Brink</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Berkum</surname><given-names>J. J. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bastiaansen</surname><given-names>M. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tesink</surname><given-names>C. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kos</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Buitelaar</surname><given-names>J. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hagoort</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Empathy matters: ERP evidence for inter-individual differences in social language processing</article-title>. <source>Soc. Cogn. Affect Neurosci.</source>
<volume>7</volume>, <fpage>173</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>183</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/scan/nsq094</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21148175</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van den Noort</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bosch</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Haverkort</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hugdahl</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>A standard computerized version of the reading span test in different languages</article-title>. <source>Eur. J. Psychol. Assess.</source>
<volume>24</volume>, <fpage>35</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>42</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1027/1015-5759.24.1.35</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van der Beek</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bouma</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Malouf</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>van Noord</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group> (eds.). (<year>2001</year>). <source>The Alpino Dependency Treebank</source>. <publisher-loc>Amsterdam</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Rodopi</publisher-name></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van Petten</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Luka</surname><given-names>B. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Prediction during language comprehension: benefits, costs, and ERP components</article-title>. <source>Int. J. Psychophysiol.</source>
<volume>83</volume>, <fpage>176</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>190</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijpsycho.2011.09.015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22019481</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van Petten</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Weckerly</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>McIsaac</surname><given-names>H. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kutas</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>Working memory capacity dissociates lexical and sentential context effects</article-title>. <source>Psychol. Sci.</source>
<volume>8</volume>, <fpage>238</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>242</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1467-9280.1997.tb00418.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Involvement of cognitive control in sentence comprehension: evidence from ERPs</article-title>. <source>Brain Res.</source>
<volume>1203</volume>, <fpage>103</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>115</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.brainres.2008.01.090</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18313650</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>