<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">R Soc Open Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">R Soc Open Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">RSOS</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">royopensci</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Royal Society Open Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2054-5703</issn><publisher><publisher-name>The Royal Society Publishing</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">29410830</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">5792907</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rsos.171186</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">rsos171186</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="hwp-journal-coll"><subject>1006</subject><subject>192</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Chemistry</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="leader"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Nanostructure selenium compounds as pseudocapacitive electrodes for high-performance asymmetric supercapacitor</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="short">Selenium compounds based supercapacitor</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-2142-0146</contrib-id><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>Guofu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1">1</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hua</surname><given-names>Fengting</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Kanjun</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fenga</surname><given-names>Enke</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>Hui</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Zhiguo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lei</surname><given-names>Ziqiang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1">1</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor2"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="af1"><label>1</label><institution>Key Laboratory of Eco-Environment-Related Polymer Materials of Ministry of Education, Key Laboratory of Polymer Materials of Gansu Province, College of Chemistry and Chemical Engineering, Northwest Normal University</institution>, <addr-line>Lanzhou 730070</addr-line>, <country>People's Republic of China</country></aff><aff id="af2"><label>2</label><institution>College of Chemistry and Environmental Science, Lanzhou City University</institution>, <addr-line>Lanzhou 730070</addr-line>, <country>People's Republic of China</country></aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">Authors for correspondence: Guofu Ma e-mail: <email>magf@nwnu.edu.cn</email></corresp><corresp id="cor2">Authors for correspondence: Ziqiang Lei e-mail: <email>leizq@nwnu.edu.cn</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other"><p>This article has been edited by the Royal Society of Chemistry, including the commissioning, peer review process and editorial aspects up to the point of acceptance.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>1</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>10</day><month>1</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>10</day><month>1</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the <pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. --><volume>5</volume><issue>1</issue><elocation-id>171186</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>1</day><month>9</month><year>2017</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>8</day><month>11</month><year>2017</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2018 The Authors.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2018</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>Published by the Royal Society under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="rsos171186.pdf"/><self-uri content-type="reviewer_comments" xlink:href="rsos171186_review_history.pdf"/><abstract><p>The electrochemical performance of an energy conversion and storage device like the supercapacitor mainly depends on the microstructure and morphology of the electrodes. In this paper, to improve the capacitance performance of the supercapacitor, the all-pseudocapacitive electrodes of lamella-like Bi<sub>18</sub>SeO<sub>29</sub>/BiSe as the negative electrode and flower-like Co<sub>0.85</sub>Se nanosheets as the positive electrode are synthesized by using a facile low-temperature one-step hydrothermal method. The microstructures and morphology of the electrode materials are carefully characterized, and the capacitance performances are also tested. The Bi<sub>18</sub>SeO<sub>29</sub>/BiSe and Co<sub>0.85</sub>Se have high specific capacitance (471.3&#x02009;F&#x02009;g<sup>&#x02013;1</sup> and 255&#x02009;F&#x02009;g<sup>&#x02013;1</sup> at 0.5&#x02009;A&#x02009;g<sup>&#x02013;1</sup>), high conductivity, outstanding cycling stability, as well as good rate capability. The assembled asymmetric supercapacitor completely based on the pseudocapacitive electrodes exhibits outstanding cycling stability (about 93% capacitance retention after 5000 cycles). Moreover, the devices exhibit high energy density of 24.2&#x02009;Wh&#x02009;kg<sup>&#x02013;1</sup> at a power density of 871.2&#x02009;W&#x02009;kg<sup>&#x02013;1</sup> in the voltage window of 0&#x02013;1.6&#x02009;V with 2&#x02009;M KOH solution.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Bi<sub>18</sub>SeO<sub>29</sub>/BiSe</kwd><kwd>Co<sub>0.85</sub>Se</kwd><kwd>asymmetric supercapacitor</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution>Changjiang Scholars and Innovative Research Team</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>IRT15R56</award-id></award-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution>National Natural Science Foundation of China</institution><institution-id>http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100001809</institution-id></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>21164009</award-id><award-id>21174114</award-id></award-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution>Key Laboratory of Polymer Materials of Gansu Province</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source></award-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution>Key Laboratory of Eco-Environment-Related Polymer Materials (Northwest Normal University) of Ministry of Education</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source></award-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution>China Postdoctoral Science Foundation</institution><institution-id>http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100002858</institution-id></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>2013M540778</award-id></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>cover-date</meta-name><meta-value>January, 2018</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><label>1.</label><title>Introduction</title><p>Supercapacitors, prospective energy storage and conversion devices, have attracted tremendous interest due to the need for power output devices for digital communications and electric vehicles owing to their facile manufacture, fast charging/discharge, long cycle life and higher power density than batteries [<xref rid="RSOS171186C1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="RSOS171186C4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Intrinsically, supercapacitors based on the principle of charge storage are divided into two types: pseudocapacitors and electric double-layer capacitors (EDLCs) [<xref rid="RSOS171186C5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. In EDLCs, the charges are stored because of the surface adsorption of the ions from the electrolyte as a result of electrostatic attraction, thus forming two charged layers (double layer). Pseudocapacitors store charges by fast and reversible oxidation/reduction (Faradaic) reactions occurring at the electrode/electrolyte interfaces, as well as in the bulk near the surface of the electrode. Pseudocapacitors show higher capacitance when compared with EDLC-type devices due to the additional charge transferred within the defined potential [<xref rid="RSOS171186C6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="RSOS171186C8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>].</p><p>Up to now, electrode materials with long cycle stability and high capacitance have obtained breakthrough progress, for instance transition metal sulfides (CuS [<xref rid="RSOS171186C9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>], FeS [<xref rid="RSOS171186C10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>], Al<sub>2</sub>S<sub>3</sub> [<xref rid="RSOS171186C11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>], etc.), transition metal oxides/hydroxides (NiO [<xref rid="RSOS171186C12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>], ZnO [<xref rid="RSOS171186C13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>], TiO<sub>2</sub> [<xref rid="RSOS171186C14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>], Co(OH)<sub>2</sub> [<xref rid="RSOS171186C15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>], CoNi<sub>2</sub>S<sub>4</sub> [<xref rid="RSOS171186C16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>], etc.) as well as conducting polymer materials (polyaniline [<xref rid="RSOS171186C17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>], polypyrrole [<xref rid="RSOS171186C18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>], etc.). The above electrode materials have been investigated for use in asymmetric supercapacitors extensively, due to their fast reversible redox reactions, cost-effectiveness, easy processability and relatively good cyclic stability [<xref rid="RSOS171186C19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. However, compared with the transition metal dichalcogenide, the two-dimensional (2D) layered transition metal selenide has been paid less attention. The weak van der Waals force of 2D layered metal selenide is beneficial for insertion of guest species. Owing to their superior electronic structure and physical properties, the 2D nanosheet structural materials have attracted abundant attention compared to the corresponding bulk materials [<xref rid="RSOS171186C20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. Recently, transition metal selenide has been shown to display outstanding electrochemical performance. Balasingam <italic>et al</italic>. have synthesized a few-layered MoSe<sub>2</sub> nanosheet by a simple hydrothermal method and further studied its electrochemical charge storage properties. It is shown that the MoSe<sub>2</sub> nanosheet electrode provides a symmetric device that exhibits 49.7&#x02009;F&#x02009;g<sup>&#x02013;1</sup> with a scan rate of 2&#x02009;mV&#x02009;s<sup>&#x02013;1</sup> and a largest specific capacitance of 198.9&#x02009;F&#x02009;g<sup>&#x02013;1</sup> [<xref rid="RSOS171186C21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Wang <italic>et al</italic>. made a flexible all-solid-state supercapacitor based on three-dimensional (3D) hierarchical GeSe<sub>2</sub> nanomaterials, which have a high specific capacitance of 300&#x02009;F&#x02009;g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> at a current density of 1&#x02009;A&#x02009;g<sup>&#x02013;1</sup>[<xref rid="RSOS171186C22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Choi <italic>et al</italic>. synthesized SnSe<sub>2</sub> nanoplate&#x02013;graphene composites and used them as a novel anode material for lithium ion batteries [<xref rid="RSOS171186C23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. Tang <italic>et al</italic>. synthesized a new type of binder-free electrode material of NiSe/NF (NiSe nanowire film on nickel foam) by using the one-step hydrothermal method; it has a high specific capacitance of 1790&#x02009;F&#x02009;g<sup>&#x02013;1</sup> at a current density of 5&#x02009;A&#x02009;g<sup>&#x02013;1</sup> [<xref rid="RSOS171186C24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. Yang <italic>et al</italic>. developed interconnected Co<sub>0.85</sub>Se nanomaterials on nickel foam directly through a facile single-step hydrothermal method, which exhibits a high specific capacitance of 1528&#x02009;F&#x02009;g<sup>&#x02013;1</sup> at 1&#x02009;A&#x02009;g<sup>&#x02013;1</sup> and excellent cycling stability [<xref rid="RSOS171186C25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. Therefore, the transition metal selenide possesses outstanding electrochemical energy storage properties and deserves to be further investigated as an advanced electrode material for supercapacitor application.</p><p>In recent years, in order to improve energy density and power density to attain a win&#x02013;win situation, researchers have assembled asymmetric supercapacitors (ASCs) with different electrode materials in aqueous electrolytes [<xref rid="RSOS171186C26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="RSOS171186C30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. According to the literature, <italic>E</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;1/2<italic>CV</italic><sup>2</sup> (energy density formula); in order to improve energy density (<italic>E</italic>), two approaches can be used: maximizing the specific capacitance (<italic>C</italic>) and/or enlarging the operating potential window (<italic>V</italic>). Employing ionic liquids or organic electrolytes can increase the operating voltage effectively. However, their inherent deficiencies such as poor ionic conductivity and sometimes toxicity have hindered their practical application [<xref rid="RSOS171186C26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="RSOS171186C27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. In comparison, an aqueous electrolyte is the best choice. The ASC is made up of two different electrodes, hence it is an essential prerequisite to select appropriate positive and negative electrode materials to assemble a high-performance ASC. Recently, the literature has depicted that the transition metal selenide has excellent electrochemical performance for a supercapacitor. But the synthesis of different selenium compounds as the positive and negative electrodes of a supercapacitor in the same system has not been well explored so far. In addition, the benzyl alcohol route in particular has been proved to be versatile for the synthesis of various metal oxide nanoparticles with good control over particle phase, size and shape [<xref rid="RSOS171186C28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="RSOS171186C29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. The fact that the benzyl alcohol route is typically applied without the use of surfactants makes this approach ideal for mechanistic studies. Additives such as surfactants complicate the interpretation of the results due to their possible influence on nucleation and growth by complexation of cations [<xref rid="RSOS171186C30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,<xref rid="RSOS171186C31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. Therefore, in a two-component system just consisting of a precursor and solvent, the complexity is decreased to a minimum, although benzyl alcohol itself may play multiple roles as reaction medium, oxygen source and/or capping agent. Another unique feature of non-aqueous systems is the possibility to monitor the organic reactions occurring in parallel to nanoparticle formation by standard analytical techniques. Thus, the use of benzyl alcohol as a solvent (without any template and surfactant) to synthesize transition metal selenium-based compounds is a very desirable route.</p><p>In this work, we have used a facile low-temperature one-step hydrothermal method without any template and surfactant (benzyl alcohol as the solvent) to synthesize two different transition metal selenides: Bi<sub>18</sub>SeO<sub>29</sub>/BiSe and Co<sub>0.85</sub>Se. The lamella-like Bi<sub>18</sub>SeO<sub>29</sub>/BiSe and petal-like Co<sub>0.85</sub>Se, which are used as negative and positive electrode materials, have high specific capacitance in aqueous electrolyte. The assembled ASCs possess excellent energy density and outstanding power density with a wide voltage window as well as high cycling stability in aqueous electrolyte.</p></sec><sec id="s2"><label>2.</label><title>Experimental</title><sec id="s2a"><label>2.1.</label><title>Materials</title><p>Bismuth nitrate pentahydrate (Bi(NO<sub>3</sub>)<sub>3</sub>&#x02022;5H<sub>2</sub>O, Aladdin Industrial corporation, Shanghai, China), cobalt nitrate hexahydrate (Co(NO<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>&#x02022;6H<sub>2</sub>O, Aladdin Industrial corporation, Shanghai, China), selenium oxide (SeO<sub>2</sub>, Sitong Tianjin Chemical Reagent Co. Ltd, China) and benzyl alcohol (Aladdin Industrial corporation, Shanghai, China). All chemical reagents were of analytical grade and were not further purified before use.</p></sec><sec id="s2b"><label>2.2.</label><title>Synthesis of Bi<sub>18</sub>SeO<sub>29</sub>/BiSe nanocomposite</title><p>The Bi<sub>18</sub>SeO<sub>29</sub>/BiSe nanocomposites were synthesized using the hydrothermal method in benzyl alcohol. In the typical process, Bi(NO<sub>3</sub>)<sub>3</sub>&#x02022;5H<sub>2</sub>O (0.582&#x02009;g) and SeO<sub>2</sub> (0.111&#x02009;g) were dispersed in benzyl alcohol solution (35&#x02009;ml), stirring uniformly for 1&#x02009;h with the assistance of ultrasonic vibration. After stirring vigorously at room temperature for about 10&#x02009;min, the white solution was transferred to a 50&#x02009;ml Teflon-lined stainless steel autoclave and heated at 180&#x000b0;C for 15&#x02009;h. Finally, the resulting greyish precipitate was collected by centrifugation and on cooling to room temperature naturally. Subsequently, the greyish precipitate was washed with distilled water and ethanol several times to remove any possible ions and dried in a vacuum at 65&#x000b0;C overnight.</p></sec><sec id="s2c"><label>2.3.</label><title>Synthesis of Co<sub>0.85</sub>Se nanomaterials</title><p>The cobaltous selenide (Co<sub>0.85</sub>Se) nanosheets may also be synthesized by the hydrothermal method in benzyl alcohol solution; using 0.349&#x02009;g Co(NO<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>&#x02022;6H<sub>2</sub>O and 0.111&#x02009;g SeO<sub>2</sub> as raw materials, the process was similar to the synthesis of Bi<sub>18</sub>SeO<sub>29</sub>/BiSe nanocomposites.</p></sec><sec id="s2d"><label>2.4.</label><title>Materials characterization</title><p>The morphologies of Bi<sub>18</sub>SeO<sub>29</sub>/BiSe and Co<sub>0.85</sub>Se were analysed using field emission scanning electron microscopy (SEM, Ultra Plus, Carl Zeiss) with a voltage of 5.0&#x02009;kV. The microstructure of Bi<sub>18</sub>SeO<sub>29</sub>/BiSe and Co<sub>0.85</sub>Se were further characterized by transmission electron microscopy (TEM, JEM-2010 Japan). The crystallographic structure of the materials was degassed at 200&#x000b0;C before nitrogen adsorption measurement. X-ray diffraction (XRD) was conducted using a Rigaku D/Max-2400 diffractometer, with Cu Ka radiation (<italic>&#x003bb;</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.15418&#x02009;nm) at 40&#x02009;kV and 100&#x02009;mA. X-ray photoelectron spectroscopy (XPS) was performed using an Escalab 210 system (Germany). In the SEM, the elemental mapping of relative energy-dispersive X-ray spectrometry (EDS) was performed by a probe focused to 0.2&#x02009;nm with a camera length of 20&#x02009;cm.</p></sec><sec id="s2e"><label>2.5.</label><title>Electrochemical measurements</title><sec id="s2e1"><label>2.5.1.</label><title>Three-electrode system</title><p>The electrochemical performance of Bi<sub>18</sub>SeO<sub>29</sub>/BiSe and Co<sub>0.85</sub>Se was studied in 2&#x02009;M KOH solution using a three-electrode system. High-purity carbon rods and oxidation of saturated mercury electrode (Hg/HgO) were used as the counter electrode and the reference electrode, respectively. The working electrodes were manufactured as follows: in general, 80&#x02009;wt% electrode materials (16.0&#x02009;mg), 10&#x02009;wt% commercial carbon black (acetylene black, 2.0&#x02009;mg) as well as 10&#x02009;wt% polymer binder (polyvinylidene fluoride, 2&#x02009;mg) were mixed with some <italic>N</italic>-methyl-2-pyrrolidone to form a homogeneous slurry. Further, the obtained slurry was coated on nickel foam with an area of 1.0&#x02009;cm<sup>2</sup> and dried at 65&#x000b0;C overnight, and then weighed and pressed into sheets under 13&#x02009;MPa to ensure adherence between the active materials and the current collector. The total mass of each electrode was limited to 3.0&#x02013;5.0&#x02009;mg [<xref rid="RSOS171186C32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="s2e2"><label>2.5.2.</label><title>Two-electrode system of asymmetric supercapacitors</title><p>The electrochemical measurements were further taken using a two-electrode system consisting of Bi<sub>18</sub>SeO<sub>29</sub>/BiSe and Co<sub>0.85</sub>Se electrodes in 2&#x02009;M KOH electrolyte. The working electrodes of the two electrode system were fabricated similarly to the three electrodes. The as-prepared slurry was spread on the rounded nickel foam mesh current collector with an area of 1&#x02009;cm<sup>2</sup> uniformly, and the coating was left in an oven at 65&#x000b0;C overnight. Afterwards, this was weighed and pressed into sheets under 13&#x02009;MPa to ensure adherence between the active materials and the current collector. The total mass of each electrode was limited to 3.0&#x02013;5.0&#x02009;mg. Two different electrodes of the same or very close weight were selected for measurement.</p><p>Finally, the ASCs were assembled using lamella-like Bi<sub>18</sub>SeO<sub>29</sub>/BiSe as the negative electrode and flower-like Co<sub>0.85</sub>Se as the positive electrode with a separator (filter paper) and electrolyte solution; they were assembled into a sandwich cell construction (electrode/separator/electrode). To uniformly diffuse the KOH electrolyte solution into the pseudocapacitive material electrode, the separated and pseudocapacitive material electrodes were immersed in 2 M KOH electrolyte for 6&#x02009;h and then assembled into the supercapacitor configuration.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s2f"><label>2.6.</label><title>Electrochemical testing</title><p>A CHI660D electrochemical workstation (Shanghai Chenghua Instrument Co. Ltd, China) was used in the three-electrode and two-electrode systems by cyclic voltammetry (CV), galvanostatic charge/discharge (GCD) and electrical impedance spectroscopy (EIS). The EIS measurement was measured at a frequency ranging from 10&#x02009;mHz to 100&#x02009;kHz with an impedance amplitude of &#x000b1;5&#x02009;mV in open circuit potentials. In addition, a LAND CT2001A cell tester (Wuhan Landian electronics Co. Ltd, China) with a computer controlled system was used for the cycle-life stability test.</p><p>In the three-electrode system, the gravimetric capacitances of the Bi<sub>18</sub>SeO<sub>29</sub>/BiSe or Co<sub>0.85</sub>Se sample were calculated from the charge&#x02013;discharge curves based on the following equation:
<disp-formula id="RSOS171186M2.1"><label>2.1</label><mml:math id="DM1"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x00394;</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x00394;</mml:mi><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:math></disp-formula>
where <italic>C</italic><sub>s</sub> corresponds to the specific capacitance (F&#x02009;g<sup>&#x02013;1</sup>), <italic>I</italic> represents the discharge current (A), &#x00394;<italic>t</italic> represents the discharge time (s), <italic>m</italic> refers to the total mass (g) and &#x00394;<italic>V</italic> refers to the voltage change (V) of the Bi<sub>18</sub>SeO<sub>29</sub>/BiSe or Co<sub>0.85</sub>Se.</p><p>For the two-electrode cells of ASCs, it was calculated by the equation
<disp-formula id="RSOS171186M2.2"><label>2.2</label><mml:math id="DM2"><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x00394;</mml:mi><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:math></disp-formula>
To obtain <italic>Q</italic><sup>+</sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;<italic>Q</italic><sup>&#x02212;</sup>, as well as to make use of the largest voltage window, the mass ratio of the positive and negative electrodes are acquired on the basis of the following equations [<xref rid="RSOS171186C33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]:
<disp-formula id="RSOS171186M2.3"><label>2.3</label><mml:math id="DM3"><mml:mtable columnalign="right left right left right left right left right left right left" rowspacing="3pt" columnspacing="0.278em 2em 0.278em 2em 0.278em 2em 0.278em 2em 0.278em 2em 0.278em"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x00394;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x00394;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="RSOS171186M2.4"><label>2.4</label><mml:math id="DM4"><mml:mtable columnalign="right left right left right left right left right left right left" rowspacing="3pt" columnspacing="0.278em 2em 0.278em 2em 0.278em 2em 0.278em 2em 0.278em 2em 0.278em"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">cell</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x00394;</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x00394;</mml:mi><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="RSOS171186M2.5"><label>2.5</label><mml:math id="DM5"><mml:mtable columnalign="right left right left right left right left right left right left" rowspacing="3pt" columnspacing="0.278em 2em 0.278em 2em 0.278em 2em 0.278em 2em 0.278em 2em 0.278em"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">cell</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x00394;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1000</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mn>3600</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="RSOS171186M2.6"><label>2.6</label><mml:math id="DM6"><mml:mtable columnalign="right left right left right left right left right left right left" rowspacing="3pt" columnspacing="0.278em 2em 0.278em 2em 0.278em 2em 0.278em 2em 0.278em 2em 0.278em"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mspace width="2em"/><mml:mtext>and</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="2em"/><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3600</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x00394;</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula>
where <inline-formula><mml:math id="IM1"><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:msubsup></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="IM2"><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo></mml:msubsup></mml:math></inline-formula> are the specific capacitances (F&#x02009;g<sup>&#x02013;1</sup>) , and &#x00394;<italic>V<sup>+</sup></italic> and &#x00394;<italic>V</italic><sup>&#x02212;</sup> represent the voltage ranges (V) of the Co<sub>0.85</sub>Se and Bi<sub>18</sub>SeO<sub>29</sub>/BiSe electrodes, respectively. <italic>C</italic><sub>cell</sub> denotes the specific capacitance (F&#x02009;g<sup>&#x02013;1</sup>) of the ASC device, <italic>I</italic> the discharge current (A), &#x00394;<italic>t</italic> the discharge time, <italic>m</italic> the total weight (g) of the two electrodes, &#x00394;<italic>V</italic> the voltage window (V), <italic>E</italic> (Wh&#x02009;kg<sup>&#x02013;1</sup>) the energy density and <italic>P</italic> (W&#x02009;kg<sup>&#x02013;1</sup>) the power density [<xref rid="RSOS171186C34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>].</p></sec></sec><sec id="s3"><label>3.</label><title>Results and discussion</title><sec id="s3a"><label>3.1.</label><title>Negative electrode</title><p>The purity and crystallinity of negative electrode Bi<sub>18</sub>SeO<sub>29</sub>/BiSe were investigated using powder XRD, as displayed in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="RSOS171186F1">figure&#x000a0;1</xref><italic>a</italic>; the peaks can be indexed to the hexagonal Bi<sub>18</sub>SeO<sub>29</sub> phase (JCPDS card no. 42-0098) and the BiSe phase (JCPDS card no. 42-1045) from the XRD pattern. The strong diffraction peaks at 2<italic>&#x003b8;</italic> angles of 27.77, 31.00, 32.74, 45.70, 46.97, 53.16, 55.45 and 57.34 could be readily indexed to the (221), (002), (400), (402), (440), (223), (621) and (442) planes of Bi<sub>18</sub>SeO<sub>29</sub>; the other diffraction peaks at 2<italic>&#x003b8;</italic> angles of 19.16, 29.09, 39.98 and 43.28 can be indexed to the (005), (014), (108) and (110) planes of BiSe, respectively. The microstructure and morphology of Bi<sub>18</sub>SeO<sub>29</sub>/BiSe were investigated by SEM and TEM analyses. As indicated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="RSOS171186F1">figure&#x000a0;1</xref><italic>b</italic>, the Bi<sub>18</sub>SeO<sub>29</sub>/BiSe exhibits a large amount of interconnected and ultrathin nanosheet structure. The high-resolution SEM image (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="RSOS171186F1">figure&#x000a0;1</xref><italic>c</italic>) gives a clear view of the nanosheets, consisting of abundant thin one-dimensional lamella-like structures which are well aligned together with intertwined nanosheet subunits; this can enable the easy flow and transfer of electrons and ions in the nanosheet structure. The unique structure of Bi<sub>18</sub>SeO<sub>29</sub>/BiSe can be further proved by TEM (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="RSOS171186F1">figure&#x000a0;1</xref><italic>d</italic>,<italic>e</italic>), in which are clearly displayed the thin layers with randomly intertwined nanosheet structure. Moreover, the high-resolution TEM image and the corresponding selected area electron diffraction (SAED), as described in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="RSOS171186F1">figure&#x000a0;1</xref><italic>f</italic>, demonstrate the polycrystalline nature of the nanosheets and illustrate clear lattice fringes, which can be assigned to the following crystal planes: 0.321&#x02009;nm for Bi<sub>18</sub>SeO<sub>29</sub> (221), 0.307&#x02009;nm for BiSe (014) and 0.273&#x02009;nm for Bi<sub>18</sub>SeO<sub>29</sub> (400). A SAED image is displayed in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="RSOS171186F1">figure&#x000a0;1</xref><italic>f</italic> inset; the diffraction rings from inside to outside were indexed to the (221), (014), (108), (402) and (440) planes of the hexagonal Bi<sub>18</sub>SeO<sub>29</sub>/BiSe, which exhibits a crystalline characteristic. The clear lattice fringes and SAED are in agreement with the aforementioned XRD results. Although with some reservation, an approximate electrochemically active surface area was calculated from the Brunauer&#x02013;Emmett&#x02013;Teller method (BET) [<xref rid="RSOS171186C35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. The BET surface area of the Bi<sub>18</sub>SeO<sub>29</sub>/BiSe is 19.35&#x02009;m<sup>2</sup>&#x02009;g<sup>&#x02013;1</sup>, as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="RSOS171186F2">figure&#x000a0;2</xref><italic>a</italic>, which is similar to that of pure Co<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> material (18.5&#x02009;m<sup>2</sup>&#x02009;g<sup>&#x02013;1</sup>) [<xref rid="RSOS171186C36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>] and to that of emeraldine-di-hydrogen sulfate (22.1&#x02009;m<sup>2</sup>&#x02009;g<sup>&#x02013;1</sup>) [<xref rid="RSOS171186C37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. The electrochemically active surface area can facilitate intercalation and de-intercalation of electrolyte ions.
<fig id="RSOS171186F1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>(<italic>a</italic>) XRD pattern of Bi<sub>18</sub>SeO<sub>29</sub>/BiSe nanosheets; (<italic>b</italic>,<italic>c</italic>) SEM and (<italic>d</italic>,<italic>e</italic>) TEM images of Bi<sub>18</sub>SeO<sub>29</sub>/BiSe nanosheets at various magnifications; (<italic>f</italic>) high-resolution TEM image of the Bi<sub>18</sub>SeO<sub>29</sub>/BiSe nanosheets.
</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="rsos171186-g1"/></fig>
<fig id="RSOS171186F2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>(<italic>a</italic>) Nitrogen adsorption&#x02013;desorption isotherms and (inset) pore size distribution of Bi<sub>18</sub>SeO<sub>29</sub>/BiSe. (<italic>b</italic>) XPS of Bi<sub>18</sub>SeO<sub>29</sub>/BiSe; (<italic>c</italic>) high-resolution XPS spectra of Bi 4f peak; (<italic>d</italic>) high-resolution XPS spectra of Se 3d peak and (<italic>e</italic>) the corresponding element mapping images (selected from the square region) for the bismuth, selenium and oxygen of Bi<sub>18</sub>SeO<sub>29</sub>/BiSe nanosheets.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="rsos171186-g2"/></fig></p><p>To further confirm the chemical element compositions and the surface valence state information, Bi<sub>18</sub>SeO<sub>29</sub>/BiSe was evaluated by the XPS technique and EDS, as presented in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="RSOS171186F2">figure&#x000a0;2</xref>. In the XPS survey spectrum of Bi<sub>18</sub>SeO<sub>29</sub>/BiSe, the elements of Bi, Se and O as well as C can be clearly identified (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="RSOS171186F2">figure&#x000a0;2</xref><italic>b</italic>). <xref ref-type="fig" rid="RSOS171186F2">Figure&#x000a0;2</xref><italic>c</italic> shows the high-resolution spectrum of the Bi 4f region, which exhibits two asymmetrical main signals corresponding to the deconvolution of Bi 4f7/2 (159.28&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.3&#x02009;eV) and Bi 4f5/2 (164.45&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.3&#x02009;eV) with a spin&#x02013;orbit splitting of about 5.4&#x02009;eV [<xref rid="RSOS171186C38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. The binding energies of 159.28&#x02009;eV and 164.45&#x02009;eV can be attributed to the Bi<sup>3+</sup> ion [<xref rid="RSOS171186C39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. From the significant dispersion of the binding energy, it can be demonstrated that bismuth forms a mixture rather than pure metal oxide [<xref rid="RSOS171186C40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. Further, the core-level spectrum of the Se 3d region is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="RSOS171186F2">figure&#x000a0;2</xref><italic>d</italic>; the binding energy of 58.7&#x02009;eV can be assigned to oxidized Se (SeO<sub>X</sub>), which is in good agreement with previously reported values [<xref rid="RSOS171186C30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. In addition, to verify the elemental distribution, Bi<sub>18</sub>SeO<sub>29</sub>/BiSe was further characterized by EDS (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="RSOS171186F2">figure&#x000a0;2</xref><italic>e</italic>); the corresponding element mapping images can unambiguously confirm the homogeneous distribution of bismuth, selenium and oxygen in the nanomaterial.</p><p>The electrochemical behaviour of Bi<sub>18</sub>SeO<sub>29</sub>/BiSe nanosheets was first studied by CV and GCD techniques with a three-electrode system in 2&#x02009;mol&#x02009;l<sup>&#x02013;1</sup> KOH aqueous electrolyte. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="RSOS171186F3">Figure&#x000a0;3</xref><italic>a</italic> displays the CV curves of the Bi<sub>18</sub>SeO<sub>29</sub>/BiSe nanosheets as the negative electrode at different scan rates ranging from 5 to 30&#x02009;mV&#x02009;s<sup>&#x02013;1</sup> in the potential window of &#x02212;1 to 0&#x02009;V. A pair of redox peaks can be clearly observed in the CV curves of the Bi<sub>18</sub>SeO<sub>29</sub>/BiSe composite at different scan rates, showing it has typical Faradaic pseudocapacitance behaviour. In detail, the oxidation peaks were seen in forward CV scans, while the reduction peaks were seen in the reverse CV scans. In highly alkaline solution, hydroxide ions are generated naturally, which are likely to gravitate towards the cathode at high potentials Thus, the reduction peak at 0.7&#x02009;V corresponds to Bi<sup>3+</sup> transformed into <inline-formula><mml:math id="IM3"><mml:mtext>Bi( OH</mml:mtext><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>)</mml:mtext><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula> in the reduction process. The oxidation peaks at about &#x02212;0.48&#x02009;V and &#x02212;0.35&#x02009;V correspond to Bi<sup>3+</sup>/Bi<sup>0</sup> transformation. Those peaks are also seen in some other studies [<xref rid="RSOS171186C27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,<xref rid="RSOS171186C41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,<xref rid="RSOS171186C42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. It may be catalysed by the induction or oxidation of some unconverted Bi<sup>0</sup> during the reduction process, and the process has the following reaction [<xref rid="RSOS171186C27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,<xref rid="RSOS171186C43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]:
<disp-formula id="RSOS171186UM1"><mml:math id="DM7"><mml:mtable columnalign="right left right left right left right left right left right left" rowspacing="3pt" columnspacing="0.278em 2em 0.278em 2em 0.278em 2em 0.278em 2em 0.278em 2em 0.278em"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd/><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>B</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mtext>O</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mtext>H</mml:mtext><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">&#x02192;</mml:mo><mml:mtext>Bi(OH</mml:mtext><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>)</mml:mtext><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd/><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mtext>Bi(OH</mml:mtext><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>)</mml:mtext><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02009;</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mtext>O</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mtext>H</mml:mtext><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">&#x02192;</mml:mo><mml:mtext>B</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>O</mml:mtext><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>H</mml:mtext><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mtext>O</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd/><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>B</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>O</mml:mtext><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mtext>O</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mtext>H</mml:mtext><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">&#x02192;</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mtext>Bi</mml:mtext><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>O</mml:mtext><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>H</mml:mtext><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mtext>O</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd/><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>B</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mn>18</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Se</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>O</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mn>29</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mtext>BiSe&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mtext>O</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mtext>H</mml:mtext><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">&#x02192;</mml:mo><mml:mtext>B</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mn>18</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Se</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>O</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mn>30</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mtext>H/BiSeOH</mml:mtext><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mtext>e</mml:mtext><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd/><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Bi</mml:mtext><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>O</mml:mtext><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mtext>e</mml:mtext><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">&#x02192;</mml:mo><mml:mtext>Bi</mml:mtext><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>O</mml:mtext><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd/><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Bi</mml:mtext><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>O</mml:mtext><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>H</mml:mtext><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mtext>O</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">&#x02192;</mml:mo><mml:mtext>Bi</mml:mtext><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>O</mml:mtext><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>4</mml:mn><mml:mtext>O</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mtext>H</mml:mtext><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mtext>B</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd/><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>B</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">&#x02192;</mml:mo><mml:mtext>B</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>met</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula>
Here, Bi<sup>0</sup> are active atoms and Bi<sub>met</sub> is the metal bismuth.
<fig id="RSOS171186F3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>The electrochemical properties of synthesized Bi<sub>18</sub>SeO<sub>29</sub>/BiSe electrode materials via a three-electrode system: (<italic>a</italic>) CV curves at different scan rates; (<italic>b</italic>) GCD curves with various current densities; (<italic>c</italic>) with the increase in current density the changes in specific capacitance changes; and (<italic>d</italic>) cycling stability of the Bi<sub>18</sub>SeO<sub>29</sub>/BiSe electrode material at a current density of 2&#x02009;A&#x02009;g<sup>&#x02013;1</sup>.
</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="rsos171186-g3"/></fig></p><p>There are characteristic redox peaks of the electrode observed from &#x02212;1 to 0&#x02009;V which correspond to the reversible intercalation/deintercalation of OH<sup>&#x02013;</sup> ions occurring in the Bi<sub>18</sub>SeO<sub>29</sub>/BiSe bulk and at the interface of Bi<sub>18</sub>SeO<sub>29</sub>/BiSe and electrolyte to increase the discharge time.</p><p>From the CV curve, we can see that the shape remains similar even at high scan rates, which indicates that the Bi<sub>18</sub>SeO<sub>29</sub>/BiSe electrode material has excellent capacitance behaviour. And at higher sweep rates, the higher/lower potentials the reduction and oxidation peak potentials move, because the ions may only be immersed in the surface of the material; however at a lower sweep rates, ions can be effectively diffused into the inner active sites. As the lower scan rates are provided for a longer period of time, the active site interacts with the ions better. So it is obvious that as the scan rate increases, the specific capacitance will be reduced. The various current density GCD curves of the Bi<sub>18</sub>SeO<sub>29</sub>/BiSe electrode are presented in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="RSOS171186F3">figure&#x000a0;3</xref><italic>b</italic>; the charge/discharge curve reveals the pseudocapacitance behaviour. In the discharge process, there is a kink in the curve, which is perhaps some of the untransformed Bi<sup>0</sup> oxidation platforms during the reduction process. These results are consistent with that consequence of the CV curves. As exhibited in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="RSOS171186F3">figure&#x000a0;3</xref><italic>c</italic>, the specific capacitances of the Bi<sub>18</sub>SeO<sub>29</sub>/BiSe electrode at various current densities of 0.5, 1, 2, 3, 5, 8 and 10&#x02009;A&#x02009;g<sup>&#x02013;1</sup> are 471.3, 373, 331.2, 320.4, 307, 291.2 and 285&#x02009;F&#x02009;g<sup>&#x02013;1</sup>, respectively. This indicates outstanding rate capability [<xref rid="RSOS171186C44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. This phenomenon is also present in transition metal sulfides and oxides/hydroxides, which can be attributed to the diffusion effect [<xref rid="RSOS171186C45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>,<xref rid="RSOS171186C46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. To evaluate the cycling stability, the GCD cycling of Bi<sub>18</sub>SeO<sub>29</sub>/BiSe was observed at a current density of 2&#x02009;A&#x02009;g<sup>&#x02013;1</sup> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="RSOS171186F3">figure&#x000a0;3</xref><italic>d</italic>), which indicates that Bi<sub>18</sub>SeO<sub>29</sub>/BiSe has good cycling stability with about 68% capacitance retention after 5000 cycles in 2&#x02009;M KOH electrolyte. This result makes Bi<sub>18</sub>SeO<sub>29</sub>/BiSe a promising candidate as an advanced electrode material for supercapacitor application.</p></sec><sec id="s3b"><label>3.2.</label><title>Positive electrode</title><p>The Co<sub>0.85</sub>Se was characterized in detail. From the XRD pattern displayed in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="RSOS171186F4">figure&#x000a0;4</xref><italic>a</italic>, the diffraction peaks can be indexed to Co<sub>0.85</sub>Se with the hexagonal structure (JCPDS card no. 52-1008) readily. The pure phase and sharp peaks show that Co<sub>0.85</sub>Se has high crystallinity. The strong diffraction peaks at 2<italic>&#x003b8;</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;33.3, 44.7 and 50.6 unequivocally correspond to the (101), (102), and (110) planes of Co0.85Se, respectively. The morphology characteristic features of the Co<sub>0.85</sub>Se sample were analysed via SEM. The SEM images (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="RSOS171186F4">figure&#x000a0;4</xref><italic>b</italic>) display a particular flower-like morphology, which is combined with the subunits of the nanosheet. The high-resolution SEM image (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="RSOS171186F4">figure&#x000a0;4</xref><italic>c</italic>) clearly shows a flower-like 3D microstructure, which could facilitate penetration of the electrolyte into the material and also increase the electrochemical reactions of the active sites. Further, the microstructure was also described by the corresponding TEM and high-resolution TEM images. As can be seen in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="RSOS171186F4">figure&#x000a0;4</xref><italic>d</italic>&#x02013;<italic>f</italic>, Co<sub>0.85</sub>Se is constituted of many thin nanosheets, which are consistent with those in SEM. From <xref ref-type="fig" rid="RSOS171186F4">figure&#x000a0;4</xref><italic>f</italic>, well-defined lattice fringes are clearly seen with an interplanar spacing of 0.27&#x02009;nm. This corresponds to the separation between (101) lattice planes of Co<sub>0.85</sub>Se. In the SAED pattern shown in the inset of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="RSOS171186F4">figure&#x000a0;4</xref><italic>f</italic>, the diffraction rings could be easily indexed to Co<sub>0.85</sub>Se with the hexagonal (101), (102), (110) and (103) planes from inside to outside, suggesting that the nanosheet is of polycrystalline nature [<xref rid="RSOS171186C31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>], which shows good agreement with the XRD pattern and can be indexed to the structure.
<fig id="RSOS171186F4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>(<italic>a</italic>) XRD pattern of Co<sub>0.85</sub>Se nanosheets; (<italic>b</italic>,<italic>c</italic>) SEM and (<italic>d</italic>,<italic>e</italic>) TEM images of Co<sub>0.85</sub>Se nanosheets at various magnifications; (<italic>f</italic>) high-resolution TEM image of the Co<sub>0.85</sub>Se nanosheets.
</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="rsos171186-g4"/></fig></p><p>The specific surface area and pore size distribution of Co<sub>0.85</sub>Se were examined by N<sub>2</sub> adsorption&#x02013;desorption measurements. As displayed in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="RSOS171186F5">figure&#x000a0;5</xref><italic>a</italic> and inset, at a relative pressure of 0.9&#x02013;0.99, the apparent N<sub>2</sub> adsorption and the hysteresis loop indicate the coexistence of a minor fraction of mesopores/macropores, which is mainly due to the 3D voids between interconnected particles [<xref rid="RSOS171186C47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. The specific surface area of Co<sub>0.85</sub>Se calculated by the multiple points BET method is 73.3&#x02009;m<sup>2</sup>&#x02009;g<sup>&#x02013;1</sup>, which is larger than that of the previously reported Co<sub>0.85</sub>Se electrode materials; Gong <italic>et al</italic>. described a specific surface area of 26.44&#x02009;m<sup>2</sup>&#x02009;g<sup>&#x02013;1</sup> [<xref rid="RSOS171186C48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>] and Yang <italic>et al</italic>. described 59&#x02009;m<sup>2</sup>&#x02009;g<sup>&#x02013;1</sup> [<xref rid="RSOS171186C31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. A mass of the 3D porous structure will favour the penetration of electrolyte and the rapid transmission of electrons, which will improve the electrochemical properties of the Co<sub>0.85</sub>Se electrode material.
<fig id="RSOS171186F5" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p>(<italic>a</italic>) Nitrogen adsorption&#x02013;desorption isotherms and (inset) pore size distribution of Co<sub>0.85</sub>Se; (<italic>b</italic>) high-resolution XPS spectra of Co<sub>2p1/2</sub> and Co<sub>2p3/2</sub> peak; (<italic>c</italic>) high-resolution XPS spectra of Se 3d peak; and (<italic>d</italic>) the corresponding element mapping images (selected from the square region) for the Co<sub>0.85</sub>Se nanosheets.
</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="rsos171186-g5"/></fig></p><p>The XPS and EDS techniques were used to evaluate the surface valence state information and the chemical element compositions of Co<sub>0.85</sub>Se (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="RSOS171186F5">figure&#x000a0;5</xref><italic>b</italic>&#x02013;<italic>d</italic>), mainly exhibiting the Se 3d and Co 2p peaks. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="RSOS171186F5">Figure&#x000a0;5</xref><italic>b</italic> shows the Co 2p<sub>3/2</sub>, 2p<sub>1/2</sub> and two satellite peaks (marked as &#x02018;sat.&#x02019;). The Co<sup>3+</sup> 2p<sub>3/2</sub>, Co<sup>2+</sup> 2p<sub>3/2</sub> and Co<sup>2+</sup> 2p<sub>1/2</sub> are corresponding to binding energies of 779.0, 780.8 and 797.2&#x02009;eV, respectively. The two spin&#x02013;orbit doublets characteristic of Co<sup>2+</sup> and Co<sup>3+</sup> are considered and consistent with the previously reported values [<xref rid="RSOS171186C37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. Furthermore, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="RSOS171186F5">figure&#x000a0;5</xref><italic>c</italic> clearly displays the core region of the binding energy of 55.4&#x02009;eV corresponding to the Se 3d spectrum, and this approached the reported value [<xref rid="RSOS171186C49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. The results show that the synthesized Co<sub>0.85</sub>Se electrode material consisted of Co<sup>2+</sup>, Co<sup>3+</sup> and Se<sup>2</sup>, which is consistent with the formula Co<sub>0.85</sub>Se. Furthermore, the Co<sub>0.85</sub>Se electrode material is synthesized by element mapping images of cobalt and selenium in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="RSOS171186F5">figure&#x000a0;5</xref><italic>d</italic>, in which it is obvious that the elemental distributions are very uniform.</p><p>Electrochemical behaviours of the Co<sub>0.85</sub>Se electrode material were investigated by CV and GCD measurements with 2&#x02009;M KOH at a voltage window between &#x02212;0.1 and 0.6&#x02009;V (versus Hg/HgO) in a standard three-electrode system. From <xref ref-type="fig" rid="RSOS171186F6">figure&#x000a0;6</xref><italic>a</italic>, it is clear that the area surrounded by the CV curve of Co<sub>0.85</sub>Se exhibits two pairs redox peaks, which might be attributed to standard Faradaic pseudocapacitance behaviour. The two pairs ascribed to the reversible redox reaction can occur according to [<xref rid="RSOS171186C50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]
<disp-formula id="RSOS171186UM2"><mml:math id="DM8"><mml:mtable columnalign="right left right left right left right left right left right left" rowspacing="3pt" columnspacing="0.278em 2em 0.278em 2em 0.278em 2em 0.278em 2em 0.278em 2em 0.278em"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mtext>C</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>o</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.85</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Se&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mtext>O</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mtext>H</mml:mtext><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mo stretchy="false">&#x02192;</mml:mo><mml:mtext>C</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>o</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.85</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mtext>SeOH</mml:mtext><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mtext>e</mml:mtext><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mtext>C</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>o</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.85</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mtext>SeOH</mml:mtext><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mtext>O</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mtext>H</mml:mtext><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mo stretchy="false">&#x02192;</mml:mo><mml:mtext>C</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>o</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.85</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mtext>SeO</mml:mtext><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>H</mml:mtext><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mtext>O</mml:mtext><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mtext>e</mml:mtext><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula>
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="RSOS171186F6">Figure&#x000a0;6</xref><italic>a</italic> describes the typical CV curves of the Co<sub>0.85</sub>Se nanosheets at various scan rates from 5 to 30&#x02009;mV&#x02009;s<sup>&#x02013;1</sup>, from which, even at a high scan rate of 30&#x02009;mV&#x02009;s<sup>&#x02013;1</sup>, two pairs of reversible redox peaks can be obviously observed. In addition, due to the presence of polarization, with the increase of the scan rate the position of the redox peak gradually changes [<xref rid="RSOS171186C50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. The GCD test results are presented in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="RSOS171186F6">figure&#x000a0;6</xref><italic>b</italic> to analyse the charge storage capacity of the electrode material. Because the redox reaction occurs at the electrode interface by the desorption and adsorption of the hydroxyl ion in the alkaline electrolyte [<xref rid="RSOS171186C51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>], it is obvious that each charge&#x02013;discharge curve indicates pseudocapacitive performance at current densities from 0.5 to 8&#x02009;A&#x02009;g<sup>&#x02013;1</sup>, and deviates from the EDLC linear curve. All of the charge&#x02013;discharge curves are almost symmetrical, which reveals that Co<sub>0.85</sub>Se has excellent capacitive behaviour. As displayed in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="RSOS171186F6">figure&#x000a0;6</xref><italic>c</italic>, the specific capacitance of Co<sub>0.85</sub>Se is calculated to be 255, 246, 237, 229, 220, 204 and 196&#x02009;F&#x02009;g<sup>&#x02013;1</sup> at various current densities from 0.5 to 10&#x02009;A&#x02009;g<sup>&#x02013;1</sup>, exhibiting an outstanding rate capability. The stability of the Co<sub>0.85</sub>Se electrode material was tested using the charging and discharge technique at a current density of 2&#x02009;A&#x02009;g<sup>&#x02013;1</sup>. Finally, it is seen to retain about 78% of its initial capacitance after 5000 cycles, indicating that the Co<sub>0.85</sub>Se positive electrode material possesses outstanding cycling stability.
<fig id="RSOS171186F6" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><p>The electrochemical properties of synthesized electrode Co<sub>0.85</sub>Se materials in a three-electrode system: (<italic>a</italic>) CV curves with various scan rates; (<italic>b</italic>) GCD curves at different current densities; (<italic>c</italic>) the change of specific capacitance with the increase in current density; and (<italic>d</italic>) cycling stability of Co<sub>0.85</sub>Se electrode material at a current density of 2&#x02009;A&#x02009;g<sup>&#x02013;1</sup>.
</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="rsos171186-g6"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="s3c"><label>3.3.</label><title>Asymmetric supercapacitor</title><p>In practical applications, to further evaluate the electrochemical performance of the electrode materials, we assembled an ASC, in which Bi<sub>18</sub>SeO<sub>29</sub>/BiSe and Co<sub>0.85</sub>Se worked as the negative and positive electrode materials in 2&#x02009;M KOH electrolyte. To ensure the electrochemical stability of the two-electrode cell with the acquired optimized potential window, the CVs of Bi<sub>18</sub>SeO<sub>29</sub>/BiSe (black) and the Co<sub>0.85</sub>Se (red) were tested in 2&#x02009;M KOH electrolyte at 30&#x02009;mV&#x02009;s<sup>&#x02013;1</sup>. As displayed in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="RSOS171186F7">figure&#x000a0;7</xref><italic>a</italic>, the stable potential range of Co<sub>0.85</sub>Se is between 0 and 0.6&#x02009;V and the capacitive behaviour of Bi<sub>18</sub>SeO<sub>29</sub>/BiSe is between &#x02212;1 and 0&#x02009;V. Therefore, the operating cell voltage can be optimized to 1.6&#x02009;V in 2&#x02009;M KOH aqueous solution for the ASC of Bi<sub>18</sub>SeO<sub>29</sub>/BiSe//Co<sub>0.85</sub>Se (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="RSOS171186F7">figure&#x000a0;7</xref><italic>b</italic>). In the design of the asymmetric cell, the balance of the charge stored between the positive and negative electrodes was necessary and it was calculated by equations (2.2) and (2.3). The CV curves of the Bi<sub>18</sub>SeO<sub>29</sub>/BiSe//Co<sub>0.85</sub>Se ASC device were analysed at various scan rates (between 10 and 100&#x02009;mV&#x02009;s<sup>&#x02013;1</sup>) with an operating voltage of 1.6&#x02009;V. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="RSOS171186F7">Figure&#x000a0;7</xref><italic>b</italic> clearly shows that three pairs of redox peaks can be attributed to the redox reactions of Bi<sub>18</sub>SeO<sub>29</sub>/BiSe and Co<sub>0.85</sub>Se in 2&#x02009;M KOH electrolyte. In addition, all curves show similar shapes; meanwhile changes in anode and cathode peaks even at high scan rate of 100&#x02009;mV&#x02009;s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> of the ASC are small, indicating outstanding reversibility of the ASC. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="RSOS171186F7">Figure&#x000a0;7</xref><italic>c</italic> exhibits the GCD curves of the Bi<sub>18</sub>SeO<sub>29</sub>/BiSe//Co<sub>0.85</sub>Se ASC device at different current densities (ranging from 0.5 to 8&#x02009;A&#x02009;g<sup>&#x02013;1</sup>), and this proves the coexistence of the oxidation of anions and surface adsorption of ions in this ASC device. An advanced Ragone diagram (energy density versus power density) of the Bi<sub>18</sub>SeO<sub>29</sub>/BiSe//Co<sub>0.85</sub>Se ASC device is obtained from the GCD data (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="RSOS171186F7">figure&#x000a0;7</xref><italic>c</italic>) as revealed in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="RSOS171186F7">figure&#x000a0;7</xref><italic>d</italic>, according to equations (2.5) and (2.6). The device exhibits a high energy density that reaches 24.2&#x02009;Wh&#x02009;kg<sup>&#x02013;1</sup> at an outstanding power density of 871.2&#x02009;W&#x02009;kg<sup>&#x02013;1</sup> at a current density of 1&#x02009;A&#x02009;g<sup>&#x02013;1</sup>. Even when the current density is as high as 15&#x02009;A&#x02009;g<sup>&#x02013;1</sup>, the energy density still remains at 11.9&#x02009;Wh&#x02009;kg<sup>&#x02013;1</sup> with an excellent power density of 13&#x02009;387.5&#x02009;W&#x02009;kg<sup>&#x02013;1</sup>. The energy density of the Bi<sub>18</sub>SeO<sub>29</sub>/BiSe//Co<sub>0.85</sub>Se ASC device is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="RSOS171186F7">figure&#x000a0;7</xref><italic>d</italic>. To verify the feasibility of energy supply for the Bi<sub>18</sub>SeO<sub>29</sub>/BiSe//Co<sub>0.85</sub>Se ASC, the three-tandem cell group can light up a red light-emitting diode (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="RSOS171186F7">figure&#x000a0;7</xref><italic>d</italic>, inset). Therefore, the excellent high energy density indicates that it has great potential as a supercapacitor.
<fig id="RSOS171186F7" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 7.</label><caption><p>(<italic>a</italic>) CV curves of the Bi<sub>18</sub>SeO<sub>29</sub>/BiSe and Co<sub>0.85</sub>Se electrodes via a two-electrode cell at 30&#x02009;mV&#x02009;s<sup>&#x02013;1</sup> in 2&#x02009;M KOH; (<italic>b</italic>) CV curves of the ASC device with different scan rates; (<italic>c</italic>) GCD curves at different current densities; (<italic>d</italic>) Ragone plot related to energy and power densities of the ASC; (<italic>e</italic>) Nyquist plot of the ASC (inset shows the equivalent circuit model); (<italic>f</italic>) cycling stability of the Bi<sub>18</sub>SeO<sub>29</sub>/BiSe//Co<sub>0.85</sub>Se ASC in a two-electrode cell.
</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="rsos171186-g7"/></fig></p><p>The facilitated ion or electron transport kinetics of the Bi<sub>18</sub>SeO<sub>29</sub>/BiSe//Co<sub>0.85</sub>Se ASC device was investigated by EIS. The Nyquist plot of the ASC device and the corresponding equivalent circuit are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="RSOS171186F7">figure&#x000a0;7</xref><italic>e</italic> and in the inset of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="RSOS171186F7">figure&#x000a0;7</xref><italic>e</italic>, respectively. It consists of three different parts at a distinct frequency range: high frequencies, an unfinished semicircular part; the middle frequencies, an inclined portion in the curve (about 45&#x000b0;); and the low frequencies, the linear part. The high frequency of the real axis intercept indicates the internal resistance (<italic>R</italic><sub>s</sub>), which is the sum of the large amount of electrolyte resistance, the contact resistance of the electrode/electrolyte interface and the intrinsic resistance of the electrode active material [<xref rid="RSOS171186C52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. The charge transfer resistance (<italic>R</italic><sub>ct</sub>) is the diameter of the semicircle which is related to the charge transfer at the electrode/electrolyte interface and thus produced a Faraday reaction [<xref rid="RSOS171186C46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]; in the middle frequencies, the 45&#x000b0; slope of the line is called Warburg impedance (<italic>Z</italic><sub>w</sub>), which is caused by the diffusion process of the electrolyte [<xref rid="RSOS171186C53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]. Moreover, <italic>C</italic><sub>L</sub> and <italic>C</italic><sub>dl</sub> represent the limit capacitance and the double-layer capacitance [<xref rid="RSOS171186C54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]. As can be seen from the fitted results, a Bi<sub>18</sub>SeO<sub>29</sub>/BiSe//Co<sub>0.85</sub>Se ASC device not only has a low <italic>R</italic><sub>s</sub> (0.88&#x02009;&#x02126;&#x02009;cm<sup>2</sup>), but also possesses a small <italic>R</italic><sub>ct</sub> (1.87&#x02009;&#x02126;&#x02009;cm<sup>2</sup>), as well as a low Warburg resistance (0.017&#x02009;&#x02126;&#x02009;cm<sup>2</sup>). The values demonstrate that the electrolyte permeation and ion diffusion into the pore structure are very easy, and these values may belong to electrode materials with special structure. On the one hand, Bi<sub>18</sub>SeO<sub>29</sub>/BiSe is an ultrathin nanosheet, and it can provide an efficient pathway for charge transportation; on the other hand, Co<sub>0.85</sub>Se material has a 3D high surface area, for adsorbing ions to provide abundant electrical active sites. These results can facilitate transport of the electrolyte. The cyclic stability of the Bi<sub>18</sub>SeO<sub>29</sub>/BiSe//Co<sub>0.85</sub>Se ASC device is evaluated by the GCD process with a current density of 2&#x02009;A&#x02009;g<sup>&#x02013;1</sup> after 5000 cycles and an operating voltage of 0&#x02013;1.6&#x02009;V (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="RSOS171186F7">figure&#x000a0;7</xref><italic>f</italic>). Owing to the full activation of the Bi<sub>18</sub>SeO<sub>29</sub>/BiSe and Co<sub>0.85</sub>Se materials, the specific capacitance increases at the beginning, and even after 1500 cycles, the degradation of the active material was not observed with maintenance of 100% initial capacity. Thus, excellent cycling performance is shown. Finally, the ASC device shows only a slight decrease in specific capacitance (about 93% of the initial specific capacitance retention after 5000 cycles), indicating excellent cycle stability. The above results mean that the high-performance ASC with excellent stability may be a candidate for energy storage devices in future electronic application.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s4"><label>4.</label><title>Conclusion</title><p>In summary, the negative Bi<sub>18</sub>SeO<sub>29</sub>/BiSe and positive Co<sub>0.85</sub>Se electrode materials are prepared through a simple one-step hydrothermal method without any template and surfactant. Bi<sub>18</sub>SeO<sub>29</sub>/BiSe and Co<sub>0.85</sub>Se have high specific capacitance (471.3&#x02009;F&#x02009;g<sup>&#x02013;1</sup> and 255&#x02009;F&#x02009;g<sup>&#x02013;1</sup> at 0.5&#x02009;A&#x02009;g<sup>&#x02013;1</sup>), high conductivity, outstanding cycling stability, as well as good rate capability. The all-pseudocapacitive electrodes fabricated Bi<sub>18</sub>SeO<sub>29</sub>/BiSe//Co<sub>0.85</sub>Se ASC device has excellent electrochemical performance with a good cycling stability (93% capacitance retention after 5000 cycles at a current density of 2&#x02009;A&#x02009;g<sup>&#x02013;1</sup>) and high energy density (about 24.2&#x02009;Wh&#x02009;kg<sup>&#x02013;1</sup>) as well as high power density (about 871.2&#x02009;W&#x02009;kg<sup>&#x02013;1</sup>) in aqueous electrolyte at a wide voltage window of 0&#x02013;1.6&#x02009;V. The results demonstrate that the electrode material preparation approach is easy and also the resulting ASC is promising as an energy-storage device.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We acknowledge useful input from two anonymous reviewers.</p></ack><sec id="s5"><title>Data accessibility</title><p>This article has no additional data.</p></sec><sec id="s6"><title>Authors' contributions</title><p>G.M. and F.H. carried out the conception and design, and participated in the acquisition analysis and interpretation of data, data analysis, carried out sequence alignments and drafted the manuscript. K.S. and E.F. carried out the statistical analyses. H.P. and Z.Z. collected field data. Z.L. conceived of and designed the study, coordinated the study and helped draft the manuscript. All the authors gave their final approval for publication.</p></sec><sec id="s7" sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p>We declare we have no competing interests.</p></sec><sec id="s8"><title>Funding</title><p>This research was financially supported by the National Science Foundation of China (nos. 21164009 and 21174114), the programme for Changjiang Scholars and Innovative Research Team in University (IRT15R56), the China Postdoctoral Science Foundation (2013M540778), Key Laboratory of Eco-Environment-Related Polymer Materials (Northwest Normal University) of Ministry of Education, and Key Laboratory of Polymer Materials of Gansu Province.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="RSOS171186C1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ivey</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>Manganese oxide-based materials as electrochemical supercapacitor electrodes</article-title>. <source>Chem. Soc. Rev.</source>
<volume>40</volume>, <fpage>1697</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1721</lpage>. (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1039/C0CS00127A">doi:10.1039/C0CS00127A</ext-link>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21173973</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RSOS171186C2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2017</year>
<article-title>Fe<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> nanoneedles on ultrafine nickel nanotube arrays as efficient anode for high-performance asymmetric supercapacitors</article-title>. <source>Adv. Funct. Mater.</source>
<volume>27</volume>, <fpage>1606728</fpage> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/adfm.201606728">doi:10.1002/adfm.201606728</ext-link>)</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RSOS171186C3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hou</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lou</surname><given-names>XW</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>Ultrathin mesoporous NiCo<sub>2</sub>O<sub>4</sub> nanosheets supported on Ni foam as advanced electrodes for supercapacitors</article-title>. <source>Adv. Funct. Mater.</source>
<volume>22</volume>, <fpage>4592</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4597</lpage>. (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/adfm.201200994">doi:10.1002/adfm.201200994</ext-link>)</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RSOS171186C4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>Mesoporous carbon incorporated metal oxide nanomaterials as supercapacitor electrodes</article-title>. <source>Adv. Mater.</source>
<volume>24</volume>, <fpage>4197</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4202</lpage>. (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/adma.201104942">doi:10.1002/adma.201104942</ext-link>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23030034</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RSOS171186C5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>A review of electrode materials for electrochemical supercapacitors</article-title><italic>.</italic>
<source>Chem. Soc. Rev.</source>
<volume>41</volume>, <fpage>797</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>828</lpage>. (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1039/C1CS15060J">doi:10.1039/C1CS15060J</ext-link>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21779609</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RSOS171186C6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Augustyn</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dunn</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>Pseudocapacitive oxide materials for high-rate electrochemical energy storage</article-title>. <source>Energy Environ. Sci.</source>
<volume>7</volume>, <fpage>1597</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1614</lpage>. (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1039/C3EE44164D">doi:10.1039/C3EE44164D</ext-link>)</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RSOS171186C7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hui</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hui</surname><given-names>KN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>Hierarchical nitrogen-doped porous carbon with high surface area derived from endothelium corneum gigeriae galli for high-performance supercapacitor</article-title>. <source>Electrochim. Acta</source>
<volume>130</volume>, <fpage>464</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>469</lpage>. (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.electacta.2014.03.015">doi:10.1016/j.electacta.2014.03.015</ext-link>)</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RSOS171186C8"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>Preparation and characterization of flexible asymmetric supercapacitors based on transition-metal-oxide nanowire/single-walled carbon nanotube hybrid thin-film electrodes</article-title>. <source>ACS Nano</source>
<volume>4</volume>, <fpage>4403</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4411</lpage>. (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1021/nn100856y">doi:10.1021/nn100856y</ext-link>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20731426</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RSOS171186C9"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dou</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2017</year>
<article-title>Three-dimensional graphene combined with hierarchical CuS for the design of flexible solid-state supercapacitors</article-title>. <source>Electrochim. Acta</source>
<volume>237</volume>, <fpage>109</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>118</lpage>. (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.electacta.2017.03.207">doi:10.1016/j.electacta.2017.03.207</ext-link>)</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RSOS171186C10"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Qian</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2017</year>
<article-title>One-pot hydrothermal synthesis of RGO/FeS composite on Fe foil for high performance supercapacitors</article-title>. <source>Electrochim. Acta</source>
<volume>246</volume>, <fpage>497</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>506</lpage>. (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.electacta.2017.06.090">doi:10.1016/j.electacta.2017.06.090</ext-link>)</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RSOS171186C11"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Iqbal</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hassan</surname><given-names>MU</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ashiq</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Iqbal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bibi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Parveen</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2017</year>
<article-title>High specific capacitance and energy density of synthesized graphene oxide based hierarchical Al<sub>2</sub>S<sub>3</sub> nanorambutan for supercapacitor applications</article-title>. <source>Electrochim. Acta</source>
<volume>246</volume>, <fpage>1097</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1103</lpage>. (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.electacta.2017.06.123">doi:10.1016/j.electacta.2017.06.123</ext-link>)</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RSOS171186C12"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>New off-on sensor for captopril sensing based on photoluminescent MoO x quantum dots</article-title>. <source>ACS Appl. Mater. Inter.</source>
<volume>8</volume>, <fpage>1774</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1779</lpage>. (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1021/acsomega.7b00088">doi:10.1021/acsomega.7b00088</ext-link>)</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RSOS171186C13"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Borysiewicz</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ekielski</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ogorza&#x00142;ek</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wzorek</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kaczmarski</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wojciechowski</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2017</year>
<article-title>Highly transparent supercapacitors based on ZnO/MnO<sub>2</sub> nanostructures</article-title>. <source>Nanoscale</source>
<volume>9</volume>, <fpage>7577</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7587</lpage>. (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1039/C7NR01320E">doi:10.1039/C7NR01320E</ext-link>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28537626</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RSOS171186C14"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ke</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Guan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2017</year>
<article-title>Surface-charge-mediated formation of H-TiO<sub>2</sub>@Ni(OH)<sub>2</sub> heterostructures for high-performance supercapacitors</article-title>. <source>Adv. Mater.</source>
<volume>29</volume>, <fpage>1604164</fpage> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/adma.201604164">doi:10.1002/adma.201604164</ext-link>)</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RSOS171186C15"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>WY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2017</year>
<article-title>One-pot synthesis of heterogeneous Co<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub>-nanocube/Co(OH)<sub>2</sub>-nanosheet hybrids for high-performance flexible asymmetric all-solid-state supercapacitors</article-title>. <source>Nano Energy</source>
<volume>35</volume>, <fpage>138</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>145</lpage>. (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.nanoen.2017.02.044">doi:10.1016/j.nanoen.2017.02.044</ext-link>)</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RSOS171186C16"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pei</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rodrigues</surname><given-names>M-TF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ajayan</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>CoNi<sub>2</sub>S<sub>4</sub>-graphene-2D-MoSe<sub>2</sub> as an advanced electrode material for supercapacitors</article-title>. <source>Adv. Energy. Mater.</source>
<volume>6</volume>, <fpage>1600341</fpage> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/aenm.201600341">doi:10.1002/aenm.201600341</ext-link>)</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RSOS171186C17"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zou</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2017</year>
<article-title>Three-dimensional reduced graphene oxide/polyaniline nanocomposite film prepared by diffusion driven layer-by-layer assembly for high-performance supercapacitors</article-title>. <source>J. Power Sources</source>
<volume>343</volume>, <fpage>60</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>66</lpage>. (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.jpowsour.2017.01.034">doi:10.1016/j.jpowsour.2017.01.034</ext-link>)</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RSOS171186C18"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gong</surname><given-names>MX</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2017</year>
<article-title>A fiber asymmetric supercapacitor based on FeOOH/PPy on carbon fibers as an anode electrode with high volumetric energy density for wearable applications</article-title>. <source>Nanoscale</source>
<volume>9</volume>, <fpage>10&#x02009;794</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>10&#x02009;801</lpage>. (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1039/C7NR02896B">doi:10.1039/C7NR02896B</ext-link>)</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RSOS171186C19"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Qi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>In situ growth of NiCo<sub>2</sub>S<sub>4</sub> nanotube arrays on Ni foam for supercapacitors: maximizing utilization efficiency at high mass loading to achieve ultrahigh areal pseudocapacitance</article-title>. <source>J. Power Sources</source>
<volume>254</volume>, <fpage>249</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>257</lpage>. (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.jpowsour.2013.12.092">doi:10.1016/j.jpowsour.2013.12.092</ext-link>)</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RSOS171186C20"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>Half-metallic ferromagnetism in synthetic Co<sub>9</sub>Se<sub>8</sub> nanosheets with atomic thickness</article-title>. <source>J. Am. Chem. Soc.</source>
<volume>134</volume>, <fpage>11&#x02009;908</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>11&#x02009;911</lpage>. (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1021/ja3046603">doi:10.1021/ja3046603</ext-link>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21721566</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RSOS171186C21"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Balasingam</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jun</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>Few-layered MoSe<sub>2</sub> nanosheets as an advanced electrode material for supercapacitors</article-title>. <source>Dalton Trans.</source>
<volume>44</volume>, <fpage>15&#x02009;491</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>15&#x02009;498</lpage>. (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1039/C5DT01985K">doi:10.1039/C5DT01985K</ext-link>)</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RSOS171186C22"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hou</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>Three-dimensional hierarchical GeSe<sub>2</sub> nanostructures for high performance flexible all-solid-state supercapacitors</article-title>. <source>Adv. Mater.</source>
<volume>25</volume>, <fpage>1479</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1486</lpage>. (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/adma.201204063">doi:10.1002/adma.201204063</ext-link>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23180449</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RSOS171186C23"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>IG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Son</surname><given-names>SU</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>SnSe<sub>2</sub> nanoplate-graphene composites as anode materials for lithium ion batteries</article-title>. <source>Chem. Commun.</source>
<volume>47</volume>, <fpage>5241</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5243</lpage>. (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1039/C1CC10317B">doi:10.1039/C1CC10317B</ext-link>)</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RSOS171186C24"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Asiri</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title><italic>In situ</italic> growth of NiSe nanowire film on nickel foam as an electrode for high-performance supercapacitors</article-title>. <source>ChemElectroChem</source>
<volume>2</volume>, <fpage>1903</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1907</lpage>. (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/celc.201500285">doi:10.1002/celc.201500285</ext-link>)</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RSOS171186C25"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2017</year>
<article-title>Interconnected Co<sub>0.85</sub>Se nanosheets as cathode materials for asymmetric supercapacitors</article-title>. <source>J. Power Sources</source>
<volume>340</volume>, <fpage>6</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>13</lpage>. (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.jpowsour.2016.11.061">doi:10.1016/j.jpowsour.2016.11.061</ext-link>)</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RSOS171186C26"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ueno</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yasuda</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dokko</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2017</year>
<article-title>Application of ionic liquids to energy storage and conversion materials and devices</article-title>. <source>Chem. Rev.</source>
<volume>117</volume>, <fpage>7190</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7239</lpage>. (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1021/acs.chemrev.6b00504">doi:10.1021/acs.chemrev.6b00504</ext-link>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28084733</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RSOS171186C27"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chaudoy</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Van</surname><given-names>FT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Deschamps</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ghamouss</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2017</year>
<article-title>Ionic liquids in a polyethylene oxide cross-linked gel polymer as an electrolyte for electrical double layer capacitor</article-title>. <source>J. Power Sources</source>
<volume>342</volume>, <fpage>872</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>878</lpage>. (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.jpowsour.2016.12.097">doi:10.1016/j.jpowsour.2016.12.097</ext-link>)</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RSOS171186C28"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pinna</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Niederberger</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2008</year>
<article-title>Surfactant-free nonaqueous synthesis of metal oxide nanostructures</article-title>. <source>Angew. Chem., Int. Ed.</source>
<volume>47</volume>, <fpage>5292</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5304</lpage>. (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/anie.200704541">doi:10.1002/anie.200704541</ext-link>)</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RSOS171186C29"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Niederberger</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pinna</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<source>Metal oxide nanoparticles in organic solvents: synthesis, formation, assembly and application</source>. <publisher-loc>London, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RSOS171186C30"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bullen</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mulvaney</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>Nucleation and growth kinetics of CdSe nanocrystals in octadecene</article-title>. <source>Nano Lett.</source>
<volume>4</volume>, <fpage>2303</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2307</lpage>. (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1021/nl0496724">doi:10.1021/nl0496724</ext-link>)</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RSOS171186C31"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ludi</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>S&#x000fc;ess</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Werner</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Niederberger</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>Mechanistic aspects of molecular formation and crystallization of zinc oxide nanoparticles in benzyl alcohol</article-title>. <source>Nanoscale</source>
<volume>4</volume>, <fpage>1982</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1995</lpage>. (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1039/C1NR11557J">doi:10.1039/C1NR11557J</ext-link>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22159429</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RSOS171186C32"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lei</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>Formation of carbon nanosheets via simultaneous activation and catalytic carbonization of macroporous anion-exchange resin for supercapacitors application</article-title>. <source>ACS Appl. Mater. Interfaces</source>
<volume>6</volume>, <fpage>20&#x02009;795</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>20&#x02009;803</lpage>. (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1021/am505066v">doi:10.1021/am505066v</ext-link>)</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RSOS171186C33"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>HB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>FX</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>CX</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tong</surname><given-names>YX</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>Amorphous nickel hydroxide nanospheres with ultrahigh capacitance and energy density as electrochemical pseudocapacitor materials</article-title>. <source>Nat. Commun.</source>
<volume>4</volume>, <fpage>1894</fpage> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/ncomms2932">doi:10.1038/ncomms2932</ext-link>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23695688</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RSOS171186C34"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lei</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>High-performance aqueous asymmetric supercapacitor based on K<sub>0.3</sub>WO<sub>3</sub> nanorods and nitrogen-doped porous carbon</article-title>. <source>J. Power Sources</source>
<volume>330</volume>, <fpage>219</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>230</lpage>. (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.jpowsour.2016.09.022">doi:10.1016/j.jpowsour.2016.09.022</ext-link>)</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RSOS171186C35"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dupont</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hollenkamp</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Donne</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>Electrochemically active surface area effects on the performance of manganese dioxide for electrochemical capacitor applications</article-title>. <source>Electrochim. Acta</source>
<volume>104</volume>, <fpage>140</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>147</lpage>. (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.electacta.2013.04.007">doi:10.1016/j.electacta.2013.04.007</ext-link>)</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RSOS171186C36"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Abdolmaleki</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kazerooni</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gholivand</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Heydari</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pendashteh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>Facile electrostatic coprecipitation of f-SWCNT/Co<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> nanocomposite as supercapacitor material</article-title>. <source>Ionics</source>
<volume>2</volume>, <fpage>515</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>523</lpage>. (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s11581-014-1173-5">https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s11581-014-1173-5</ext-link>)</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RSOS171186C37"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vonlanthen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lazarev</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>See</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wudl</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Heeger</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>A stable polyaniline-benzoquinone- hydroquinone supercapacitor</article-title>. <source>Adv. Mater.</source>
<volume>26</volume>, <fpage>5095</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5100</lpage>. (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/adma.201400966">doi:10.1002/adma.201400966</ext-link>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24923597</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RSOS171186C38"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Riggs</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moulder</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mouilenberg</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name></person-group> (eds). <year>1978</year>
<source>Handbook of X-ray photoelectron spectroscopy</source>. <publisher-loc>Eden Prairie, MN</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Perkin-Elmer Corporation</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RSOS171186C39"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>Infrared, Raman and XPS spectroscopic studies of Bi<sub>2</sub>O <sub>3</sub>-B<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>-Ga<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> glasses</article-title>. <source>Solid State Sci.</source>
<volume>11</volume>, <fpage>2065</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2070</lpage>. (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/solidstatessciences.2009.09.007">doi:10.1016/solidstatessciences.2009.09.007</ext-link>)</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RSOS171186C40"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wenkin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ruiz</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Delmon</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Devillers</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2002</year>
<article-title>The role of bismuth as promoter in Pd&#x02013;Bi catalysts for the selective oxidation of glucose to gluconate</article-title>. <source>J. Mol. Catal. A</source>
<volume>180</volume>, <fpage>141</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>159</lpage>. (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S1381-1169(01)00421-6">doi:10.1016/S1381-1169(01)00421-6</ext-link>)</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RSOS171186C41"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>FL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Qu</surname><given-names>YN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>ZL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Su</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tong</surname><given-names>YX</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>Synthesis of hierarchical rippled Bi<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> nanobelts for supercapacitor applications</article-title>. <source>Chem. Commun.</source>
<volume>46</volume>, <fpage>5021</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5023</lpage>. (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1039/C002126A">doi:10.1039/C002126A</ext-link>)</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RSOS171186C42"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kristian</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>Bi<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> deposited on highly ordered mesoporous carbon for supercapacitors</article-title>. <source>Electrochem. Commun.</source>
<volume>11</volume>, <fpage>313</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>317</lpage>. (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.elecom.2008.11.041">doi:10.1016/j.elecom.2008.11.041</ext-link>)</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RSOS171186C43"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>SX</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Qian</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>Bi<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> with activated carbon composite as a supercapacitor electrode</article-title>. <source>J. Alloys Compd.</source>
<volume>615</volume>, <fpage>12</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>17</lpage>. (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.jallcom.2014.06.149">doi:10.1016/j.jallcom.2014.06.149</ext-link>)</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RSOS171186C44"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ning</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>Asymmetric supercapacitors based on graphene/MnO<sub>2</sub> and activated carbon nanofiber electrodes with high power and energy density</article-title>. <source>Adv. Funct. Mater.</source>
<volume>21</volume>, <fpage>2366</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2375</lpage>. (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/adfm.201100058">doi:10.1002/adfm.201100058</ext-link>)</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RSOS171186C45"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nagaraju</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Raju</surname><given-names>GSR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ko</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>Hierarchical Ni-Co layered double hydroxide nanosheets entrapped on conductive textile fibers: a cost-effective and flexible electrode for high-performance pseudocapacitors</article-title>. <source>Nanoscale</source>
<volume>8</volume>, <fpage>812</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>825</lpage>. (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1039/C5NR05643H">doi:10.1039/C5NR05643H</ext-link>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26450829</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RSOS171186C46"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>Hollow spheres: MS<sub>2</sub> (M&#x02009;=&#x02009;Co and Ni) hollow spheres with tunable interiors for high-performance supercapacitors and photovoltaics (Adv. Funct. Mater. 15/2014)</article-title>. <source>Adv. Funct. Mater.</source>
<volume>24</volume>, <fpage>2154</fpage> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/adfm.201470095">doi:10.1002/adfm.201470095</ext-link>)</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RSOS171186C47"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>Nitrogen doped microporous carbons with tunable and selective performances in supercapacitor and heterogeneous catalysis</article-title>. <source>Electrochim. Acta</source>
<volume>190</volume>, <fpage>912</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>922</lpage>. (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.electacta.2015.12.113">doi:10.1016/j.electacta.2015.12.113</ext-link>)</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RSOS171186C48"><label>48</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gong</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>Mesoporous Co<sub>0.85</sub>Se nanosheets supported on Ni foam as a positive electrode material for asymmetric supercapacitor</article-title>. <source>App. Surf. Sci.</source>
<volume>362</volume>, <fpage>469</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>476</lpage>. (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.apsusc.2015.11.194">doi:10.1016/j.apsusc.2015.11.194</ext-link>)</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RSOS171186C49"><label>49</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Riggs</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moulder</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Muilenberg</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1979</year>
<comment><italic>Handbook of X-ray photoelectron spectroscopy</italic></comment>
<comment>Eden Prairie, MN: Perkin-Elmer Corporation, Physical Electronics Division</comment>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RSOS171186C50"><label>50</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Banerjee</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bhatnagar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Upadhyay</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yadav</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ogale</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>Hollow Co<sub>0.85</sub>Se nanowire array on carbon fiber paper for high rate pseudocapacitor</article-title>. <source>ACS Appl. Mater. Interfaces</source>
<volume>6</volume>, <fpage>18&#x02009;844</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>18&#x02009;852</lpage>. (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1021/am504333z">doi:10.1021/am504333z</ext-link>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24344828</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RSOS171186C51"><label>51</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ju</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>Supercapacitive behaviors of activated mesocarbon microbeads coated with polyaniline</article-title>. <source>Int. J. Hydrog. Energy</source>
<volume>37</volume>, <fpage>14&#x02009;365</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>14&#x02009;372</lpage>. (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.ighydene.2012.07.087">doi:10.1016/j.ighydene.2012.07.087</ext-link>)</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RSOS171186C52"><label>52</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>HB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Madhavi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lou</surname><given-names>XW</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>Controlled growth of NiMoO<sub>4</sub> nanosheet and nanorod arrays on various conductive substrates as advanced electrodes for asymmetric supercapacitors</article-title>. <source>Adv. Energy Mater.</source>
<volume>5</volume>, <fpage>1401172</fpage> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/aenm.201401172">doi:10.1002/aenm.201401172</ext-link>)</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RSOS171186C53"><label>53</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bosman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>Three-dimensional tubular arrays of MnO<sub>2</sub>-NiO nanoflakes with high areal pseudocapacitance</article-title>. <source>J. Mater. Chem.</source>
<volume>22</volume>, <fpage>2419</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2426</lpage>. (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1039/C1JM14804D">doi:10.1039/C1JM14804D</ext-link>)</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RSOS171186C54"><label>54</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>Electrochemical performance of asymmetric supercapacitor based on Co<sub>3</sub>O <sub>4</sub>/AC materials</article-title>. <source>J. Electroanal. Chem.</source>
<volume>706</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6</lpage>. (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.jelechem.2013.07.032">doi:10.1016/j.jelechem.2013.07.032</ext-link>)</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>