<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Transl Psychiatry</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Transl Psychiatry</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Translational Psychiatry</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2158-3188</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26440538</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4930124</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">tp2015146</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/tp.2015.146</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Differential levels of p75NTR ectodomain in CSF and blood in patients with Alzheimer's disease: a novel diagnostic marker</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running">p75NTR ectodomain and AD</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jiao</surname><given-names>S-S</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="note1"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bu</surname><given-names>X-L</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="note1"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y-H</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Q-H</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>C-H</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>X-Q</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>X-F</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y-J</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="caf1">*</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><institution>Department of Neurology, Daping Hospital, Third Military Medical University</institution>, Chongqing, <country>China</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><institution>Division of Health Sciences, School of Pharmacy and Medical Sciences, Sansom Institute, University of South Australia</institution>, Adelaide, SA, <country>Australia</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="caf1"><label>*</label><institution>Department of Neurology, Daping Hospital, Third Military Medical University</institution>, 10 Changjiang Branch Road, Yu-Zhong District, Chongqing 400042, <country>China</country>. E-mail: <email>yanjiang_wang@tmmu.edu.cn</email></corresp><fn fn-type="present-address" id="note1"><label>3</label><p>These authors contributed equally to this work.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>10</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>06</day><month>10</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>1</day><month>10</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><volume>5</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>e650</fpage><lpage/><history><date date-type="received"><day>07</day><month>05</month><year>2015</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>20</day><month>07</month><year>2015</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>29</day><month>07</month><year>2015</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2015 Macmillan Publishers Limited</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2015</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Macmillan Publishers Limited</copyright-holder><license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><!--author-paid--><license-p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in the credit line; if the material is not included under the Creative Commons license, users will need to obtain permission from the license holder to reproduce the material. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link></license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Alzheimer's disease (AD) is the primary cause of dementia in the elderly. The ectodomain of p75 neurotrophin receptor (p75NTR-ECD) has been suggested to play important roles in regulating beta-amyloid (A&#x003b2;) deposition and in protecting neurons from the toxicity of soluble A&#x003b2;. However, whether and how the serum and cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) levels of p75NTR-ECD change in patients with AD are not well documented. In the present study, we determined the concentrations of serum p75NTR-ECD in an AD group, a Parkinson disease group and a stroke group, as well as in a group of elderly controls without neurological disorders (EC). We also determined the levels of CSF p75NTR-ECD in a subset of the AD and EC groups. Our data showed that a distinct p75NTR-ECD profile characterized by a decreased CSF level and an increased serum level was present concomitantly with AD patients but not with other diseases. p75NTR-ECD levels in both the serum and CSF were strongly correlated with Mini-Mental State Examination (MMSE) scores and showed sound differential diagnostic value for AD. Moreover, when combining CSF A&#x003b2;42, CSF A&#x003b2;42/40, CSF ptau181 or CSF ptau181/A&#x003b2;42 with CSF p75NTR-ECD, the area under the receiver operating characteristic curve (AUC) and diagnostic accuracies improved. These findings indicate that p75NTR-ECD can serve as a specific biomarker for AD and the determination of serum and CSF p75NTR-ECD levels is likely to be helpful in monitoring AD progression.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>Alzheimer's disease (AD) is the most common form of neurodegenerative disease and is the primary cause of dementia in the elderly.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">2</xref></sup> Several lines of evidence indicate that the p75 neurotrophin receptor (p75NTR) plays multiple roles in the pathogenesis of AD, including those related to beta-amyloid (A&#x003b2;) generation,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">3</xref></sup> neuronal death,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">5</xref></sup> neuritic dystrophy<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">6</xref></sup> and Tau hyperphosphorylation.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">8</xref></sup> Our previous study found that the ectodomain of p75NTR (p75NTR-ECD), which is shed by the tumour necrosis factor-alpha-converting enzyme (TACE), inhibits A&#x003b2; aggregation and reduces the A&#x003b2; burden in the hippocampus of AD mice and that p75NTR-ECD deletion conversely increases the A&#x003b2; burden and AD phenotypes in mice.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">9</xref></sup> Soluble p75ECD has been suggested to be physiologically distributed in the central nervous system and is developmentally regulated by ageing. The level of p75NTR-ECD is significantly reduced in the brains of AD subjects and mice, likely due to the A&#x003b2;-induced reduction in the expression and activity of TACE.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">10</xref></sup> These findings suggest that p75NTR-ECD could be one of the endogenous protective mechanisms underlying the regulation of A&#x003b2; pathologies and that it likely plays an important role in preventing A&#x003b2;-induced neurotoxicity by protecting neurons from the toxicity of soluble A&#x003b2; and A&#x003b2; oligomers.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">11</xref></sup> However, to date, whether and to what extent the serum and cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) levels of soluble p75NTR-ECD change in patients with AD are not well documented, and the association of changes between p75NTR-ECD and cognition is also unknown.</p><p>Accordingly, we determined the concentrations of p75NTR-ECD in the serum of four groups of subjects including an AD group, Parkinson disease (PD) group (as a neurodegeneration disease control), an acute ischemic stroke group (as a cerebrovascular disease control) and age-matched elderly controls without neurologic disorders (EC), as well as the concentrations of CSF p75NTR-ECD in a subset within the AD and EC groups. We also detected A&#x003b2;40, A&#x003b2;42, total tau and phosphorylated tau (ptau181) levels in the serum and CSF of the AD and EC groups. We further investigated the association between cognitive functions and the level of p75NTR-ECD in the CSF and serum and then explored the utility of serum/CSF p75NTR-ECD alone or combined with other AD biomarkers for discriminating AD from other diseases.</p></sec><sec><title>Materials and methods</title><sec><title>Subjects</title><p>This study was carried out on patients with AD, PD, acute ischemic stroke and EC. Participants with AD (<italic>n</italic>=156), PD (<italic>n</italic>=79) and stroke (<italic>n</italic>=83), and EC (<italic>n</italic>=129) were recruited from the department of neurology and the health examination centre of Daping Hospital. All AD subjects participating in this study met the clinical diagnostic criteria for probable AD according to the National Institute of Neurological and Communicative Disorders and Stroke&#x02013;Alzheimer's disease and Related Disorders Association and DSM-IV criteria for dementia of the Alzheimer type. PD diagnosis was on the basis of the UK PD Society Brain Bank clinical diagnostic criteria, and each patient with PD was diagnosed by at least two specialists with &#x0003e;4 years of clinical experience on movement disorders. Patients with first-ever acute ischemic stroke were fully conscious and could cooperate with investigators to complete neurologic and neuropsychological examinations. The elderly controls consisted of subjects who had no history or signs of neurologic disorders in the clinical examination. The subjects per group were not eligible if they had (1) severe cardiac, pulmonary, hepatic or renal diseases or any type of tumour or (2) declined to participate in the study.</p><p>Clinical data were collected, including age, education, gender, comorbidities (for example, hyperlipidaemia, hypertension and diabetes mellitus) and the scores of multiple scales, such as mini-mental state examination (MMSE), clinical dementia rating (CDR) and activities of daily living (ADL). The scales mentioned above were conducted following our previous protocols,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">13</xref></sup> and the evaluation on PD patients was performed in the clinical 'on' state. The study was approved by the Institutional Review Board of Daping Hospital and registered in the Chinese Clinical Trial Registry (No. ChiCTR-OCC-12001966). Informed consent was acquired from all subjects or, if needed, from authorized caregivers.</p></sec><sec><title>Sample collection</title><p>Blood samples were collected from fasting participants and then centrifuged at 2000&#x02009;<italic>g</italic> at 4&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for 10&#x02009;min. Serum was separated, and aliquots were stored at &#x02212;80&#x02009;&#x000b0;C until assayed. Some of the subjects underwent lumbar puncture (AD, <italic>n</italic>=25; EC, <italic>n</italic>=26). The CSF samples were centrifuged at 2000&#x02009;<italic>g</italic> at 4&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for 10&#x02009;min to eliminate cells, and the aliquots were then immediately frozen and stored at &#x02212;80&#x02009;&#x000b0;C until biochemical analyses.</p></sec><sec><title>ApoE genotyping</title><p>ApoE genotyping in AD and elderly control groups was performed via EDTA blood samples. ApoE genotypes (rs429358 and rs7412) were determined with the restriction fragment length polymorphism method. The PCR reactions were performed with 1&#x02009;&#x003bc;l DNA sample, 1 &#x000d7; GC-I buffer (TaKaRa, Kusatsu, Japan), 2.0&#x02009;m<sc>M</sc> Mg<sup>2&#x0002b;</sup>, 0.2&#x02009;m<sc>M</sc> dNTP (Generay Biotech, Shanghai, China), 1U HotStarTaq polymerase (Qiagen, Hilden, Germany), 2&#x02009;&#x003bc;l multiple PCR primers (Sangon, Shanghai, China) and ddH<sub>2</sub>O in a total volume of 10&#x02009;&#x003bc;l. The cycling program was the same as described previously.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">14</xref></sup> The digestion of endonuclease was performed with AflIII or HaeII (New England Biolabs, Ipswich, MA, USA) for rs429358 or rs7412, respectively. Then, the products were analyzed with an ABI3130XL sequencer (Applied Biosystems, Waltham, MA, USA).</p></sec><sec><title>ELISA assays of A&#x003b2;40, A&#x003b2;42, total tau, ptau181 and p75NTR-ECD</title><p>Enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA) kits were used to determine the serum and CSF levels of A&#x003b2;40 (SIG-38950, Covance, Emeryville, CA, USA), A&#x003b2;42 (SIG-38953, Covance), total tau (KUB0041, Invitrogen, Waltham, MA, USA) and ptau181 (KUO0631, Invitrogen) according to the manufacturer's instructions. For A&#x003b2; measurement, serum and CSF samples were diluted to 1:24 and 1:3, respectively. For tau measurement, both serum and CSF samples were diluted to 1;1. To detect the serum and CSF levels of p75NTR-ECD, a human nerve growth factor receptor ELISA kit (R&#x00026;D, Minneapolis, MN, USA) was used. Briefly, MaxiSorp 96-well plates were coated overnight with 2.0&#x02009;&#x003bc;g&#x02009;ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> to capture the antibody at room temperature (RT) and then incubated with blocking buffer (5&#x00025; bovine serum albumin in phosphate-buffered saline with 1&#x00025; Tween-20) for 2&#x02009;h at RT. Standards and samples (1:3 dilution) were prepared, and 100&#x02009;&#x003bc;l of the standards or samples were added into the wells and then incubated for 2&#x02009;h at RT. After washing, the plates were treated with 100&#x02009;ml per well detection antibody (biotinylated goat anti-human nerve growth factor receptor IgG) at 200&#x02009;ng&#x02009;ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> in blocking buffer for 1&#x02009;h at RT. The plates were washed again and incubated with 100&#x02009;ml per well Streptavidin-horseradish peroxidase in a 1:200 dilution for 1&#x02009;h at RT. After a final wash, colour was developed via tetramethylbenzidine for 30&#x02009;min. The plates were read at 450&#x02009;nm using a microplate reader. The concentration of p75NTR-ECD was determined from a standard curve based on reference standards. The lowest detection limit was 1&#x02009;pg&#x02009;ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>. For all ELISA tests, samples and standards were measured in duplicate, and the means of the duplicates were used for statistical analyses.</p></sec><sec><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>Data analyses were performed using SPSS (version 16, IBM, Armonk, NY, USA). The continuous variables were first assessed for normal distribution using the one-sample Kolmogorov&#x02013;Smirnov test. Statistical comparisons of continuous variables among multiple groups were tested using a one-way analysis of variance test (for normal distributions) or a nonparametric Kruskal&#x02013;Wallis test (for a non-normal distribution) as appropriate. Comparisons of continuous variables between two groups were performed using the independent-sample <italic>t</italic>-test or Mann&#x02013;Whitney <italic>U</italic>-test, as applicable. The comparisons of categorical variables between groups were performed using Fisher's exact test or the <italic>&#x003c7;</italic><sup>2</sup>-test. The AD patients were divided into three subsets according to their MMSE scores: MMSE&#x02a7d;10, MMSE=11&#x02013;20 and MMSE&#x02a7e;21, and the trend test was performed. Correlations between the p75NTR-ECD level and the scale scores and levels of A&#x003b2; and tau were analysed with Pearson or Spearman correlation analysis and partial correlation analysis with adjustment for age, education, sex and comorbidities. Optimal sensitivity and specificity were determined via the receiver operating characteristic (ROC) curve analysis utilising a nonparametric approach. The Youden index was calculated for each cutoff value as the corresponding [(sensitivity&#x0002b;specificity)&#x02212;1] to determine the cutoff values that maximised the discriminating power of the test. The results are expressed as means&#x000b1;s.d. The statistical threshold was fixed at <italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.05.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Results</title><sec><title>Characteristics of the study subjects</title><p>The details of demographic and clinical data of subjects with serum samples in the four groups are summarized in <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. There were no significant differences in age, education, sex, hyperlipidaemia or hypertension between the four groups. Consistent with previous studies,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">15</xref></sup> there was a higher occurrence of diabetes in the AD group compared with the other groups. As expected, AD patients had significantly lower MMSE scores and higher CDR and ADL scores than the other groups. The distribution of the ApoE&#x0025b;4 allele between AD and EC was significantly different. Additionally, the levels of four serum biomarkers (A&#x003b2;42, A&#x003b2;40, total tau and ptau181) in the AD group were significantly higher than their counterparts in the EC group.</p><p>The demographic and clinical information (including CSF levels of A&#x003b2;42, A&#x003b2;40, total tau and ptau181) of subjects with CSF samples (AD, <italic>n</italic>=25; EC, <italic>n</italic>=26) are presented in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Table 1</xref>. There were no differences in age, sex, comorbidities or ApoE&#x0025b;4 allele state between the two subset groups. Compared with EC participants, AD patients had lower education (<italic>P</italic>=0.01) and MMSE score (<italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.001). In terms of CSF biomarkers, AD patients had higher levels of total tau and ptau181 and lower levels of A&#x003b2;42 than the EC participants. The CSF levels of A&#x003b2;40 in AD were comparable with that in the EC group.</p></sec><sec><title>p75NTR-ECD levels in the serum and CSF of different groups</title><p>There was a significant difference in the serum levels of p75NTR-ECD among the groups (F=22.211, <italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.001; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1a</xref>). <italic>Post hoc</italic> tests revealed that the serum p75NTR-ECD level in the AD group (49.14&#x000b1;24.53&#x02009;pg&#x02009;ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) was significantly higher than that in the EC (29.36&#x000b1;20.21&#x02009;pg&#x02009;ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>), PD (33.36&#x000b1;11.35&#x02009;pg&#x02009;ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) and stroke (35.17&#x000b1;25.39&#x02009;pg&#x02009;ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) groups. No difference in the serum p75NTR-ECD level was found between EC and PD (<italic>P</italic>=0.571), EC and stroke (<italic>P</italic>=0.228) or PD and stroke (<italic>P</italic>=0.951). The CSF p75NTR-ECD level of the AD group (375.6&#x000b1;202.2&#x02009;pg&#x02009;ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) was significantly lower than that of the EC group (661.7&#x000b1;248.2&#x02009;pg&#x02009;ml&#x02212;1; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1b</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Correlation of p75NTR-ECD with A&#x003b2; and tau</title><p>The results of correlation analyses of p75NTR-ECD with A&#x003b2;40, A&#x003b2;42, ptau181 and total tau are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2</xref>. The serum p75NTR-ECD was positively correlated with serum A&#x003b2;42 (<italic>r</italic>=0.147, <italic>P</italic>=0.013) and serum ptau181 (<italic>r</italic>=0.183, <italic>P</italic>=0.002), and CSF p75NTR-ECD was negatively correlated with CSF ptau181 and total tau.</p></sec><sec><title>Correlation of p75NTR-ECD with severity of AD</title><p>The correlation of serum p75NTR-ECD levels with the MMSE, CDR and ADL scores was investigated. Results are shown in <xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>. In a model including AD patients and EC subjects, statistical analysis revealed a remarkable negative correlation between the serum p75NTR-ECD level and MMSE scores (<italic>r</italic>=&#x02212;0.472, <italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.001). After adjusting for age, education, sex and comorbidities, the correlation remained significant (<italic>r</italic><sub>adjusted</sub>=&#x02212;0.482, <italic>P</italic><sub>adjusted</sub>&#x0003c;0.001). A similar result was also found for the correlation between the serum p75NTR-ECD level and CDR scores (<italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.001, <italic>P</italic><sub>adjusted</sub>&#x0003c;0.001), indicating that a higher serum level of p75NTR-ECD was associated with a greater cognitive decline. The serum level of p75NTR-ECD was also positively correlated with ADL scores (<italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.001), suggesting that the serum p75NTR-ECD level may reflect the daily living disability. In another model including AD patients only, the serum level of p75NTR-ECD was also significantly correlated with MMSE, CDR and ADL scores (<xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>).</p><p>The CSF p75NTR-ECD level was also correlated with MMSE scores. The lower the CSF p75NTR-ECD level, the higher the severity of cognitive decline (<italic>r</italic>=0.608, <italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.001; <italic>r</italic><sub>adjusted</sub>=0.554, <italic>P</italic><sub>adjusted</sub>&#x0003c;0.001).</p><p>To further investigate whether serum p75NTR-ECD could be used as a predictor of AD progression, we divided AD patients into three subsets according to the MMSE score: MMSE&#x02a7d;10, MMSE=11&#x02013;20 and MMSE&#x02a7e;21, and compared the difference in the p75NTR-ECD level between these three subsets. We found that the serum p75NTR-ECD concentration in the subset of MMSE&#x02a7d;10 was significantly higher than that in MMSE=11&#x02013;20 (<italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.001) or MMSE&#x02a7e;21 (<italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.001; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Figure 1A</xref>). The AD patients in the subset with MMSE&#x02a7d;10 also had a relatively lower CSF p75NTR-ECD level compared with AD patients with MMSE=11&#x02013;20 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Figure 1B</xref>). Trend tests further revealed that, with an increase in MMSE, serum and CSF p75NTR-ECD had a downward and upward trend, respectively (for serum, F=4.273, <italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.027; for CSF, F=18.093, <italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.001).</p></sec><sec><title>Evaluation of p75NTR-ECD as a diagnostic marker for AD</title><p>Given the correlation between p75NTR-ECD and cognitive decline in AD, we investigated whether the measurement of p75NTR-ECD is helpful in diagnosing AD. First, the discriminative value of serum p75NTR-ECD was evaluated. Using the ROC curve analysis, we found that the area under the ROC curve (AUC) of serum p75NTR-ECD in AD versus non-AD (including PD patients, stroke patients and EC subjects) was 0.720 (<italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.001, 95&#x00025; confidence interval=0.666&#x02013;0.774; <xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). When applying the optimal cutoff value of 41.5&#x02009;pg&#x02009;ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> calculated using the Youden index, the overall sensitivity and specificity of serum p75NTR-ECD for distinguishing AD from non-AD was 63.4&#x00025; and 76.3&#x00025;, respectively. Taken separately, the accuracy of serum p75NTR-ECD in AD versus EC, AD versus PD, and AD versus stroke was 72.5&#x00025;, 75.3&#x00025; and 73.7&#x00025;, respectively. Notably, the specificity of serum p75NTR-ECD in AD versus PD was above 90&#x00025; (<xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). The AUC for serum p75NTR-ECD in AD versus EC was 0.752 (95&#x00025; confidence interval=0.695&#x02013;0.808), which was higher than any of the AUC values generated by each of the known serum biomarkers (A&#x003b2;42, A&#x003b2;40, total A&#x003b2;, A&#x003b2;42/A&#x003b2;40, ptau181, total tau, ptau181/A&#x003b2;42 and total tau/A&#x003b2;42; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Table 2</xref>). When combining each of these known serum biomarkers with serum p75NTR-ECD, the AUC value, sensitivity and specificity were all elevated compared with each alone (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Table 3</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3a and b</xref>), indicating that serum p75NTR-ECD has a potential diagnostic value for AD when applied alone or in combination with serum A&#x003b2; and tau.</p><p>The utility of CSF p75NTR-ECD in discriminating AD from EC was also evaluated. The AUC for CSF p75NTR-ECD reached 0.815 (<italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.001, 95&#x00025; confidence interval=0.700&#x02013;0.931), and the sensitivity and specificity were 80.0&#x00025; and 80.8&#x00025;, respectively. When combining CSF p75NTR-ECD with CSF A&#x003b2;42, CSF A&#x003b2;42/40, CSF ptau181 or CSF ptau181/ A&#x003b2;42, the AUCs were above 0.900 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3c and d</xref>), and the accuracies were above 88&#x00025; (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Table 3</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p>The role of p75NTR in AD pathogenesis has been well investigated; however, there are few studies focusing on the potential effects of p75NTR-ECD in AD. In the present study, we determined the concentrations of serum p75NTR-ECD in AD patients, PD patients, stroke patients and in EC, and found that serum p75NTR-ECD is specifically elevated in the AD group, indicating that p75NTR-ECD may benefit in diagnosing AD. Using a regression analysis, we then found that the level of p75NTR-ECD in the serum was strongly correlated with MMSE and CDR scores and had an important differentiating diagnostic value for AD. Moreover, within a subset cohort from which CSF samples were collected, we found that the level of p75NTR-ECD in the CSF was reduced in AD groups compared with elderly controls. Our data suggest that measurements of serum and CSF p75NTR-ECD may be helpful in AD diagnosis.</p><p>p75NTR-ECD, a soluble and diffusible molecule, is physiologically shed by TACE,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">16</xref></sup> and its shedding is considered to be a critical switch event that determines the balance between the enhancement effect on A&#x003b2; production and neurotoxicity of full-length p75NTR and the potential beneficial effect on blocking the toxicity of the A&#x003b2; oligomer of the p75NTR-ECD.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">10</xref></sup> Thus, p75NTR-ECD may be an important modulating molecule in AD pathogenesis. In the present study, we found for we believe the first time that, compared with age-matched controls, only the AD group demonstrated a higher serum p75NTR-ECD level among three disease groups (AD, PD and stroke), indicating that this change was likely to be AD-specific. Why the p75NTR-ECD level in serum was elevated in AD is not known. It may be due to the alteration of plasma TACE activity. Plasma TACE activity in subjects with mild cognitive impairment and patients with AD is known to be increased.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">19</xref></sup> Because TACE is the main cleaving enzyme of p75NTR,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">20</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">21</xref></sup> it is reasonable to suggest that a higher TACE activity would generate a higher level of p75NTR-ECD in the serum in AD. p75NTR is not only expressed in the central nervous system but also in the peripheral nervous system,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">22</xref></sup> liver,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">23</xref></sup> skeletal muscle,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">24</xref></sup> white adipose tissue<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">25</xref></sup> and lymphocytes.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">26</xref></sup> Considering that A&#x003b2; can trigger the upregulation of p75NTR,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">27</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">28</xref></sup> it is possible that the increased A&#x003b2; in the periphery upregulates the expression of p75NTR in these peripheral tissues, which would thereby increase the circulating p75NTR-ECD level in parallel with the full-length p75NTR. Whether the full-length p75NTR in blood cells is increased in AD requires further investigation. Paradoxically, we also found a reduction in CSF p75NTR-ECD in AD patients. A&#x003b2; and other neurodegenerative ligands, such as prion protein, are known to induce the endocytosis of TACE and reduction in TACE activity via PDK1 activation in the AD brain.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">29</xref></sup> A&#x003b2; accumulation in the AD brain could conceivably reduce TACE activity, which leads to the reduction of p75NTR shedding and the reduction of the p75NTR-ECD level in the CSF of AD subjects.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">10</xref></sup></p><p>The findings of the present study showed a parallel change in p75NTR-ECD and A&#x003b2; in the CSF and serum of AD subjects. Soluble A&#x003b2;40 and 42 are well known to be decreased in CSF<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">19</xref></sup> and increased in the peripheral blood,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">30</xref></sup> which represent changes that are used for diagnosing AD.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">31</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">32</xref></sup> We found here that the p75NTR-ECD level is also reduced in the CSF and increased in the serum, and that both phenomena have diagnostic significance and are sensitive and specific as A&#x003b2;. This discovery is not only significant for determining AD diagnosis but also links the neurotrophic hypothesis with the amyloid hypothesis in AD. The mechanism underlying the parallel changes in A&#x003b2; and p75NTR-ECD remains unclear; however, p75NTR-ECD can bind with A&#x003b2;,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">33</xref></sup> and both full-length p75NTR and p75NTR-ECD affect A&#x003b2; metabolism.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">9</xref></sup> Thus, these two events may be interdependent in AD pathogenesis. Here, we propose that the aberrant metabolism of p75NTR-ECD in CSF may disrupt the steady state of A&#x003b2; in CSF and subsequently promote the abnormal deposition of A&#x003b2; in brains and, as a result, decrease the soluble A&#x003b2; in the CSF. On the other hand, the overproduction of A&#x003b2; in the AD brain interferes with the shedding of p75NTR-ECD, resulting in a reduced amount of p75NTR-ECD in CSF. To date, the mechanism linking A&#x003b2; with tau remains unclear. In the present study, we found that p75NTR-ECD is significantly correlated with ptau181 both in the serum and CSF. In light of the role of p75NTR-ECD in A&#x003b2; metabolism, this phenomenon may imply that p75NTR-ECD is a mediator linking A&#x003b2; with tau. Taken together, p75NTR-ECD provides a novel perspective into AD pathogenesis. This perspective indicates that p75NTR-ECD is a promising therapeutic target and diagnostic marker for AD.</p><p>Although knowledge on neuroimaging biomarkers has greatly increased,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">34</xref></sup> biomarkers from the serum or CSF are also required to improve the diagnostic sensitivity and specificity and monitor AD progression.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">35</xref></sup> Our data showed that p75NTR-ECD levels are strongly associated with MMSE and CDR scores, implying that p75NTR-ECD, as a novel biomarker, may be useful in distinguishing AD from other diseases. Applying the Youden index method, we found that the serum p75NTR-ECD level had a diagnostic accuracy of ~70&#x00025;, and that CSF p75NTR-ECD had an accuracy of ~80&#x00025;. The application of p75NTR-ECD alone or in combination with other biomarkers can be used to strongly supplement classical biochemical and neuroimaging markers in the diagnosis of AD. Of note, because p75NTR-ECD correlates with the severity of AD, measurements of p75NTR-ECD levels may be of great use in monitoring AD progression in clinical trials and could be used as an early predictor for the progression from prodromal to AD-type dementia.</p><p>Novel biomarkers for AD have been continuously emerging. N-truncated forms of A&#x003b2; in CSF, such as A&#x003b2; 11&#x02013;40, A&#x003b2; 11&#x02013;42, A&#x003b2; 17&#x02013;40 and A&#x003b2; 17&#x02013;42, have been suggested to have potential diagnostic value in early AD detection and mild cognitive impairment stratification.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">36</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">37</xref></sup> In contrast to these studies, the present study did not focus on the early AD stage, which is widely considered to be a pivotal time for disease-modifying therapies of AD.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">38</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">39</xref></sup> Our future efforts will focus on determining whether serum and CSF p75NTR-ECD levels are predictors of AD in prodromal or mild cognitive impairment populations. Notably, we focused more intensely than other studies on determining the utility and feasibility of serum p75NTR-ECD in discriminating between AD and controls and other diseases. These findings may provide easy and more convenient access to AD diagnosis in relevant studies.</p><p>In summary, AD patients have abnormal p75NTR-ECD profiles. Knowledge of this may provide a novel perspective into AD pathogenesis. The present study indicates substantial diagnostic potential for p75NTR-ECD in AD; a longitudinal study that integrates brain imaging is warranted.</p></sec></body><back><ack><p>This work was supported by the National Natural Science Foundation of China (grant no. 81270423, 30973144, 81200988 and 81000549), the Chongqing Science and Technology Committee (grant no. CSTC2010BA5004 and CSTC2012JJA10111), China Postdoctoral Science Foundation (grant no. 2012M521861 and 2013T60955) and the Chongqing Postdoctoral Science Foundation (grant no. Xm201342).</p></ack><fn-group><fn><p><xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Information</xref> accompanies the paper on the Translational Psychiatry website (http://www.nature.com/tp)</p></fn></fn-group><notes><p>The authors declare no conflict of interest.</p></notes><ref-list><ref id="bib1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Hebert LE, Scherr PA, Bienias JL, Bennett DA, Evans DA. <article-title>Alzheimer disease in the US population: prevalence estimates using the 2000 census</article-title>. <source>Arch Neurol</source>
<year>2003</year>; <volume>60</volume>: <fpage>1119</fpage>&#x02013;1122.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12925369</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Kalaria RN, Maestre GE, Arizaga R, Friedland RP, Galasko D, Hall K et al. <article-title>Alzheimer's disease and vascular dementia in developing countries: prevalence, management, and risk factors</article-title>. <source>Lancet Neurol</source>
<year>2008</year>; <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>812</fpage>&#x02013;826.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18667359</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Costantini C, Scrable H, Puglielli L. <article-title>An aging pathway controls the TrkA to p75NTR receptor switch and amyloid beta-peptide generation</article-title>. <source>EMBO J</source>
<year>2006</year>; <volume>25</volume>: <fpage>1997</fpage>&#x02013;2006.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16619032</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Sotthibundhu A, Sykes AM, Fox B, Underwood CK, Thangnipon W, Coulson EJ. <article-title>Beta-amyloid(1-42) induces neuronal death through the p75 neurotrophin receptor</article-title>. <source>J Neurosci</source>
<year>2008</year>; <volume>28</volume>: <fpage>3941</fpage>&#x02013;3946.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18400893</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Perini G, Della-Bianca V, Politi V, Della Valle G, Dal-Pra I, Rossi F et al. <article-title>Role of p75 neurotrophin receptor in the neurotoxicity by beta-amyloid peptides and synergistic effect of inflammatory cytokines</article-title>. <source>J Exp Med</source>
<year>2002</year>; <volume>195</volume>: <fpage>907</fpage>&#x02013;918.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11927634</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Knowles JK, Rajadas J, Nguyen TV, Yang T, LeMieux MC, Vander Griend L et al. <article-title>The p75 neurotrophin receptor promotes amyloid-beta(1-42)-induced neuritic dystrophy <italic>in vitro</italic> and <italic>in vivo</italic></article-title>. <source>J Neurosci</source>
<year>2009</year>; <volume>29</volume>: <fpage>10627</fpage>&#x02013;10637.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19710315</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Saez ET, Pehar M, Vargas MR, Barbeito L, Maccioni RB. <article-title>Production of nerve growth factor by beta-amyloid-stimulated astrocytes induces p75NTR-dependent tau hyperphosphorylation in cultured hippocampal neurons</article-title>. <source>J Neurosci Res</source>
<year>2006</year>; <volume>84</volume>: <fpage>1098</fpage>&#x02013;1106.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16862561</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Yang T, Knowles JK, Lu Q, Zhang H, Arancio O, Moore LA et al. <article-title>Small molecule, non-peptide p75 ligands inhibit Abeta-induced neurodegeneration and synaptic impairment</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>
<year>2008</year>; <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>e3604</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18978948</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Wang YJ, Wang X, Lu JJ, Li QX, Gao CY, Liu XH et al. <article-title>p75NTR regulates Abeta deposition by increasing Abeta production but inhibiting Abeta aggregation with its extracellular domain</article-title>. <source>J Neurosci</source>
<year>2011</year>; <volume>31</volume>: <fpage>2292</fpage>&#x02013;2304.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21307265</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Yao XQ, Jiao SS, Saadipour K, Zeng F, Wang QH, Zhu C et al. <article-title>p75NTR ectodomain is a physiological neuroprotective molecule against amyloid-beta toxicity in the brain of Alzheimer's disease</article-title>. <source>Mol Psychiatry</source>
<year>2015</year>; e-pub of print 28 April 2015; doi:10.1038/mp.2015.49.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Zhou XF, Wang YJ. <article-title>The p75NTR extracellular domain: a potential molecule regulating the solubility and removal of amyloid-beta</article-title>. <source>Prion</source>
<year>2011</year>; <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>161</fpage>&#x02013;163.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21814043</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Wang JY, Zhou DH, Li J, Zhang M, Deng J, Tang M et al. <article-title>Leisure activity and risk of cognitive impairment: the Chongqing aging study</article-title>. <source>Neurology</source>
<year>2006</year>; <volume>66</volume>: <fpage>911</fpage>&#x02013;913.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16291928</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Li J, Wang YJ, Zhang M, Xu ZQ, Gao CY, Fang CQ et al. <article-title>Vascular risk factors promote conversion from mild cognitive impairment to Alzheimer disease</article-title>. <source>Neurology</source>
<year>2011</year>; <volume>76</volume>: <fpage>1485</fpage>&#x02013;1491.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21490316</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Zeng F, Zou HQ, Zhou HD, Li J, Wang L, Cao HY et al. <article-title>The relationship between single nucleotide polymorphisms of the NTRK2 gene and sporadic Alzheimer's disease in the Chinese Han population</article-title>. <source>Neurosci Lett</source>
<year>2013</year>; <volume>550</volume>: <fpage>55</fpage>&#x02013;59.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23831349</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Milone M. <article-title>Mitochondria, diabetes, and Alzheimer's disease</article-title>. <source>Diabetes</source>
<year>2012</year>; <volume>61</volume>: <fpage>991</fpage>&#x02013;992.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22517655</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Weskamp G, Schlondorff J, Lum L, Becherer JD, Kim TW, Saftig P et al. <article-title>Evidence for a critical role of the tumor necrosis factor alpha convertase (TACE) in ectodomain shedding of the p75 neurotrophin receptor (p75NTR)</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>
<year>2004</year>; <volume>279</volume>: <fpage>4241</fpage>&#x02013;4249.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14638693</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Sun Q, Hampel H, Blennow K, Lista S, Levey A, Tang B et al. <article-title>Increased plasma TACE activity in subjects with mild cognitive impairment and patients with Alzheimer's disease</article-title>. <source>J Alzheimers Dis</source>
<year>2014</year>; <volume>41</volume>: <fpage>877</fpage>&#x02013;886.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24685635</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Bai L, Song N, Yu J, Tan L, Shen Y, Xie J et al. <article-title>Elevated plasma levels of soluble TNFRs and TACE activity in Alzheimer's disease patients of Northern Han Chinese descent</article-title>. <source>Curr Alzheimer Res</source>
<year>2013</year>; <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>57</fpage>&#x02013;62.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23368432</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Zhang J, Jia J, Qin W, Wang S. <article-title>Combination of plasma tumor necrosis factor receptors signaling proteins, beta-amyloid and apolipoprotein E for the detection of Alzheimer's disease</article-title>. <source>Neurosci Lett</source>
<year>2013</year>; <volume>541</volume>: <fpage>99</fpage>&#x02013;104.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23500026</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Zampieri N, Xu CF, Neubert TA, Chao MV. <article-title>Cleavage of p75 neurotrophin receptor by alpha-secretase and gamma-secretase requires specific receptor domains</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>
<year>2005</year>; <volume>280</volume>: <fpage>14563</fpage>&#x02013;14571.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15701642</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Kenchappa RS, Zampieri N, Chao MV, Barker PA, Teng HK, Hempstead BL et al. <article-title>Ligand-dependent cleavage of the P75 neurotrophin receptor is necessary for NRIF nuclear translocation and apoptosis in sympathetic neurons</article-title>. <source>Neuron</source>
<year>2006</year>; <volume>50</volume>: <fpage>219</fpage>&#x02013;232.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16630834</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Zhou XF, Li HY. <article-title>Roles of glial p75NTR in axonal regeneration</article-title>. <source>J Neurosci Res</source>
<year>2007</year>; <volume>85</volume>: <fpage>1601</fpage>&#x02013;1605.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17335080</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Passino MA, Adams RA, Sikorski SL, Akassoglou K. <article-title>Regulation of hepatic stellate cell differentiation by the neurotrophin receptor p75NTR</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<year>2007</year>; <volume>315</volume>: <fpage>1853</fpage>&#x02013;1856.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17395831</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Deponti D, Buono R, Catanzaro G, De Palma C, Longhi R, Meneveri R et al. <article-title>The low-affinity receptor for neurotrophins p75NTR plays a key role for satellite cell function in muscle repair acting via RhoA</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Cell</source>
<year>2009</year>; <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>3620</fpage>&#x02013;3627.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19553472</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Baeza-Raja B, Li P, Le Moan N, Sachs BD, Schachtrup C, Davalos D et al. <article-title>p75 neurotrophin receptor regulates glucose homeostasis and insulin sensitivity</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>
<year>2012</year>; <volume>109</volume>: <fpage>5838</fpage>&#x02013;5843.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22460790</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Zhou L, Xiong J, Lim Y, Ruan Y, Huang C, Zhu Y et al. <article-title>Upregulation of blood proBDNF and its receptors in major depression</article-title>. <source>J Affect Disord</source>
<year>2013</year>; <volume>150</volume>: <fpage>776</fpage>&#x02013;784.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23537780</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Chakravarthy B, Gaudet C, Menard M, Atkinson T, Brown L, Laferla FM et al. <article-title>Amyloid-beta peptides stimulate the expression of the p75(NTR) neurotrophin receptor in SHSY5Y human neuroblastoma cells and AD transgenic mice</article-title>. <source>J Alzheimers Dis</source>
<year>2010</year>; <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>915</fpage>&#x02013;925.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20157247</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Ito S, Menard M, Atkinson T, Gaudet C, Brown L, Whitfield J et al. <article-title>Involvement of insulin-like growth factor 1 receptor signaling in the amyloid-beta peptide oligomers-induced p75 neurotrophin receptor protein expression in mouse hippocampus</article-title>. <source>J Alzheimers Dis</source>
<year>2012</year>; <volume>31</volume>: <fpage>493</fpage>&#x02013;506.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22635104</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Pietri M, Dakowski C, Hannaoui S, Alleaume-Butaux A, Hernandez-Rapp J, Ragagnin A et al. <article-title>PDK1 decreases TACE-mediated alpha-secretase activity and promotes disease progression in prion and Alzheimer's diseases</article-title>. <source>Nat Med</source>
<year>2013</year>; <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>1124</fpage>&#x02013;1131.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23955714</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Chiu MJ, Yang SY, Horng HE, Yang CC, Chen TF, Chieh JJ et al. <article-title>Combined plasma biomarkers for diagnosing mild cognition impairment and Alzheimer's disease</article-title>. <source>ACS Chem Neurosci</source>
<year>2013</year>; <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>1530</fpage>&#x02013;1536.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24090201</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Koyama A, Okereke OI, Yang T, Blacker D, Selkoe DJ, Grodstein F. <article-title>Plasma amyloid-beta as a predictor of dementia and cognitive decline: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Arch Neurol</source>
<year>2012</year>; <volume>69</volume>: <fpage>824</fpage>&#x02013;831.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22451159</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Shi J. <article-title>Fluctuations of CSF amyloid-beta levels: implications for a diagnostic and therapeutic biomarker</article-title>. <source>Neurology</source>
<year>2007</year>; <volume>69</volume>: <fpage>1063</fpage>&#x02013;1064.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17785679</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Yaar M, Zhai S, Pilch PF, Doyle SM, Eisenhauer PB, Fine RE et al. <article-title>Binding of beta-amyloid to the p75 neurotrophin receptor induces apoptosis. A possible mechanism for Alzheimer's disease</article-title>. <source>J Clin Invest</source>
<year>1997</year>; <volume>100</volume>: <fpage>2333</fpage>&#x02013;2340.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9410912</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Jack CR Jr, Barrio JR, Kepe V. <article-title>Cerebral amyloid PET imaging in Alzheimer's disease</article-title>. <source>Acta Neuropathol</source>
<year>2013</year>; <volume>126</volume>: <fpage>643</fpage>&#x02013;657.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24100688</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Lu H, Zhu XC, Jiang T, Yu JT, Tan L. <article-title>Body fluid biomarkers in Alzheimer's disease</article-title>. <source>Ann Transl Med</source>
<year>2015</year>; <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>70</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25992369</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Ranaldi S, Caillava C, Prome S, Rubrecht L, Cobo S, Salvetat N et al. <article-title>N-truncated Abeta peptides in complex fluids unraveled by new specific immunoassays</article-title>. <source>Neurobiol Aging</source>
<year>2013</year>; <volume>34</volume>: <fpage>523</fpage>&#x02013;539.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22738722</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Abraham JD, Prome S, Salvetat N, Rubrecht L, Cobo S, du Paty E et al. <article-title>Cerebrospinal Abeta11-x and 17-x levels as indicators of mild cognitive impairment and patients' stratification in Alzheimer's disease</article-title>. <source>Transl Psychiatry</source>
<year>2013</year>; <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>e281</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23860482</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Mangialasche F, Solomon A, Winblad B, Mecocci P, Kivipelto M. <article-title>Alzheimer's disease: clinical trials and drug development</article-title>. <source>Lancet Neurol</source>
<year>2010</year>; <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>702</fpage>&#x02013;716.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20610346</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Smith AD. <article-title>Why are drug trials in Alzheimer's disease failing</article-title>? <source>Lancet</source>
<year>2010</year>; <volume>376</volume>: <fpage>1466</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21036274</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="sup1"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="xob1"><label>Supplementary Information</label><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="tp2015146x1.doc"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></back><floats-group><fig id="fig1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Ectodomain of p75 neurotrophin receptor (p75NTR-ECD) levels of serum and cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) in different groups. (<bold>a</bold>) Comparison of serum p75NTR-ECD levels among EC, AD patients, PD patients and stroke patients [means&#x000b1;s.e.m., one-way analysis of variance (ANOVA), Tukey's test, &#x0002a;&#x0002a;<italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.01]. (<bold>b</bold>) Comparison of CSF p75NTR-ECD levels between EC and patients with AD (means&#x000b1;s.e.m., Student's <italic>t-</italic>test, &#x0002a;&#x0002a;<italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.01). AD, Alzheimer's disease; EC, elderly controls without neurologic disorders; PD, Parkinson disease.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="tp2015146f1"/></fig><fig id="fig2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>The correlation analyses of serum or cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) ectodomain of p75 neurotrophin receptor (p75NTR-ECD) with other biomarkers. (<bold>a</bold>&#x02013;<bold>d</bold>) The correlation of serum p75NTR-ECD with serum A&#x003b2;40 (<bold>a</bold>), serum A&#x003b2;42 (<bold>b</bold>), serum ptau181 (<bold>c</bold>) and serum total tau (<bold>d</bold>). (<bold>e</bold>&#x02013;<bold>h</bold>) The correlation of CSF p75NTR-ECD with CSF A&#x003b2;40 (<bold>e</bold>), CSF A&#x003b2;42 (<bold>f</bold>), CSF ptau181 (<bold>g</bold>) and CSF total tau (<bold>h</bold>).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="tp2015146f2"/></fig><fig id="fig3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Receiver operating characteristic (ROC) curve of serum and cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) ectodomain of p75 neurotrophin receptor (p75NTR-ECD) alone or in combination with other biomarkers. (<bold>a</bold>) The ROC curve of serum p75NTR-ECD and other serum biomarkers. (<bold>b</bold>) The ROC curve of serum p75NTR-ECD in combination with other biomarkers. (<bold>c</bold>) The ROC curve of CSF p75NTR-ECD and other CSF biomarkers. (<bold>d</bold>) The ROC curve of CSF p75NTR-ECD in combination with other CSF biomarkers.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="tp2015146f3"/></fig><table-wrap id="tbl1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Demographic and clinical characteristics of patients in four groups (serum samples)</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1"><colgroup><col align="left"/><col align="char" char="&#x000b1;"/><col align="char" char="&#x000b1;"/><col align="char" char="&#x000b1;"/><col align="char" char="&#x000b1;"/><col align="char" char="."/></colgroup><thead valign="bottom"><tr><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><italic>Variables</italic></th><th align="center" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;" charoff="50"><italic>EC,</italic> n=<italic>129</italic></th><th align="center" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;" charoff="50"><italic>AD,</italic> n=<italic>156</italic></th><th align="center" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;" charoff="50"><italic>PD,</italic> n=<italic>79</italic></th><th align="center" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;" charoff="50"><italic>Stroke,</italic> n=<italic>83</italic></th><th align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">P-<italic>value</italic></th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Age, years, means&#x000b1;s.d.</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;" charoff="50">71.7&#x000b1;9.6</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;" charoff="50">70.8&#x000b1;15.2</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;" charoff="50">68.6&#x000b1;8.0</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;" charoff="50">69.8&#x000b1;9.9</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.272</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Education, years, means&#x000b1;s.d.</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;" charoff="50">11.5&#x000b1;3.9</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;" charoff="50">8.2&#x000b1;4.2</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;" charoff="50">10.7&#x000b1;4.7</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;" charoff="50">11.1&#x000b1;4.1</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.568</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Female gender, <italic>n</italic> (&#x00025;)</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;" charoff="50">53 (41.1)</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;" charoff="50">83 (53.2)</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;" charoff="50">43 (54.4)</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;" charoff="50">39 (47.0)</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.145</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">MMSE score, means&#x000b1;s.d.</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;" charoff="50">28.0&#x000b1;2.0</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;" charoff="50">13.6&#x000b1;6.7</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;" charoff="50">26.0&#x000b1;3.8</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;" charoff="50">27.0&#x000b1;3.8</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x0003c;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">CDR score, means&#x000b1;s.d.</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;" charoff="50">0.0&#x000b1;0.0</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;" charoff="50">2.0&#x000b1;1.2</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;" charoff="50">0.2&#x000b1;0.5</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;" charoff="50">0.1&#x000b1;0.2</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x0003c;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">ADL score, means&#x000b1;s.d.</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;" charoff="50">20.8&#x000b1;2.2</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;" charoff="50">48.1&#x000b1;19.4</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;" charoff="50">23.0&#x000b1;6.9</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;" charoff="50">32.0&#x000b1;8.5</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x0003c;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Hyperlipidaemia, <italic>n</italic> (&#x00025;)</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;" charoff="50">30 (23.2)</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;" charoff="50">28 (17.9)</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;" charoff="50">19 (24.1)</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;" charoff="50">22 (26.5)</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.278</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Hypertension, <italic>n</italic> (&#x00025;)</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;" charoff="50">55 (42.6)</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;" charoff="50">54 (34.6)</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;" charoff="50">23 (29.1)</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;" charoff="50">32 (38.5)</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.228</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Diabetes mellitus, <italic>n</italic> (&#x00025;)</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;" charoff="50">14 (10.9)</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;" charoff="50">32 (20.5)</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;" charoff="50">6 (8.1)</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;" charoff="50">10 (12.0)</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.047</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">ApoE&#x0025b;4 carrier, <italic>n</italic> (&#x00025;)</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;" charoff="50">30 (23.3)</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;" charoff="50">63 (40.4)</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;" charoff="50">&#x02014;</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;" charoff="50">&#x02014;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.002</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Heterozygote, <italic>n</italic> (&#x00025;)</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;" charoff="50">30 (23.3)</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;" charoff="50">51 (32.7)</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;" charoff="50">&#x02014;</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;" charoff="50">&#x02014;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.079</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Homozygote, <italic>n</italic> (&#x00025;)</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;" charoff="50">0.0 (0.0)</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;" charoff="50">12 (7.7)</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;" charoff="50">&#x02014;</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;" charoff="50">&#x02014;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Serum A&#x003b2;40 (pg&#x02009;ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>), means&#x000b1;s.d.</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;" charoff="50">60.2&#x000b1;34.7</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;" charoff="50">86.2&#x000b1;55.5</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;" charoff="50">&#x02014;</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;" charoff="50">&#x02014;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x0003c;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Serum A&#x003b2;42 (pg&#x02009;ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>), means&#x000b1;s.d.</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;" charoff="50">49.3&#x000b1;27.7</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;" charoff="50">68.4&#x000b1;61.9</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;" charoff="50">&#x02014;</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;" charoff="50">&#x02014;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Serum total tau (pg&#x02009;ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>), means&#x000b1;s.d.</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;" charoff="50">181.0&#x000b1;103.2</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;" charoff="50">227.1&#x000b1;102.2</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;" charoff="50">&#x02014;</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;" charoff="50">&#x02014;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x0003c;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Serum ptau<sub>181</sub> (pg&#x02009;ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>), means&#x000b1;s.d.</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;" charoff="50">107.1&#x000b1;57.8</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;" charoff="50">150.8&#x000b1;57.70</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;" charoff="50">&#x02014;</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;" charoff="50">&#x02014;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x0003c;0.001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="t1-fn1"><p>Abbreviations: AD, Alzheimer's disease; ADL, activities of daily living; CDR, clinical dementia rating; EC, elderly controls without neurologic disorders; MMSE, mini-mental state examination; PD, Parkinson disease.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="tbl2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>The correlation of serum p75NTR-ECD with neuropsychological evaluation score</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1"><colgroup><col align="left"/><col align="char" char="."/><col align="char" char="."/><col align="char" char="."/><col align="char" char="."/><col align="char" char="."/><col align="char" char="."/></colgroup><thead valign="bottom"><tr><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</th><th colspan="3" align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50"><italic>Unadjusted</italic><hr/></th><th colspan="3" align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50"><italic>Adjusted</italic><xref ref-type="fn" rid="t2-fn2">a</xref><hr/></th></tr><tr><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</th><th align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">r-<italic>value</italic></th><th align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50"><italic>95&#x00025; CI</italic></th><th align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">P-<italic>value</italic></th><th align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">r-<italic>value</italic></th><th align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50"><italic>95&#x00025; CI</italic></th><th align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">P-<italic>value</italic></th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td colspan="7" align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><italic>MMSE</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>&#x02003;</bold>Overall</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;0.472</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;0.558&#x02013;&#x02212;0.377</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x0003c;0.001</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;0.482</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;0.592&#x02013;&#x02212;0.364</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x0003c;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><bold>&#x02003;</bold>AD</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;0.363</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;0.492&#x02013;&#x02212;0.219</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x0003c;0.001</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;0.374</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x02212;0.500&#x02013;&#x02212;0.213</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x0003c;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7" align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><italic>CDR</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;Overall</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.457</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.360&#x02013;0.545</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x0003c;0.001</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.460</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.341&#x02013;&#x02212;0.577</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x0003c;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;AD</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.305</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.157&#x02013;0.441</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x0003c;0.001</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.304</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.142&#x02013;0.453</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x0003c;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7" align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><italic>ADL</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;Overall</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.443</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.345&#x02013;0.532</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x0003c;0.001</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.438</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.304&#x02013;0.551</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x0003c;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02003;AD</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.325</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.177&#x02013;0.459</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x0003c;0.001</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.320</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.160&#x02013;0.453</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x0003c;0.001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="t2-fn1"><p>Abbreviations: AD, Alzheimer's disease; ADL, activities of daily living; CDR, clinical dementia rating; CI, confidence interval; MMSE, mini-mental state examination; p75NTR-ECD, ectodomain of p75 neurotrophin receptor.</p></fn><fn id="t2-fn2"><label>a</label><p>Adjusted for age, sex, education, hyperlipidaemia, hypertension and diabetes.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="tbl3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><title>Discriminative values of serum p75NTR-ECD using an ROC curve analysis</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1"><colgroup><col align="left"/><col align="char" char="."/><col align="char" char="."/><col align="char" char="."/><col align="char" char="."/></colgroup><thead valign="bottom"><tr><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><italic>ROC analysis</italic></th><th align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50"><italic>AD versus EC</italic></th><th align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50"><italic>AD versus PD</italic></th><th align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50"><italic>AD versus stroke</italic></th><th align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50"><italic>AD versus non-AD</italic></th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">AUC</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.752</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.689</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.702</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.720</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50"><italic>P</italic>-value</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x0003c;0.001</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x0003c;0.001</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x0003c;0.001</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">&#x0003c;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">95&#x00025; CI</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.695&#x02013;0.808</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.623&#x02013;0.754</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.633&#x02013;0.771</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">0.666&#x02013;0.774</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Cutoff, pg&#x02009;ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup></td><td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">34.2</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">48.6</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">35.8</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">41.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Sensitivity, &#x00025;</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">70.5</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">48.7</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">65.4</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">63.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Specificity, &#x00025;</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">74.4</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">93.7</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">81.9</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">76.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Accuracy, &#x00025;</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">72.5</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">75.3</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">73.7</td><td align="center" valign="top" char="." charoff="50">69.9</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="t3-fn1"><p>Abbreviations: AD, Alzheimer's disease; AUC, area under the ROC; 95&#x00025; CI, 95&#x00025; confidence interval; EC, elderly control without neurologic disorders; PD, Parkinson disease; p75NTR-ECD, ectodomain of p75 neurotrophin receptor; ROC, receiver operating characteristic.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></floats-group></article>